<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Good newes from Canaan Full of heauenly comfort and consolation, for all those that are afflicted either in bodie or minde. With a proofe of true repentance for the same. By William Cowper, minister of Gods word, and B. of Galloway.</title>
            <author>Cowper, William, 1568-1619.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 237 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 150 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B12251</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5919</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114575</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849800</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849800</idno>
            <idno type="VID">177902</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B12251)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177902)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1268:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Good newes from Canaan Full of heauenly comfort and consolation, for all those that are afflicted either in bodie or minde. With a proofe of true repentance for the same. By William Cowper, minister of Gods word, and B. of Galloway.</title>
                  <author>Cowper, William, 1568-1619.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 279, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Stansby for Iohn Budge, and are to be sold at his shops, at the South doore of Pauls, and at Britaines Burse,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms LI --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:177902:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177902:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>GOOD NEVVES <hi>FROM</hi> CANAAN.</p>
            <p>Full of heauenly comfort and conſolation, for all thoſe that <hi>are afflicted either in bodie or minde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With a proofe of true repentance for <hi>the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>William Cowper,</hi> Miniſter of Gods Word, and B. of <hi>Galloway.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>W. Stansby</hi> for <hi>Iohn Budge,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhops, at the South doore of Pauls, <hi>and at Britaines Burſe.</hi> 1613.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:177902:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177902:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPFVLL, IOHN MVRRAY, one of his <hi>Maiesties Bed-Chamber.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Worſhipful, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo far obliged to his Maieſties fauour, as I confeſſe I am ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer able to requite it, I can of dutie doe no leſſe, then with <hi>Dauid,</hi> ſhew ſuch kindnes as I may to <hi>Mephiboſeth,</hi> for <hi>Iona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thans</hi> ſake, that is, take mee to the loweſt, where I cannot reach to the higheſt, endeuouring to loue and honour all ſuch, as I can know are
<pb facs="tcp:177902:3"/> beloued of his Highneſſe, ſpecially whom God hath called to ſerue and attend his Maieſtie, and the more neerely by calling they ſtand in this ſeruice, the more entirely ſhall mine affection be toward the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Among theſe, as God hath honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red you to be one; ſo is there reaſon why theſe, who loue you, ſhould thanke God for you, not ſo much for your place of preferment, as for your fidelity in it, theſe foure and twentie yeares, by which you haue deſerued the commendation of a faithfull ſeruant, and encreaſe of your Maſters fauourable affection towards you.</p>
            <p>It is a common ſpeech, that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliaritie breeds contempt, &amp; moſt excellent things by conſuetude be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the leſſe regarded, but this holds not alwayes true, for of ſuch as are wiſe, a knowne &amp; tried good is liked, euer the longer, the better. And I doe ſo verily thinke of all his Highneſſe loyall ſeruants which at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
<pb facs="tcp:177902:3"/> his Maieſty, that as they know better then others by long experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence the rare qualities, wherewith his Highnes is endued from aboue; ſo they eſteeme much more of his Maieſtie then others can: yet is it not amiſſe they ſhould ſtill be wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened with warnings, who haue ſuch an incomparable iewel in their keeping, as is called by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <hi>The breath of our nostrils;</hi> and in whom, not onely theſe famous kingdoms vnder his Highneſſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, but all the Churches in Chriſtendome haue ſuch intereſt. In the conſeruing of <hi>This one,</hi> in whom vnder God wee are all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued; no circumſpection, no care, no vigilancy, no ſeruice can be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient.</p>
            <p>It was a iuſt imputation of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> to <hi>Abner,</hi> and his fellow Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, that their Maſter, King <hi>Saul</hi> being ſleeping, they were careleſſe of him, and ſuffered <hi>Abiſhai,</hi> who both would and might haue ſlaine
<pb facs="tcp:177902:4"/> him, if <hi>Dauid</hi> had not ſtayed him, to take away his ſpeare, and pot from his head, <hi>Yee are worthie</hi> (ſaid <note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 26. 16.</note> he) <hi>to die, becauſe yee haue not kept your Master, the Lords annointed.</hi> But heere, as there is no compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon betweene that curſed King, and our ſacred Soueraigne: ſo the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perexcellencie of his perſon makes the leaſt omiſſion of any dutiful at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance in ſuch as are called vnto it, a double offence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of where his treaſure was, pointed with his finger to his friends, and domeſtique ſeruants; and indeed, where they are faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, they are ſingular bleſſings of God: for as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>The plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 14. 35</note> 
               <hi>of a King is in a wiſe ſeruant.</hi> And againe, <hi>Righteous lippes are the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 16. 16</note> 
               <hi>delight of Kings, and the King loues him that ſpeakes right things. Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus aut ſeruus fidelis protectio fortis, munitum palatium, viuus the ſaurus:</hi> A faithfull friend or ſeruant, is a
<pb facs="tcp:177902:4"/> ſtrong protection, a fenced palace, a liuing treaſure, ſaid <hi>Nazianzen.</hi> Neither doe I thinke that euer <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nazianzen. Orat.</hi> 22.</note> or any Monarch, or King in the world, did countenance and credit ſuch as ſerue them, more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently and louingly, then the King of Britaine doth ſuch as at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend his Highneſſe, which cannot but oblige euery loyall heart the more carefully and willingly to ſerue his Highnes againe.</p>
            <p>And this, as in regard of your Chriſtian profeſsion is moſt ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for you, it being a duety the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolique Canon requires of all Chriſtian ſeruants, <hi>That they ſhould pleaſe their Masters in all things, ſhewing all good faithfulneſſe, that they may adorne the doctrine of God our Sauiour;</hi> ſo is it alſo fitting for that place wherein ye ſtand in the world, that ye may be anſwerable to that fidelitie in his Highnes ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, for which your Honourable predeceſſors haue beene greatly
<pb facs="tcp:177902:5"/> praiſed before you. For it is known that the honourable houſe of <hi>Coke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poole,</hi> whereof ye are a ſonne, being a principall family of that ancient, populous and flouriſhing tribe of <hi>Murray,</hi> notwithſtanding their dwelling be in a part of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, of olde greatly giuen to miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order, troups of rebels compaſsing them on euery ſide; yet did they ſtill retain the honorable ſtate and faſhions of other honourable hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in the land, their houſe euer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a terror to the euill, a refuge to the good, a barre to the aduerſarie, and a publique example in moſt turbulent times, of loyaltie to their Soueraigne. Thus haue they liued vnſtayned in honour, fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of the worſt ſort, loued of the beſt, euer gratious to their King, neuer blotted with the remiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of any offence done againſt his Crowne, but alway beautified with manifold proofes of their fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delitie in his Highneſſe ſeruice;
<pb facs="tcp:177902:5"/> wherin ſundrie of them haue borne honourable offices both in Court and out of it, vnto this day. And all theſe, by their example prouoke you to leaue the name of that houſe as honourable for your part, as you haue receiued it from them: which as hitherto you haue done, ſo I hope for the time to come it may happely be inlarged, but ſhal neuer be impaired by any deed of yours.</p>
            <p>And hereunto (right worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full) remember it is pietie and the true feare of God muſt aduance you. God hath conioyned theſe two precepts together; <hi>My ſonne</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 24. 21.</note> 
               <hi>feare God and the King:</hi> he cannot keepe the one who violates the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; therefore your loue, feare, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence, and fidelitie toward the King, muſt be grounded on your loue and feare of God. Keepe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way within you a humble heart; for beſide that it is the way to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, it will keep you from falling. Among many priuiledges, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with
<pb facs="tcp:177902:6"/> humilitie indues ſuch as poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe it, this is one, <hi>Humilis non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet vnde cadat.</hi> Thinke frequently vpon your end, make readie ere it come vpon you; it is no wiſedome to begin to prepare, when of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie we muſt remoue. The fooliſh men of the world, <hi>de mortalibus immortalia cogitant,</hi> dreame of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie in mortall things: but looke you to others who haue bin great before you and now are not, and by them learn to be wiſe. Liue at continuall enmitie with ſinne; this is the onely enemie that is able to hurt you; ſubdue it and ye ſhall feare none other. Such ſins as you haue done, vndoe them by godly ſorrow; ſuch as of weakeneſſe you may doe, preuent them with godly care. Keep ſo your Court on earth, that you ſtill learn to be a Courtier in heauen, holy in life, feruent in praier; by theſe hath a man fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with God, and acceſſe to the Throne of the heauenly King, to
<pb facs="tcp:177902:6"/> ſpeake to his Maieſtie when hee pleaſeth. In this holy diſpoſition, if this my little Treatiſe may ſerue any way to confirme you, I ſhall be abundantly contented. I haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated it vnto you as a token of my loue, for the good which is in you toward all that feare God, and your courteous fauour ſhewed to my ſelfe in particular. And ſo hoping that with as good an hart ye will accept it, as I do offer it. I reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your owne in Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> William Cowper, <hi>B. of Galloway.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="quotation">
            <pb facs="tcp:177902:7"/>
            <bibl>
               <hi>ESA.</hi> 1. 18. 19.</bibl>
            <q>
               <p>Come and let vs reaſon toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſaith the Lord: Though your ſinnes were as crimſon, they ſhall bee made white as ſnow: though they were redde like ſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, they ſhall be as wooll.</p>
               <p>If ye conſent and obey, ye ſhall eate the good things of the land.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:177902:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177902:8"/>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:177902:8"/>
            <head>GOOD NEWES From CANAAN.</head>
            <head>My helpe is in the Name of the LORD.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>To him that excelleth. A Pſalme of</hi> DAVID, <hi>when the Prophet</hi> NATHAN <hi>came vnto him, after that hee had gone in vnto Bath-ſheba.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE inſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <note place="margin">This Pſalme is a Pſalme of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and the vſe of it is threefold.</note> of this Pſalme being conſiderede, will let vs ſee that it is a Pſalme of Repentance, made
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:177902:9"/> by <hi>Dauid,</hi> after hee had defiled the wife of <hi>Vriah,</hi> and murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Vriah</hi> him ſelfe. It ſerues vnto vs for this threefold vſe. Firſt, as a preſeruatiue to keepe <note place="margin">1. <hi>A preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue to keep vs that wee ſinne not.</hi>
               </note> vs, that we fall not into the like ſinnes; for why ſhall wee commit that, which we ſee by example of others, will either commit vs to eternall damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or at leaſt breed vs much griefe, paine and dolor, before wee can bee quit of it? This ſinne of <hi>Dauid</hi> thorough Gods mercie, preuailed not againſt him to damnation, yet yee ſee what anguiſh of Spirit, what terrour of minde, what ſighing, what teares, what roaring night and day he ſuſtained, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee could bee deliuered from it, and find himſelfe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:177902:9"/> to his former ioy! thus ſhall all fleſh finde it, that the falles momentarie, and peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing pleaſures of ſinne, ſhall haue ſorrow in the ende. For the motions thereof are like theſe Locuſts of the bottome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe pit, hauing faces of men, and their haire like the haire of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuel.</hi> 9.</note> women, but a taile like a Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion, which ſtingeth vnto the death.</p>
            <p>Next it ſerues as a corrobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiue <note place="margin">2. <hi>A corobora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, to keep ſuch as haue fallen in ſin, from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire.</hi>
               </note> to keepe ſuch as haue fallen into the like ſinnes, that they fall not further into the deepe of deſperation, ſo the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, that the mercie of God ſhewed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 16</note> him after that he had beene a blaſphemer, perſecutor and oppreſſor, was for an enſample
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:177902:10"/> vnto all them, who ſhal in time to come beleeue in Chriſt vnto eternall life. Thus the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God, when they looke to the ſinnes of other Gods Saints recorded in holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, doe not hereby confirme themſelues in ſinne, but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort themſelues againſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire. It is true of them all, <note place="margin">Baſil de paeniten.</note> which <hi>Baſil</hi> ſpake of <hi>Peters</hi> threefold deniall, they are Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtred, <hi>Vt tu quo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> conſolationem haberes,</hi> Let vs meditate vpon the ſinnes of others, as <hi>Bernard</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Bernard.</note> did; <hi>Omnino propter manſuetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem quae in te eſt, domine Ieſu, currimus poſt te, audientes quod non ſpernas pauperem peccatorem, non horruiſti confitentem latro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem non lachrymantem peccatri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem, non Cananaeam ſupplicantem,</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:177902:10"/> 
               <hi>non deprehenſam in adulterio, non ſupplicantem publicanum, non ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantem diſcipulum, non perſequu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torem diſcipulorum: In odore ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum currimus.</hi> Surely LORD IESVS for the meeknes which is in thee, we runne after thee hearing, that thou deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedſt not the poore ſinner, thou abhorredſt not the penitent theefe, the mourning ſinfull woman, nor the woman of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan</hi> when ſhee requeſted thee, nor the woman apprehended in adulterie, nor the Publican praying vnto thee, nor the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple that denied thee, nor yet the Diſciple who perſecuted thy Diſciples, in the ſmell of theſe thine oyntments, wee runne after thee.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, it ſerueth as a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoratiue
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:177902:11"/> to raiſe vp ſuch as <note place="margin">A reſtora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue to raiſe vp ſuch as haue fallen. Augu.</note> haue fallen in the ſame maner, for here, <hi>Non cadendi exemplum, ſed ſi cecideris, reſurgendi propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitum eſt.</hi> There are many who delight to heare or reade the ſinnes of God his Saints, as if they were vnto them <hi>patrocinia peccati,</hi> defences of their ſinnes. But alas, what folly is this, to loue that in <hi>Dauid,</hi> which hee hated in himſelfe? <hi>Hoc non est defenſionem parare animae tuae, ſed comites inquirere ad gehennam:</hi> This is not to prepare a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence for thy owne Soule, but to ſeeke companions to goe with thee into hell, flattering thy ſelfe that thou art in ſtate good enough, becauſe thou art not mateleſſe: but remembe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt not that albeit thou hadſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:177902:11"/> neuer ſo many inuolued with thee in the giltineſſe of thy ſinnes, what comfort can that be vnto thee, <hi>Non enim propte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea minus ardebis, quia cum mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis ardebis,</hi> Shall thy fire in hell be the leſſe, becauſe many will there burn with thee? Nay, by the contrarie the more matter, the bolder fire.</p>
            <p>It were great wiſedome to <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Great wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, to make other mens ſinnes a medicine for vs. Chryſoſt. in Matth. Hom.</hi> 27.</note> embrace that counſell of <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome,</hi> that wee ſhould not ſo much looke to <hi>Dauid</hi> his fall, as to his riſing. Conſider what he did after his fall, how hee put on ſackcloth, how he wate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his bed with teares; how he roared night and day, ſigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and crying continually till hee found the forgiueneſſe of his ſinnes, <hi>Sic medicamenta no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Augu.</note>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:177902:12"/> 
               <hi>de alienis vulneribus faciemus,</hi> So ſhall we make medicaments to our ſelues of the wounds of others, and not bee like vnto phranticke perſons, who ſlay themſelues with the yrons of the Chirurgian, by which they haue ſeene him cut the fleſh of others, he did it of skill for cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and they of their madnes for killing.</p>
            <p>In this inſcription of the <note place="margin">Three things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in the inſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this Pſalme.</note> Pſalme, wee conſider three things: Firſt, how <hi>Dauid</hi> goes into <hi>Bethſheba</hi> and commits A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterie with her. Next how <hi>Nathan</hi> comes to <hi>Dauid</hi> ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping in his ſinne, wakens him and raiſeth him vp by Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: And thirdly, how hee makes this Pſalme, and giues it to bee ſung publickely in the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:177902:12"/> Church as the firſt fruites of his Repentance.</p>
            <p>In the firſt of theſe again, there <note place="margin">1. <hi>The conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of</hi> Dauid <hi>his perſon, who ſinned ſhold make vs feare our owne weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi>
               </note> are three circumſtances to bee conſidered. The perſon, the ſins which hee committes, and the time. The perſon that fals is <hi>Dauid,</hi> a man endued with moſt notable graces of the ſpirit, a man highly commended of God. A man who before had endured ſtrong temptations, and preuailed victor in them all. Now is ouercome, and falles moſt fearfully, this ſhould wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vs, to take heede vnto that warning of the Apoſtle, <hi>He that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.</note> 
               <hi>ſtands, let him take heede that hee fall not.</hi> In him let vs conſider our ſelues, ſhall we preſume of our ſtrength, when wee ſee a ſtronger then wee ouercome?
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:177902:13"/> Nay, rather let vs feare our weakneſſe, and worke out our owne ſaluation in feare and trembling, <hi>Sit lapſus maiorum, tremor minorum,</hi> Let the fall of <note place="margin">Aug.</note> the greater ones make the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker afraid, <hi>Ille hodie &amp; ego cras:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Bern.</note> Hee hath ſinned this day, and we may ſinne to morrow, let others as they liſt drawe on ſinne by examples; But let vs learne, it is a great point of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, to become wiſe by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of others, rather then by experience in our ſelues, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gregor. mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. lib.</hi> 2.</note> thus <hi>Si maiorum caſus ad humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem nos accingat,</hi> wee ſhall not readily fall in the like ſnare of the diuell.</p>
            <p>As for the ſins hee commits, <note place="margin">2. Dauids <hi>ſins are adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, murther careleſſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie.</hi>
               </note> they are very heinous: firſt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterie, next Murther, by the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:177902:13"/> one thinking to couer the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: And thirdly, with them both he fals into no ſmall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of GOD, that for the ſpace of nine monethes hee keepes cloſe his ſinne, frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the externall ſacrifices of Gods worſhip, but not touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his conſcience, with a ſenſe or remorſe for his ſinne, for hee was ſo farre from being troubled for it, that when hee wrote to <hi>Ioab</hi> to expoſe <hi>Vriah</hi> to the ſword of the enemie, he willed him not to be troubled for the matter. Thus wee ſee from one ſinne he goes to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Erranti enim nullus termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> and ſo for any thing wee can perceiue in him, had ſtill walked on in his ſinnes, till hee had fallen in the bottome of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:177902:14"/> hell, if the Lord by grace had not recalled, and recouered him.</p>
            <p>There is ſuch a fellowſhip <note place="margin">Of the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip and combinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong ſinnes</note> among ſinfull affections, they are ſo combined together, that if we giue place to any one of them, many moe perforce ſhal enter vpon vs, they are like the ſeruants of a Tyrant, who fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding one that hath beene fugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue from their Lord, do ioyne themſelues together to bring him backe againe: And euery one of them helpes an other, to keepe him vnder bondage, hauing once ſubdued him, <hi>Sic ope vicaria fugitiuum ſuum vitia</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gregor. mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. lib.</hi> 7.</note> 
               <hi>retinent, &amp; vbi ſemel amiſſum ſub dominij ſui iure recipiunt, ſibi viciſsim ad vindictam tradunt.</hi> Thus is it a great worke of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:177902:14"/> Gods mercie and power, when any of his Saints are deliuered from their ſeruitude.</p>
            <p>As to the third, the time <note place="margin">3. <hi>The time when</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid <hi>ſinned warnes vs, how peril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie.</hi>
               </note> when <hi>Dauid</hi> falles into theſe ſinnes, it is noted 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 11. being at peace, and quietneſſe at home himſelfe, new ariſen from his after-noones ſleepe, walking vpon the rooffe of his Palace, he ſees <hi>Bathſheba</hi> waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her ſelfe in the Garden, and by vnſanctified looking vnto her is ſnared. His people are fighting againſt <hi>Ammon,</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf is ſleeping at home &amp; pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering his body, and <hi>Bathſheha</hi> forgetting her huſband in the battell, falles too her pleaſure and bathes her ſelfe, and that not ſecretly at home, but euen in proſpect of the Kings palace.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:177902:15"/> In all the perſecutions which <hi>Dauid</hi> ſuffered by <hi>Saul,</hi> in all his troubles by <hi>Abſalom,</hi> he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued not ſuch a wound; As a man, the ſtronger the Winde bloweth, holds his garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts the faſter about him, whereas the beating heate of the Sunne, makes him to lay them aſide: ſo <hi>Dauid</hi> vnder temptation was the more feruent in prayer; the more he was troubled by men, the faſter did hee cleaue to the Lord his God: but now being freed from trouble and liuing in proſperitie, what a great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage doth Sathan get ouer him?</p>
            <p>Sure it is, a man hath neuer <note place="margin">A man hath moſt cauſe of feare when he is leaſt croſſed.</note> more cauſe to feare, then when he findes his eſtate moſt quiet. It is a moſt dangerous thing to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:177902:15"/> liue without ſome croſſe, or temptation, that may chaſe a man to God. As an idle man readily fals aſleepe, and being aſleepe, any Iewell he hath in his hand, doth eaſily fall from him: ſo carnall proſperitie caſts men in careleſſe ſecuritie, whereby ſpirituall graces are greatly weakened into them, <hi>Facilior cautio, vbi manifeſta for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mido,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Cyprian. de ſimplicitate praelat.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; ad certamen animus ante praeſtruitur, quando ſe aduerſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us confitetur,</hi> When our aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie ſhewes himſelfe moſt plainely, then is it moſt eaſie for vs to beware of him, <hi>Plus metuendus est inimicus cum la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenter obrepit, cum per pacis ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginem fallens occultis acceſsibus ſerpit, vnde etiam illi nomen ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentis.</hi> But then haue wee moſt
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:177902:16"/> cauſe to feare him, when be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiling vs by the ſhew, and I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of peace, he creeps in by ſecret wayes, inſinuating him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe craftily to get vantage o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs, for the which cauſe alſo the name of a Serpent is attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted vnto him.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered <note place="margin">Nathan <hi>viſits</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid <hi>like a whole Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to cure a ſicke Phiſitian.</hi>
               </note> in the inſcription, is how <hi>Nathan</hi> comes to <hi>Dauid,</hi> and raiſeth him vp, <hi>Aſtat post peccatum propheta prophetae, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luti medicus medico agrotanti;</hi> Here one Prophet comes vnto an other, like one Phiſitian vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiting an other Phiſitian in his diſeaſe. This is the duetie of Chriſtians, ſince they are of one communion, to edifie one another in the moſt holy faith, to exhort one another. Hee
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:177902:16"/> that is ſtronger in the faith, ought to confirme the weaker, and hee that ſtands ſhould raiſe vp with the ſpirit of meekneſſe him that hath fallen, conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">Euery Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſhould edifie ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> alſo himſelfe. It was the voice of <hi>Cain,</hi> am I my bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers keeper, and it ſhould bee farre from Chriſtians. That Lawe pertaines to vs all, <hi>Thou ſhalt not hate thy brother in thine</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leui.</hi> 19. 17</note> 
               <hi>heart, but thou ſhalt plainely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke him, and ſuffer him not to ſinne;</hi> for it is no loue but ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, to know thy brother in a ſinne, and not to rebuke him. And truely it is no ſmall bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of GOD, when among Chriſtians, ſuch inſtrumentes of grace as <hi>Nathan</hi> was, doe a bound, who being endewed with grace from aboue, are
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:177902:17"/> able by grace to comfort the feeble minded, to ſtrengthen the weake, and to raiſe them vp that haue fallen.</p>
            <p>Againe, that <hi>Dauid</hi> hauing <note place="margin">Man ſinnes by nature, but cannot riſe without grace.</note> ſinned, riſeth not till the Lord ſent <hi>Nathan</hi> to raiſe him, learns vs a leſſon, which ſhould hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vs all, and binde vs to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the great mercie of God toward vs, he fals by him ſelfe, he riſeth not by himſelfe. Nine monethes lies hee as it were dead in that graue of ſin, till the Lord who called vpon <hi>Lazarus,</hi> called vpon him alſo, and made him come out of it. It is eaſie for any man to fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a pit, but not ſo eaſie for him to come out of it. <hi>Si ſtare</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Bern.</note> 
               <hi>non potuit humana natura adhuc integra, quanto minus poterit per</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:177902:17"/> 
               <hi>ſeipſam reſurgere iam corrupta,</hi> as it was with him, ſo is it with vs all, <hi>perditio tua ex te, ô Iſrael:</hi> thy deſtruction is of thy ſelfe, O Iſrael; but our ſaluation is of the Lord, and from the Lambe that ſits with him vpon the throne.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, wee ſee this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence <note place="margin">Reprobate men ſinne and repent not, not ſo the godly.</note> betweene the godly and the wicked, the one falles and riſeth not. <hi>Iudas</hi> betrayed Chriſt; <hi>Peter</hi> forſware him, the one goes on in his ſinnes, and periſheth, the other is renewed by repentance. The difference then is not in ſinne, wherein wee are alſo as deepe as they, but in this that the Lord hath had mercie vpon vs. O how are wee obliged to bleſſe him, who hath put a difference by
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:177902:18"/> grace betweene vs and them, where there was no difference by nature. And this is to bee marked for them who haue an eye to ſee, how <hi>Dauid</hi> ſinned e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as they haue ſinned, and therefore account the leſſe of their ſinnes, but haue not an eye to ſee that they haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented, as <hi>Dauid</hi> repented, and that therefore being farre vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like him in Repentance, they can haue no comfort, that hee was like them in ſinne.</p>
            <p>The third point of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription <note place="margin">The order of ſinging Leuites vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the law Leuiticall.</note> is in theſe words, <hi>To him that excelleth: A Pſalme of Dauid.</hi> Wherein wee ſee how he dedicateth this Pſalme, as the firſt fruite and teſtimonie of his Repentance, to bee ſung publikely in the Church, for
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:177902:18"/> vnderſtanding whereof wee muſt know how <hi>Dauid</hi> ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſome of the Leuites, skilled in Muſicke to praiſe the Lord by ſinging, and playing vpon Inſtruments, theſe were in number foure thouſand, who <note place="margin">1. <hi>Chron.</hi> 23. 5.</note> by courſe ſerued the Lord in his Sanctuarie. They were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided in ſeuerall claſſes; and ouer euery one of them, ſome that were Maſters of Muſicke, Precentors, who in ſinging and playing excelled the reſt, ſuch as <hi>Aſaph, Heman, Idithun, &amp;c.</hi> and to theſe it is, that <hi>Dauid</hi> dedicateth this Pſalme to bee ſung publikely, for the word <hi>Natſeah</hi> in <hi>Piel,</hi> ſignifieth one that is an ouerſeer, or preſident ouer others, for his excellencie in ſtrength, or skill, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:177902:19"/> and ſo here and in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Pſalmes <hi>Dauid</hi> vſeth it, to ſignifie a maſter of Muſicke.</p>
            <p>The inſtruments they vſed in prayſing the Lord, are moſt <note place="margin">Two ſortes of muſicall Inſtruments vſed in the Leuiticall Law.</note> of them reckoned vp in the laſt Pſalme; all of them may be reduced to two ſorts, whereof the one are called <hi>Neginoth,</hi> ſuch as made a ſound by tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, from the word <hi>Nagan, pulſauit;</hi> the other called <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiloth,</hi> ſuch as being hollow, made a ſound by breathing, from the word <hi>Halal.</hi> Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time the muſicall Inſtrument was premitted, and the ſinging voice followed, and then the Song was called <hi>Canticum Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi,</hi> for <hi>Pſalterium</hi> properly is a kind of muſicall Inſtrument, called of the Hebrewes <hi>Naula,</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:177902:19"/> but is tranſlated to ſignifie the Pſalmes. Sometime againe the Song was firſt ſung with the voice, and the muſicall Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment followed, and then it is called <hi>Pſalmus cantici.</hi> What vpon this is to be obſerued, ſee our notes vpon the one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and nineteene Pſalme.</p>
            <p>Onely now we marke, how <note place="margin">The godly are content to ſhame themſelues, by Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſinne that they may giue glorie vnto God.</note> 
               <hi>Dauid</hi> careth not to take ſhame to himſelfe, by confeſſing his Murther and Adultrie pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely in the Church, that hee may giue glorie vnto God; So is it with all Gods childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who hath felt the terror of an accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing conſcience for ſinne, who are grieued in themſelues for diſpleaſing the Lord, and are earneſtly ſeeking to be reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with God, they refuſe not
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:177902:20"/> to manifeſt their owne ſhame, yea and as it were with that fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Leper vnder the Law, with his clothes rent, with his head bare, with a couering vpon his lips, to crie out before all the world, <hi>I am vncleane, I am vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leuit.</hi> 13. 45.</note> that ſo they may get peace from God, and may giue him glory by their repentance as they diſhonoured him by their ſinne. I ſpeake not this <note place="margin">This is not to be vnder ſtood of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate ſinnes.</note> of priuate ſinnes, the example wherof hath not offended thy neighbour; Such ſinnes I ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wiſh to be buried, as Iſrael with their paddles buried their filth without the Campe vnder the earth, nor laied open to the eyes of others: but of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ſinnes, it is not our ſhame to confeſſe theſe for remouing
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:177902:20"/> of the ſlander, but double ſinne and ſhame to conceale them, how ſo euer it bee currant now, as an vndoubted axiome among carnall men, that no man is bound to ſweare to his owne ſhame, ſure wee are, it is not warranted by any Diuine authoritie, for ſo <hi>Achan</hi> might haue excuſed himſelf when <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua,</hi> willed him by confeſſing of theft, to giue glorie to God, and ſo <hi>Dauid</hi> here might haue ſhifted himſelfe from this pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke confeſſion; where the conſcience is ſleeping, any war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant <note place="margin">A ſleeping Conſcience excuſeth ſinne.</note> is thought ſufficient to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe a ſinne, and man feares not to defraude the Lord of that glorie, hee ſhould haue by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of it, but where the Lord wakens the conſcience,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:177902:21"/> all excuſes are ſet aſide, and man is glad to disburden him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, by confeſſing his ſinne vnto the Lord. This the Lord will haue of all fleſh at the length, for ſo hath hee ſworne, <hi>As I liue ſaith the Lord,</hi> euerie tongue ſhall confeſſe to me, he ſhall then force them to giue him glorie by confeſſing, who now wickedly defraude him of it by concealing: But happie and wiſe is he, who doth it in time when Mercie is to be found with the LORD.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:177902:21"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>PSALME. 51. VERSE 1.</bibl>
               <q>Haue mercie vpon me, O God, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thy louing kindneſſe, according to the multitude of thy compaſsions, put away mine iniquitie.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Itherto the inſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption <note place="margin">The ſumme and order of this Pſalme.</note> or preface of the PSALME: Nowe followes the PSALME, wherein <hi>Dauid</hi> firſt praieth for himſelfe to the 18. Verſe; Next for the Church of GOD
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:177902:22"/> Verſe 18. In the praier for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, he hath firſt a generall pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, <hi>haue mercie on me, O God,</hi> Verſe 1. then three particular petitions, firſt, the remiſſion of his ſinne, which he expreſſeth by putting away, waſhing, purging, to the Verſe 8. Next the reſtitution of peace, and ioy to his conſcience, which by his ſinne he had ſore empaired, Verſe 89. Thirdly, the reno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of his Heart and Spirit within him, which moſt feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully hee had altered from the loue of God, to the loue of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, Verſe 10. 11. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This Pſalme is frequently <note place="margin">
                  <hi>They ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not rightly vſe the words of this Pſalme, who want</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uids <hi>diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</hi>
               </note> ſung in the mouthes of many men, but ſure it is theſe words which were true, when <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpake them, are but lies when
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:177902:22"/> they are pronounced by many men, for ſo they pray, O Lord conſider my diſtreſſe, when as in very deede they had neuer ſuch a thing, as a diſtreſſed ſoule for ſinne. Is not this a mocking of God to pray him to looke vpon that, which is not in thee, to pray him conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that, which thou neuer conſideredſt thy ſelfe, learne therefore when yee ſing this Pſalme of <hi>Dauid,</hi> to take on ſo neare as yee may <hi>Dauid</hi> his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, though yee haue not ſinned as he did, yet looke vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your other ſinnes, and be ye humbled for them, otherwaies your confeſſion of ſinnes ſhall be but a profeſſion of ſinne, to ſay with <hi>Dauid,</hi> againſt thee on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly haue I ſinned, and then ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:177902:23"/> to haue no remorſe for ſin, or no confidence in Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, ſhall profit thee no more then the confeſſion of <hi>Saul</hi> or <hi>Iudas:</hi> I haue ſinned, ſaid the one; I haue ſinned in betraying innocent bloud, ſaid the other, their confeſſion was ſomewhat like <hi>Dauids,</hi> their heart no way like <hi>Dauids:</hi> And it is certaine that the Lord, <hi>Radicem attendit, non florem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Haue mercie on me.</hi> What <note place="margin">Wher Sinne perſues no refuge but to mercie.</note> was <hi>Dauid</hi> his eſtate when hee brake out in theſe words, yee may ſee out of the 32. Pſalme, his conſcience being wakned by the miniſtrie of <hi>Nathan,</hi> hee is ſo terrified with the liuely ſenſe of his ſinne and ſight of that wrath which by it he had deſerued, that his bones were
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:177902:23"/> conſumed, and the moiſture of his body turned in the drogth of Sommer: In this perplexed eſtate the firſt comfort that he findes is by looking vp to the mercie of God.</p>
            <p>Naturall men may maruell <note place="margin">No exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal comfort can ſuſtaine a man trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for ſinne.</note> what is this that ſhould haue troubled <hi>Dauid</hi> ſo ſore, was he not King of <hi>Canaan,</hi> his ſinnes were murther, and adulterie; but was there any in the Land to put him to an Aſſize? was there any to puniſh him? what needed hee to feare? But hee himſelfe tells thee what ailed him, the hand of God was hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie vpon him night and day, the Lord had erected a Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall in his owne conſcience, and did there ſit and iudge him, wher no man might iudge him,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:177902:24"/> there the Lord conuicted him of ſinne, and threatned him with terrours, for ſure it is all the comforts of the world, if thou hadſt them in one, cannot ſuſtaine thee when God in thy own co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience perſecutes thee for ſinne, examples are <hi>Baltha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> and <hi>Dauid: The ſpirit of a man will ſuſtaine his infirmitie, but a wounded ſpirit, who can beare it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore <hi>Dauid</hi> ſore <note place="margin">Dauids <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellation from God to God.</hi>
               </note> ſtraitned with the iudgement of God, turnes him to the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of God, hee findes no other thing whereupon to relie his faith, he can get no other gripe whereby to hold him, that hee fall not in the pit of deſperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but this mercie. O Lord, in regard of thy power thou art
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:177902:24"/> inuincible, who can reſiſt thee? who can indure the ſtroke of thine hand? In regard of thy wiſedome, thou art all-ſeeing, nothing can be hid from thee In regard of thy iuſtice thou art moſt holy, &amp; canſt not bee cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, in none of theſe can I finde comfort, the only hope of mine heart is in thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and mercie, ſo that now hee flees <hi>ad co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munem peccantium</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note> 
               <hi>portum,</hi> to the common harbor of all poore penitent ſinners, who are toſt too and fro with the tumbling thoughts of an accuſing conſcience, threatning more fearefull death, then the raging waues of the Sea to <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas,</hi> neuer can ſettle nor reſt til they come within the Port of God his mercie, euen ſo here
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:177902:25"/> doth <hi>Dauid,</hi> terrified with Gods iudgement, before which hee could not ſtand, he appeales to Gods mercie, <hi>tanquam ab infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riori ſede ad ſuperiorem,</hi> as the higher bench wherein the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of God ſhineth moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently, <hi>for mercie reioyſes againſt iudgement.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 2. 13.</note>
            </p>
            <p>When we heare that <hi>Dauid,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Nothing in the world to be eſteemed miſerie, but only iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</note> and others of Gods Saints, crie for mercie, we muſt remember that this includes a humble co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of their miſerie, and what was <hi>Dauids</hi> miſerie which he craues to bee cured by God his mercie, hee tells you in the end of the Verſe, no other but the miſerie of ſinne: <hi>Nathan</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. 10.</note> had threatned him with the ſword, &amp; that he ſhould make his Sonne, who came out of his
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:177902:25"/> bowels, a ſcourge vnto him, but <hi>Dauid</hi> counts none of theſe his miſerie, for which hee craues mercie, his miſerie is his iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and the mercie he craues is the putting away of his iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. This blinde age counts bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily infirmities &amp; want of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall things miſerie, but ſinne they count no miſerie, blinder then the Egyptians of old, who eſteemed ſheepe-heards abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable, but Idolaters not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable: but indeede it is farre otherwaies: wert thou ſo poore as <hi>Lazarus,</hi> filled with biles in thy bodie from head to foot as <hi>Iob</hi> was, yet if thou bee freed from ſin, thou art freed from miſerie, and bee the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie, wert thou ſo rich as that glutton clad in purple, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:177902:26"/> delicately euery day <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thou health and honor, and all the comforts of the world af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the deſire of thine owne heart, if yet thou bee in thy ſinnes, the end ſhall declare thou art a miſerable creature.</p>
            <p>This will be manifeſt at the <note place="margin">Euen the wicked at the laſt ſhal feare finde more then death.</note> length in all the wicked, that their miſerie is not in ſickneſſe, nay not in death it ſelfe, but in an euill conſcience guiltie of ſinne, though now they abhor nothing but death, &amp; eſteeme ſinne but a paſtime: the day is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming, wherin they ſhal ſeeke death &amp; not find it, ſaying, hills and mountaines fall vpon vs, and couer vs, they ſhall be glad to be ſmothered to the death, and to ſuffer the greateſt miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie that can come to their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:177902:26"/> vpon condition they were freed from the miſerie of an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill conſcience; which ſinne hath brought vpon them.</p>
            <p>But howſoeuer this miſerie <note place="margin">A comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie.</note> of <hi>Dauid</hi> was exceeding great, he eſpies in God by the eye of faith a greater mercie to cure it, and therefore cries hee for mercie according to the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of his commiſerations; O Lord, I know that whatſoeuer is in thee is thy ſelfe, thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie is no leſſe then thy ſelfe. <hi>Cum ſis miſericors, quid es, niſi ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa miſericordia,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Hieron. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanarola.</note> ſeeing thou art mercifull, what art thou but mercie it ſelfe? and what can mercie doe but thine owne worke? canſt thou denie thy ſelfe? canſt thou depart from thine owne nature? what is the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:177902:27"/> worke of mercie, but to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way miſerie, here am I Lord before thee a miſerable man, and my greateſt miſerie is my ſinne, doe thy owne worke, O Lord, cure my miſerie with thy mercie, ſhew the vertue of thy mercies vpon mee, <hi>abyſſus abyſsum inuocat, abyſſus miſeriae inuocat abyſsum miſericor diae,</hi> one deepe calls vpon an other, the deepe of miſerie calls vpon the deepe of mercie, greater is the deepe of mercie then the deepe of miſerie; let therefore the deepe of thy mercie ſwallow vp the deepe of my miſerie, and put thou away mine iniquitie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>On me. Dauid</hi> doeth not now <note place="margin">The humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of a penitent thinks not his name worth to be named.</note> as at other times expreſſe his name, as when hee ſaid, Lord remember <hi>Dauid, &amp;c.</hi> neither
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:177902:27"/> takes hee here to himſelfe the name of Gods ſeruant, as cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mably he doth in other places, but concealeth his name, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed of himſelfe, not vnlike that forlorne child, I haue ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt heauen and againſt <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 15.</note> thee, and am no more worthy to be called thy ſonne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>According to thy louing kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Dauid <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends on Gods mercy not on his owne merit.</hi>
               </note> We haue heard <hi>Dauid</hi> his petition in generall: Now the reaſon whereby he will moue the Lord to grant it, is not from any merit in himſelfe, hee vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly diſclaimes that, but only from God his louing kindneſſe and commiſeration, vpon theſe two doth hee now faſten his gripes, and by the meditation of them hee conceiues ſome hope of fauour in the Lord, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:177902:28"/> when in himſelfe hee had receiued a condemnatorie ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of death, by reaſon of his ſinne.</p>
            <p>Two things are requiſite in <note place="margin">The two eyes of a penitent ſinner, and what loſſe it is to want either of them.</note> a ſinner, that would haue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie; firſt, an eye to know his ſinnes that being aſhamed of himſelfe, he may reſolue, there can be no life for him, if he reſt in himſelfe. And next an eye to ſee Gods mercie, many haue not the firſt, &amp; therefore thinke that either without a Sacrifice, or with a ſmall ſacrifice, God will bee pleaſed, they cannot mourne for ſinne, eſteeming their ſinnes ſo ſmall that they neede no great mourning: O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers againe haue not the other eye whereby to ſee Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie in Chriſt, they ſee their own
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:177902:28"/> ſinne, but ſee not God his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and therefore are carried either to a temporall deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which may befal the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that for a time they ſeeme to themſelues vtterly vndone, or then to a finall, us all the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probates doe: examples wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of wee haue in <hi>Cain, Saul,</hi> and <hi>Iudas,</hi> from whoſe miſerable condition the Lord preſerue vs.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>Dauid</hi> finding nothing <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Two things in God</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid <hi>grounds vpon.</hi>
               </note> in himſelfe to comfort him, when he lookes vp to God hee ſees two things, as I ſaid, that ſuſtaine him; firſt, the kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe <note place="margin">1 <hi>His benig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie or kindneſſe, this is either generall.</hi>
               </note> of God; next the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold compaſſions of God; the word expreſſing his kindneſſe is <hi>Cheſed,</hi> the benignitie of God, and this is either general, wher
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:177902:29"/> by hee loues his creatures con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing them, as he made them, and delights to doe good vnto them, in ſo farre as they are the works of his hands. <hi>Thou Lord</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 5. 45</note> 
               <hi>ſaueſt man and beaſt, he makes his Sunne to ariſe on the euill and the good, and ſendeth raine on the iuſt and vniuſt.</hi> And this howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it rendred ſome comfort, yet could it not giue full com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to DAVID, conſidering that ſinne, the poiſon of the Serpent in him, made him iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">Or ſpeciall.</note> abhominable to God. And therefore hee caſts his eye fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnto that ſpeciall benigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of God, which in effect is his mercie, whereby hee loues his owne in Chriſt redeemes them from their ſinnes, and ſaues them by his grace when
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:177902:29"/> they haue loſt themſelues by their iniquitie.</p>
            <p>And this is euident by the other word immediatly he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioynes <note place="margin">The ſpeciall is in effect Gods mercy and tender compaſsion.</note> of God his compaſſion which is the other ground, whereupon the faith of <hi>Dauid</hi> repoſed, for the word <hi>Racham</hi> ſignifies to loue from the verie bowells and inward affection, being deduced from the name <hi>Rêchêm,</hi> which ſignifies the <note place="margin">What great comfort wee haue into it.</note> wombe or matrice, that with moſt kindly and tender affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, compaſſe and nouriſh the Infant within it, ſuppoſe it cannot bee thankefull for the preſent, nor doe the duetie wherein it is bound, but rather be offenſiue to the mother that carries it, <hi>Dauid</hi> knew that the like tender affection was in God
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:177902:30"/> toward his owne poore chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, yea and much more grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, then the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s are higher <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> from the earth; ſo farre are the thoughts of God his loue and compaſſion, aboue all that can bee in vs, it is poſſible the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may forget the birth of her wombe, but the LORD cannot forget them who are his.</p>
            <p>Therefore doth he not only <note place="margin">Compaſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in the plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall number are aſcribed to God.</note> aſcribe vnto God compaſſions but great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſions, or a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of them, &amp; ſo he ſpeakes for two cauſes, firſt becauſe where God ſhewes mercies, he <note place="margin">1 <hi>Becauſe where he ſhewes mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, he ſhews many mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
               </note> ſhewes many mercies together a heape and a verie maſſe of mercies. The royall heart of <hi>Alexander</hi> thought it not hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable for him to giue a ſmall
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:177902:30"/> thing, what then ſhall we think of our God? The ods is ſo great that there can bee no compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. But ſure where hee giues any of his chief bleſſings, there hee giues ſuch a treaſure forth of his infinite riches of mercie, as we are not able to ſpeake of.</p>
            <p>Yet for our comfort in our <note place="margin">Sixe ranks of mercie.</note> meditation, his mercies ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto vs, ſince wee could <note place="margin">1 <hi>Preuenting mercie.</hi>
               </note> know, what mercie was, wee may reduce them to ſix rankes, the firſt I call preuenting mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, whereby the Lord did vs good when wee knew him not, and kept vs from many ſinnes, which otherwaies wee would haue committed: <hi>O quanta dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natio</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bern. de E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uang.</hi> 7. <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Ser.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>pietatis, quod ingratum ſic gratia conſeruabat,</hi> Many ſinnes haue we done againſt him, but
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:177902:31"/> farre moe ſhould we haue done if his mercie had not preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vs, <hi>Agnoſce ergo gratiam eius cui debes, etiam quod non ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſiſti.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Augu.</note> 
               <hi>Mihi debet iſte quod fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum est &amp; dimiſſum vidiſti, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hi debes &amp; tu quod non feciſti.</hi> Acknowledge therefore Gods mercie toward thee, euen in theſe ſinnes, which thou haſt not done. If thou ſeeſt one who is debitor to mee for a ſin, which hee did and I forgaue him; vnderſtand alſo that thou art debitor to me for keeping thee, that thou didſt not the like, for there is no ſinne which any man hath done, but an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man would doe the like, if God by grace did not preſerue him from it.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond ranke hath in it
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:177902:31"/> his ſparing mercies, or the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies <note place="margin">Sparing mercies.</note> of his patience, though we haue beene kept from the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of many ſinnes, yet haue we done enough to condemne vs. There is an other ſort of mercie, <hi>Peccabam &amp; tu diſsimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labas, non continebam a ſceleribus &amp; tu a verberibus abſtinebas,</hi> I ſinned and thou heldſt thy tongue, I tranſgreſſed, thou ſparedſt and killedſt mee not, when wee looke to <hi>Zimri</hi> and <hi>Cosbi</hi> ſlaine in the act of harlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie; to <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira</hi> ſtriken to death in their ſinne, what ſhall wee ſay, but it is a great mercie of God, that hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto wee haue not beene ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away in the middeſt of our ſinnes?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> In the third ranke, wee place
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:177902:32"/> his pardoning mercies, for a <note place="margin">3 <hi>Pardoning mercies.</hi>
               </note> man may thinke what benefit is it to mee, to bee long ſpared, ſeeing at the laſt, iudgment will come, <hi>&amp; quo diutius expectat, eo diſtrictius iudicabit,</hi> but this fear is taken away from the godly by God his pardoning mercies, he forgiues their ſins in Chriſt, he will neuer impute their ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie vnto them, but taketh them vtterly away, <hi>Peccatum non imputatum, eſt quaſi nunquam fuerit commiſſum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But with theſe is alſo giuen <note place="margin">4 <hi>Renewing mercies.</hi>
               </note> vs the fourth ſort, that is his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing mercies. There are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>quorum infructuoſa eſt poeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia,</hi> who repent of their ſinnes, but are not renewed by amendment of life, in whom <hi>nouiſsimus error peior eſt priori,</hi>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:177902:32"/> their returning like Dogges to their vomit, is worſe then their firſt tranſgreſſion: but the Lord when hee giues to his owne children the grace of remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, doth alſo giue with it the grace of renouation, whereby hee makes them new creatures, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounding in the fruits of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, to Gods glorie, the edification of their brethren, and the comfort of their owne conſciences in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And yet all theſe were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, if it were not that the fift <note place="margin">5. <hi>Corrobora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and continuing mercie.</hi>
               </note> ranke of mercies were alſo hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped vpon vs, which I call con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing mercies, whereby wee perſeuer in that eſtate of grace, whereunto we are once called. <hi>Adam</hi> in his beſt eſtate of inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie continued not, &amp; would
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:177902:33"/> wee ſtand in grace, if perſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, which hee wanted, were not communicated vnto vs. As mercie brought vs to this ſtate of grace, ſo it is by mercie alſo that we are kept in it.</p>
            <p>And the laſt ranke is of Gods crowning mercies, whereby he <note place="margin">6. <hi>Crowning mercies.</hi>
               </note> ſhall perfect his owne worke, finiſh that which hee hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunne in vs, hee ſhall performe to vs his promiſed Kingdome, feare of euill ſhall be farre from vs, in that Paradiſe no tempter ſhall bee to ſnare vs, mercie ſhall compaſſe vs, no good ſhall be lacking to vs, the Lord ſhall bee all in all vnto vs, and from that bleſſed fellowſhip and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with him, ſhall wee neuer be diuided againe.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:177902:33"/>
            <p> And as this way Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies <note place="margin">Compaſſions in the plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, are aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed to God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the proofe and practiſe of them is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold.</note> are manifold, ſo likewiſe are the prayſes of them in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of innumerable perſons, on whom they haue beene de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, for <hi>miſerationes Dei ſunt opera &amp; proceſſus miſericordiae e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius,</hi> and ſo his meditation is, O Lord thou haſt ſhewed com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion to many a penitent ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, ſince the beginning of the world, thou neuer reiectedſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that ſought thee with a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent heart, for number they cannot bee told to whom thou haſt beene mercifull, <hi>quot enim iuſti, tot miſerationes,</hi> let them al be gathered that are in heauen and earth, if it be demanded of them, how is it they haue been ſaued, they will all anſwere, <hi>Not vnto vs, O Lord, but vnto thy</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:177902:34"/> 
               <hi>name be the praiſe;</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeeing thou, O Lord, art the ſame; And <hi>no ſhadow of change is with thee,</hi> I beſeech thee cloſe not that dore of mercie on me, which hath ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to receiue ſo many ſinners before me, and theſe Riuers of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſion which haue flowed ſo abundantly toward others, let them not bee dryed vp to mee.</p>
            <p>This earneſtneſſe of <hi>Dauids</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Feeling of our wants, make ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Prayer.</note> praier, flowes from the feeling of his great ſinnes, he knew his ſinnes were great, and therfore craues he great mercies, <hi>magna ſiquidem vulnera paribus indige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Baſil.</note> 
               <hi>Pharmacis,</hi> yea that in this one tranſgreſſion, manifold ſinnes were included, and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee needed not one, but a
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:177902:34"/> multitude of diuine commiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations: <hi>Vniuer ſam in ſe Dei gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam effundi, &amp; totum miſeratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num fontem in peccati ſui vlcera euacuari orat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But how ſoeuer the mercies <note place="margin">The mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of God are plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, yet not extended to all, and why</note> of God bee plentifull, yet are they not extended vnto all, they are free indeede; <hi>I haue mercie</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>on whom I will haue mercie,</hi> but ſo that if there be any man, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they flow not, he may alwaies finde the cauſe in himſelf, in his hard heart that cannot repent, it holds true in all the reprobate, which the Apoſtle ſpeakes of the rebellious Iewes; <hi>Yee put it from you,</hi> meaning the word of the Goſpell, wherein mercie and grace is offered, <hi>and iudge your ſelues vnworthie of euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting</hi>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:177902:35"/> 
               <hi>life,</hi> therefore that mercie which is here craued by <hi>Dauid,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 13. 46.</note> by a moſt fearefull decree was denied vnto them, God gaue that people a name <hi>Lo-Rucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mah,</hi> I will no more haue pitie <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 1. 6.</note> on them, whereupon followed another name, expreſſing their <note place="margin">Such as will not be Gods people, ſhall not find Gods mercy</note> miſerie after that once God for their ſins had caſt them away, <hi>Lo-Ammi,</hi> that is to ſay, they are not my people, and I will not bee theirs. No tongue can expreſſe the miſerie of that man, who for his proud conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance in ſinne, and contempt of grace offered vnto him, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiues moſt iuſtly from the Lord, that decree of <hi>Lo-Rucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mah,</hi> I will haue no mercie on him; where the Fountayne is ſtopped the Springs of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:177902:35"/> muſt drie vp, where mercie is denied, all good things flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from it muſt decay. This will be the curſed condition of the damned. <hi>All fat and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuel.</hi> 18. 14.</note> 
               <hi>things ſhall depart from them,</hi> from which the Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Put away mine iniquities.</hi> Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto <note place="margin">Dauid <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to his particular petitions.</hi>
               </note> we haue heard <hi>Dauid</hi> his generall petition for mercie, now followes his three parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular petitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, expreſſing what mercie it is hee craued, as wee ſhewed in the beginning of the Verſe.</p>
            <p>His firſt particular petition <note place="margin">Whereof the firſt is a petition for the remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his ſinnes.</note> is for forgiueneſſe of his ſinne, the fact was paſt, but the gilt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained, the pleaſure of it was ſoone done, but the terror of it ſtill vexed him, all the comfort
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:177902:36"/> of his Kingdome could not make him merry, the torment of an accuſing conſcience for ſin was more ſtrong to deiect him, then all the pleaſures of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan</hi> were to ſuſtaine him, yea it is moſt ſure that externall comforts are ſo far from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting a troubled conſcience, that by the contrarie they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the trouble thereof, and the more worldly comforts be preſented, the greater is the heauineſſe of that ſoule, which is afflicted for ſinne; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now when hee comes to <note place="margin">The griefe of ſinne can not be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaged by any worldly comfort.</note> the point, hee tels where his ſore was, what grieued him moſt, iniquitie, iniquitie; hee cryes out for this in the 32. Pſalme; <hi>Bleſſed is the man whoſe wickedneſſe is forgiuen, whoſe</hi>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:177902:36"/> 
               <hi>ſinne is couered, and to whom the Lord imputes not iniquitie.</hi> As if he would ſay, hee that hath not this, hath no bleſſing, all comforts without this are com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fortleſſe.</p>
            <p>Where wee haue to take vp <note place="margin">What a fear full euill ſinne is.</note> what a curſed and miſerable thing ſinne is, a ſparkle of fire come from hell, that burnes vp all the pleaſures of the Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe of a good Conſcience, a ſeede of Sathan, a peece of lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen that ſowreth and infecteth all it comes among, turning ſweeteſt things into bitter. It is but a ſmall thing to looke to, ſoone done in the twinckling of an eye, but hath an enduring ſting, and produceth manifold and great euill effects, it pertur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth all being but one, and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:177902:37"/> ſpoyle man of the comfort of all God his creatures, miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men bewitched with the deceipt of ſinne, drunken with the preſent falſe pleaſures ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of cannot beleeue this, it is but a paſtime to them to doe wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly; but let them know it ſhall turne to bitterneſſe in the end. But of this more in the third verſe, where hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines that his ſinne was euer before him.</p>
            <p>The word that in this petition <note place="margin">God hath his accompt Booke, wherein the debts of men, that is their ſinnes are Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred.</note> 
               <hi>Dauid</hi> vſeth is <hi>Machah,</hi> ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a ſcraping &amp; a blotting out; hee alludes as it ſeemes to the maner of them, who haue their accompt Bookes, wherein they write vp their debts, whereof they purpoſe to haue paiment, although they ſpare for a time,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:177902:37"/> wherupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Dauid</hi> ſayeth, I know Lord thou haſt thine owne accompt Booke, wherein thou writeſt the tranſgreſſions of them, with whom thou mindeſt to enter in iudgement accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that, <hi>The ſinne of Iuda is written with a Penne of yron, and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iere.</hi> 17.</note> 
               <hi>the point of a Diamond.</hi> Let not O Lord my debt ſtand Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred there, but of thy mercie put it and blot it out, I haue done enough for my part to put my owne name out of the Booke of life, and inſert it in the Roll of them that muſt come to iudgement. I know there is a ſtanding decree in thy Booke, <hi>That death is the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of ſinne;</hi> If my ſinne ſtand in thy Regiſter, I am but a dead man, <hi>Lord quicken me, forgiue</hi>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:177902:38"/> 
               <hi>me my treſpaſſe, and put away the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 2. 13.</note> 
               <hi>hand-writing of thy ordinance, which is contrarie to me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But here let vs marke, how <note place="margin">The bookes are two, the booke of his Science, and the booke of our Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</note> it is that the Lord putteth ſinne out of his two-fold Regiſter, Firſt out of the booke of his owne ſcience, hee putteth the ſinnes of his children vtterly, both the gilt and the memorie of them hee putteth away, ſo that out of his accompt booke hee ſcrapes our debt cleane a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, that it appeares not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, according to his promiſe, <hi>I will remember their ſinnes no more.</hi> But out of the Regiſter of our conſcience, hee putteth the gilt, the accuſing, and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting power of it, but abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſheth not vtterly the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of it. He reſerues ſome
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:177902:38"/> monument of our ſinnes in our memorie, after that they are forgiuen, partly to humble vs, when wee looke backe vnto them, and partly to preſerue vs from committing the like in time to come.</p>
            <p>And further we ſee how <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Blind are they who thinke they can make ſatisfaction to God for their debts.</note> acknowledgeth, his debt was more then hee was able to pay, and therefore diſclaiming his owne ſufficiencie, hee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peales to Gods mercy, beſeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the L. to blot it out, for he had not to pay it. It is a pitiful blindneſſe in the aduerſaries of the truth, that teacheth poore people to leane vnto mans ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactions, which they muſt make to God for their ſinnes, either here or in Purgatorie, how wilt thou ſatisfie that infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:177902:39"/> maieſtie of God for thy manifold ſinnes, <hi>Ille figulus, tu</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ber. Scr. de quadrup. debito.</note> 
               <hi>figmentum.</hi> When thou haſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto him all that thou art able, either by doing or ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Nonneiſtud eſt, ſicut ſtella ad ſolem, gutta ad fluuium,</hi> What is it, but as if one ſhould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare a Starre with the Sunne, or a drop with a riuer, <hi>Nemo eſt qui milleſimae imo nec minimae parte debitorum ſuorum valeat re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondere.</hi> I ſee it was blindnes, and ſo it is, whatſoeuer ſhew of learning bee in them, who maintaine it, if they knew how great is the debt that man ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vnto God, they would ſay with <hi>Bernard,</hi> There is none in the world able to anſwere the thouſand part; nay, not the ſmalleſt part of that Debt,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:177902:39"/> which man oweth vnto God. Away therefore with that blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous word of humaine ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, for except the Lord haue compaſſion on vs, and for <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mattb.</hi> 18. 27.</note> giue the debt, there remaines nothing for vs, but to be pined in priſon for euer.</p>
            <p>And this alſo is to bee obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>By three words,</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid <hi>expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his ſin, to ſhew the greatneſſe thereof.</hi>
               </note> how <hi>Dauid</hi> making menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his ſinne, contents him not with one word, but chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges there ſundrie words to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe it, whereof the one <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhang,</hi> ſignifieth defection and rebellion; the other <hi>Gnauah,</hi> ſignifieth peruerſueſſe or croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked doing; the third <hi>Chatta,</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth to erre or wander from the marke. Men who do weigh ſinne in the balance of conſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, can neuer knowe the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:177902:40"/> weight of it, they eſteeme it but a light thing, but godly men who weigh it in the ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance of the Sanctuarie, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine it according to the rule of the word, find it ſuch a hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible euill as wherein manifold euils doe concurre.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>VERSE. 2.</bibl>
               <q>Waſh me throughly from mine ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, and cleanſe me from my ſinne.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Auid</hi> inſiſts, and <note place="margin">Three things which make feruent Prayer.</note> in other termes hee repeates his former petition: There are three things which make earneſtnes
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:177902:40"/> and feruencie in prayer. Firſt, Conſcience of ſinne. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, feare or ſenſe of wrath. Thirdly, ardent deſire of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie; theſe three were at this time ſtrong in <hi>Dauid,</hi> and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſends hee vp feruent and ſtrong petitions to God.</p>
            <p>More particularly we learne <note place="margin">Sinne, a vile vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe.</note> here, that Sinne is a filthyneſſe which defiles a man, there is no vncleanneſſe can make vs ſo vile, and abhominable in the eyes of man, as ſinne maketh vs in the eyes of God; what more vile thing in the world then a Menſtruous cloth? If euen our righteouſneſſe bee like vnto it, as <hi>Eſay</hi> witneſſeth, I pray you whereunto ſhall our vnrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe be compared, or what ſimilitude can be gotten ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:177902:41"/> to expreſſe it. Now as it is an vncleannes indeed, would to God we could ſo eſteeme of it; we can ſuffer no vncleannes in our bodies, but incontinent we waſh it away; Neither can abide it in our garments, but without delay wee remedie it: yea, the ſmalleſt vncleanneſſe in the veſſels that ſerue vs for meate and drinke, makes our very foode lothſome vnto vs; But alas, wee haue not halfe of that care to keepe our Soules and Conſciences cleane, from the filthy pollution of ſinne, nor yet to waſh them in that Fountaine, opened to DAVIDS houſe for ſinne and for vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe, when we haue defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them.</p>
            <p>And yet a great neceſſitie to
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:177902:41"/> doe ſo, lies vpon vs, for we are <note place="margin">No part can we haue with Christ, if he waſh vs not.</note> warned that no vncleane thing can enter into heauenly <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem.</hi> That anſwere giuen by the Lord Ieſus vnto <hi>Peter,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 13. 8.</note> ſtands for a warning to vs all; If I waſh thee not, thou ſhalt haue no part with me; Oh that it moued vs, as it mooued him, that wee might alſo pray with him. O Lord rather then my vncleannes baniſh me from thy fellowſhip, waſh I beſeech thee not my feete onely, but my hands and my head alſo, Waſh my feete, that is my vncleane affections: Waſh my head, that is my vncleane imaginations and ſenſes. And waſh alſo my hands, that is the vncleanneſſe of mine actions.</p>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:177902:42"/>
            <p> But the word that <hi>Dauid</hi> vſeth <note place="margin">A co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Gods manifold mercies.</note> imports much waſhing, hee knew his ſinne was a deepe ſpot, not eaſily rubbed away, and therefore craues he much waſhing, ſo then, his meaning is, Many ſinnes haſt thou Lord forgiuen me, now I pray thee yet further waſh me from this ſinne alſo. Are thy mercies numbred, or are they ſo nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row that they cannot couer this tranſgreſſion among the reſt, how great ſo euer it bee. So that heere <hi>Dauid</hi> doth ſtill depend vpon the greatneſſe of Gods compaſſion, and by it is he ſuſtained, that the greatnes of his tranſgreſſion driueth him not to deſpare, when the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Peter</hi> enquired at the Lord Ieſus, how oft
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:177902:42"/> ſhall I forgiue my brother in <note place="margin">Since hee will haue vs to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeuen times in the day, what will he doe himſelfe?</note> the day, if he offend me, ſhall I forgiue him ſeuen times? Our Sauiour anſwered, not ſeuen times only, but ſeuenty times ſeuen times alſo. O word full of conſolation, how doth it animate vs to repoſe on the the Lords mercy. <hi>Nonne ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ior Deus homine? nonne melior homine?</hi> Is not the Lord grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then man? is he not better then man? If he will haue ſo great compaſſion in a man to forgiue his brother ſo often in a day: what compaſſion is in himſelfe to forgiue his owne poore penitent creature, that proſtrates himſelfe for mercy before him.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:177902:43"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>VERSE 3</bibl>
               <q>For I know mine iniquity, and my ſinne is euer before me.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Eere is ſubjoined a reaſon of his <note place="margin">Confeſſion from a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent hart obtaines mercy.</note> former petition. O Lord, I doe not hide &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale the iniquitie of my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, I ſeeke not now to couer it as I did before, but now I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge it, and I confeſſe it to thee againſt my ſelfe, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, Lord haue mercy vpon me, and forgiue it: this is a good reaſon, for it is grounded on the Lords promiſe: <hi>He that hideth his ſinnes ſhall not proſper:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 28.</note>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:177902:43"/> 
               <hi>but hee that confeſſeth, and forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth them ſhall haue mercy.</hi> And againe, <hi>If wee confeſſe our ſinnes</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1. 9.</note> 
               <hi>God is faithfull and iuſt to forgiue them.</hi> Or otherwaies we may take vp theſe words as <hi>Vatablus</hi> doth, Lord thou knoweſt that I ſeeke not mercy from thee diſſemblingly, or for faſhion, as the manner of hypocrites is, who make ſupplication for mercy, of cuſtome rather then of contrition, nay Lord I feele my ſinne a burden which trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles me, the very ſight of it ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifies and afraies me, therefore Lord take it away from thee.</p>
            <p>So long as ſinne is in a mans <note place="margin">So long as ſinne is in the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that a man loues it there is no remiſſion of it.</note> affection that hee likes it and hath pleaſure in it, it is but a mocking of God to deſire him to forgiue it, ſhall hee forgiue
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:177902:44"/> that which thou wilt not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe? ſhall he pardon thine of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences ſo long as thou haſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to offend? No, no, vnleſſe thou put thine iniquity from thee out of thine affection, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe thou find it a burden vnto thee whereof thou art weary, goe not to him to ſeeke mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: for ſo his promiſe is, <hi>Come vnto mee all yee that are weary, and laden, and I will refreſh you:</hi> But alas, it is farre otherwiſe with many, who vſe in bab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling manner theſe words of <hi>Dauid.</hi> O Lord conſider my diſtreſſe, when as they had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſuch a thing as a diſtreſſed ſoule for ſinne; and cannot ſay with <hi>Dauid,</hi> I know mine ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity and my ſinne is euer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me.</p>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:177902:44"/>
            <p> But when is this, that <hi>Dauid</hi> 
               <note place="margin">An exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of that deepe ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Gods children may fall.</note> comes to know his ſinne? after that <hi>Nathan</hi> had reproued him without, and God had wakned his owne conſcience within to accuſe him; and this was nine moneths after the committing of the ſin: al this time he ſlept in a careleſſe ſecurity, albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it he haunted the exerciſes of religion, and had ſome general knowledge of his ſinnes, yet it moued him not, till now God lets him ſee an other ſight of his ſinnes, then hee had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <p>In him wee ſee an image of <note place="margin">To ſinne is of our ſelfe, to repent is of grace.</note> our corrupt diſpoſition; wee fall eaſily into ſinne, and when we haue fallen, we can doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but lye ſtill in ſinne, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the Lord put vnder his
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:177902:45"/> mercifull hand and raiſe vs vp. As <hi>Adam</hi> when he had ſinned, ran away from the Lord, ſo is it the manner of <hi>Adams</hi> chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; after ſinne, inſteede of running to the Lord, to runne away alwaies, the longer and the further from him, if the Lord doe not follow and reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them.</p>
            <p>For this is a peece of Satans pollicy that as hee is ſubtill in <note place="margin">Satans poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, firſt drawes a man to ſin then keepes him vnto it.</note> alluring man to commit ſinne, ſo when he hath done it, he la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to blind the minde, that man ſhould neuer come to the knowledge of his ſinne till hee be paſt remedy: a fearefull ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample whereof wee haue in <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das.</hi> And therefore it is a great mercy of God towards his owne, that he opens their eies
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:177902:45"/> in time to ſee their ſinne, ſo long as he ſits vpon his mercy-ſeat to pardon and forgiue them. Satan knows he hath no vantage by ſinne, when true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance followeth it. <hi>For, wher ſinne hath abounded, there grace hath much more ſuper abounded.</hi> It is not ſinne ſo much which condemnes men, as impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency that deſpiſes mercy, and therefore Satan contents not to draw his miſerable captiues into ſinne: but when hee hath done it, hides the ſight of it from them alwaies till the time of grace bee expired, and they bee paſt recouery, then lets he them ſee the vglineſſe of their ſin, and with reſtleſſe torments diſquiets their ſoules for it.</p>
            <p>Further wee ſee heere that
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:177902:46"/> ther are two ſorts of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge <note place="margin">A twofold knowledge of ſinne.</note> of ſin: one which is but general, idle, &amp; works no refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and an other which is effectuall to worke conuerſion. <hi>Dauid,</hi> as I ſaid, before that <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> came to him, he knew that <note place="margin">One, that is idle and workes no remorſe: another, that breeds repentance.</note> murther &amp; adultery were ſins, but that troubled him not. But now God works another know ledge of ſin in him, hee ſees his ſins in another maner, he feeles now the iuſt weight of them, he taſtes now the bitter fruits of them, his ſpirit is filled with anguiſh for them and his ſoule abhors them. It is to be lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that the knoweledge of ſin which now is in moſt part of the world, is but like that knowledge of ſinne which <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> had in time of his ſecurity;
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:177902:46"/> they confeſſe they are ſinners, they know that blaſphemy, drunkenneſſe, fornication, and ſuch like, are ſinnes, but their conſcience being ſleeping, they walke ſtill on in their ſinnes, and thinkes it is Chriſtianity good enough, if euery mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning they ſay, God be merciful to mee, for I am a poore ſinner, but alas poore art thou indeed, and pittifully deceiued, this knowledge will but make thee inexcuſable, becauſe in thy words confeſſing, and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſinne, in thy workes thou practiſeſt it: but there is an other knowledge of ſin, which the Lord ſhall once diſcouer vnto thee, either in mercy for thy amendment, as hee doth heere to <hi>Dauid,</hi> or in wrath, as
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:177902:47"/> he did to <hi>Iudas.</hi> Pray vnto the Lord that this knowledge of ſinne may be giuen you in his mercy for your conuerſion, and not in his wrath for your conſuſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And my ſinne is euer before me,</hi> What meanes <hi>Dauid</hi> by <note place="margin">How ſinne lookes not alway with one face.</note> this? was not ſinne before him ere now? It was indeede ere he committed it, it ſtood before alluring him and hee liked it, and ſought occaſion to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it; when he had commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, it was before him alſo. But it looked with ſo ill fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a face, that hee ſought to hide it, and now when his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is wakened, it ſtood be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, directly to accuſe him and it troubles him ſo, that hee would faine be quit of the ſight
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:177902:47"/> therof. Oh that men could con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider this in time, how ſinne will change her countenance; before the action, ſinne comes like a laughing enemy purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to ſlay, but in flattering manner pretending friendſhip. In the action, like ſweet poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, deadly and yet delights the ſenſe, but after the action a ſtinging Scorpion leauing no other fruit behinde it, but guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe in the conſcience, terror in the minde, anguiſh in the ſpirit. <hi>Si cupis peccati cognoſcere</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chryſ. in Ioan.</hi> 8. <hi>hom.</hi> 51.</note> 
               <hi>turpitudinem, commiſſum conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dera, cum liber non amplius eius perturbaris affectibus,</hi> If men could thinke of this in time, they would not bee much mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with the beautifull face of ſinne, at the firſt comming to
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:177902:48"/> them, becauſe it is certaine that ſinne which at the firſt is before a man to tempt him, and will not let him to reſt till he doe it: that ſame ſinne at the next time ſhal ſtand before him to torment him, and not let him reſt, becauſe hee hath doe it.</p>
            <p>And this he further ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies, <note place="margin">The action of ſinne is momenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of it remaines.</note> when he ſaies, it is euer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, both night and day, ſleeping and waking, go where I will, it goes with mee; no change of place changes my trouble. <hi>Sine intermiſsione vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deo</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Baſil.</note> 
               <hi>malorum meorum imagines,</hi> and it is ſo before me that it is againſt mee, <hi>Semper coram me</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Saua.</note> 
               <hi>opponens ſe mihi, ne ad te tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeat oratio mea.</hi> Sinne is ſoone committed, in a moment paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:177902:48"/> the pleaſure of it, but the gilt, and terror is not ſo ſoone done, <hi>Paruum eſt ad horam pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cyrill, Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſ.</hi> 12.</note> 
               <hi>longaeua autem eſt ex eo, &amp; aeterna verecundia.</hi> That for which a man ſinnes, ſhall not abide with him: try when yee will, yee ſhall finde it ſo; wilt thou ſlay <hi>Naboth</hi> for his Vineycard, thou muſt go from it; wilt thou incurre the curſe with <hi>Achan</hi> for a wedge of gold, thou ſhalt not keepe it, the curſe bides with thee, the gilt of ſinne remaines, but that for which thou didſt ſin, ſhall bee taken from thee, and thou from it. The remembrance of this were a ſingular preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatiue againſt ſinne.</p>
            <p>It is an opinion of carnall men blinded with the deceit of
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:177902:49"/> ſinne, that when ſinne is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, <note place="margin">Sin is not alwaies done when it is ended, as the foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh thinke.</note> they thinke it done, and away, and ſo caſts it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde their backe, as a thing neuer any more to be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred; but truth ſhall teach them by experience, when they are iudged that it is before them. It is now nine moneths ſince <hi>Dauid</hi> ſinned, yet he finds his ſinne before him, the cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſonnes againſt their brother <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> which they committed in <hi>Canaan,</hi> mette them twenty yeeres after that, in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> though for a long time they beleeued it had been done, and forgotten. No <note place="margin">No length of time takes away ſinne with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</note> length of time can we are ſinne away, if it be not taken away by repentance, the ſinnes wee haue done many yeeres ſince,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:177902:49"/> if we mourne not for them till we get mercy, ſhall ſtand vp as freſh and young againſt vs, when we come to bee iudged as they were, the firſt houre that we committed them. The Lord make vs wiſe to thinke vpon it: our ſelues waxe old, our bodies are declyning to the graue, our yeeres are neere an end, and will wee take no paines to weare away our ſins, to make them as if they had neuer beene, or ſhall wee let them ſtand in their ſtrength and vigour againſt vs, this were a pittifull folly which will not faile to trouble vs at the laſt: happy are they who are iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this world, that they be not condemned in the world to come.</p>
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:177902:50"/>
            <p> Further, we note heere the <note place="margin">The folly of ſinners, they redeeme a periſhing pleaſure with an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>during paine.</note> folly of ſinners, and iuſt man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Lords dealing with them; their folly is heere, that that they redeeme a periſhing pleaſure with an enduring paine; Gods iuſtice is here, that he puniſheth the wicked with their owne ſinfull deedes, and lets them eat the fruit of their owne labours. This he threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth by <hi>Ezechiel,</hi> I ſhall turne your waies vpon your owne heads, and truely it were a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment greater then men are able to beare, if the Lord ſhould ſet their iniquities be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, and let them ſee them as they are. Let wicked <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 50.</note> men conſider this, that while they are multiplying ſinnes, they are but pletting coardes,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:177902:50"/> wherewith they ſhall be whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the next day with their owne hands, they are heaping vp wrath to themſelues. No place of complaining againſt the Lords iuſtice, ſhall bee left <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.</note> vnto them, when they ſhall clearely ſee, it is their owne iniquitie that vexeth and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments them.</p>
            <p>But now ſeeing <hi>Nathan</hi> the <note place="margin">Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of sinne, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the godly, and why.</note> Prophet had proclaimed to <hi>Dauid</hi> the remiſſion of his ſin, how is it, that yet it is before him? I anſwere, in his deereſt children after remiſſion of ſin, he will haue the remembrance of ſinne to remaine; Firſt, to keepe them in minde of God his great mercie, who ſlewe them not in their ſinnes, as hee hath done many, that ſo hee
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:177902:51"/> may make them the more thankfull. <hi>Vt gratior ſit miſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordia dei, vt ſentias quid tibi</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note> 
               <hi>conceſſerit. Si enim ſemper me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor fuer is cumuli peccatorum tuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, eris etiam memor magnitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinis beneficentiae dei.</hi> Next the memorie of ſinne paſt, ſerues as a preſeruatiue to keepe Gods children from the like ſinnes in time to come. And thirdly, it teacheth vs to haue compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on others, when they fall in the like ſinnes, and to reſtore them with the ſpirit of meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, conſidering alſo our ſelues.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="87" facs="tcp:177902:51"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>VERSE. 4.</bibl>
               <q>Againſt thee, againſt thee onely haue I ſinned, and done euill in thy ſight, that thou maieſt be iuſt, when thou ſpeakeſt, and pure, when thou iudgeſt.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow <hi>Dauid</hi> breks forth, and giues <note place="margin">Confeſſion of ſinne moſt need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</note> glorie to God, by an open and plain Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion of his ſins, he knew it was need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for him to doe ſo; Becauſe remiſſion of ſinnes, is promiſed vpon a condition of the confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of them. <hi>He that hideth his</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prouerb.</note> 
               <hi>ſinnes ſhall not proſper, but he that confeſſeth and forſake them, ſhall</hi>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:177902:52"/> 
               <hi>haue mercie.</hi> And againe, <hi>If we confeſſe our ſinnes, God is faithfull</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 1. 9.</note> 
               <hi>to forgiue them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But here we haue firſt to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, <note place="margin">Before men confeſsion defileth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God it cleanſeth.</note> why is it that God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires confeſſion, is it to get knowledge of that which wee haue done? Or to get out of our owne mouth, a point of Dittie againſt our ſelues? <hi>Nouit omnia Deus, ſed expectat vocem</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amb. de paenitent. li.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 7.</note> 
               <hi>tuam, non vt puniat, ſed vt ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſcat.</hi> He knowes all things, when thou committedſt thy ſinne in ſecret, hee ſaw thee, what then craueth he? nothing but that thou in thy heart mayeſt know thy ſinne; In thy mouth maieſt confeſſe it to the end, that he may forgiue it. <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat ſoluere confitentes, ne contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maces punire cogatur.</hi> The beſt <note place="margin">Augu.</note>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:177902:52"/> medicine for a ſinne, is not to hide, or excuſe, or extenuate it, but humbly to confeſſe it. <hi>Que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>admodum nobis peccatorum vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nera nunquam deſunt, ſic &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsionis medicamenta deeſſe non debent.</hi> For it is not with the Lord as it is with men, before earthly Tribunales confeſſion of ſinne defileth the confeſſor, makes him guiltie and culpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but before the heauenly it abſolues him. And this is the cauſe why the Lord requires confeſſion of a ſin from man.</p>
            <p>Now we haue to ſee what <note place="margin">Priuate ſins in what caſe ſhould they be publikely confeſſed.</note> ſort of confeſſion pleaſeth God, ſeeing it is certaine, confeſſion of ſinne hath beene made by many, which the Lord hath not accepted; here firſt wee muſt diſtinguiſh the ſinnes to
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:177902:53"/> be confeſſed, publicke ſinnes whereby God is openly diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured, and his Church ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, out of all doubt required a publike confeſſion to God, and before men; In priuate ſins the confeſſion is required to God only: <hi>Plerum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> non expedit</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ber. m. Cant. ſer.</hi> 42.</note> 
               <hi>innoteſcere omnibus, omnia quae nos ſcimus de nobis, atque ipſa charitatis veritate &amp; veritatis charitate, vetamur, palam fieri velle, quod noceat agnoſcenti:</hi> yet with this exception, that when the priuate ſin is done in ſuch a maner, as that the euill thereof redounds to the hurt of many, and that for this cauſe alſo God perſewes it to bring it to light, in this caſe priuate ſinnes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by thee, knowen to none but to thy ſelfe ſhould be
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:177902:53"/> publikly confeſſed, that thou mayeſt giue glory to God, and doe good to his Church as is euident in the example of <hi>Achan</hi> and <hi>Dauid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next wee muſt take heed to <note place="margin">Three things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in the trew confeſſion of ſinne. Ber.</note> the manner of the confeſſion, if it be trew, it muſt haue theſe three properties. Firſt it muſt proceed from contrition of the ſpirit for ſinne: <hi>Primum opus fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dei</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Contrition.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>per dilectionem operantis, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punctio cordis est, è quo ſine dubio eij ciuntur daemonia, cum eradican<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur è corde peccata,</hi> confeſſion of ſin in the mouth, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedes not from contrition for ſinne in the heart, will neuer draw downe mercy to thee, more then it did to Saule, whoſe mouth ſaid, I haue ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, but his heart was not grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:177902:54"/> for ſin. Secondly, true con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion <note place="margin">2. <hi>Faith.</hi>
               </note> proceedes from faith in Chriſt Ieſus, for there is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion which is the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of deſperation, and can not profit thee: An example wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we haue in Iudas, <hi>I haue ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in betraying of innocent blood,</hi> but wanting faith he got no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of his ſinne. And third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, true confeſſion hath alway <note place="margin">3. <hi>Correction.</hi>
               </note> with it an amendment of life: o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe <hi>Confeſsio ſine emenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione vitae est profeſsio peccati,</hi> confeſſion of ſinne without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment is a profeſſion of ſinne, thou that euery day confeſſeſt ſin, and yet walkeſt on in the ſame ſinnes, art no other, but a plaine profeſſor of ſinne. <note place="margin">A threefold happy fruit of true con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now confeſſion of ſin with
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:177902:54"/> theſe properties, brings downe to the penitent ſinner, a three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold fruit: firſt vnion and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation with God enſewes, for ſin the cauſe of diuiſion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene God and man is now remoued, <hi>quaſi duaeres ſunt homo</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Augu. in Ioan. Tract.</hi> 12.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; peccator, quod audis (homo) deus fecit, quod audis (peccator) homo ipſe fecit, dele quid fecisti, vt ſaluet deus quod fecit:</hi> Man and ſinne are two ſundry things, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy ſinne which is man his <note place="margin">1. <hi>It reconciles thee with God.</hi>
               </note> worke, and God can not but loue, and embrace man, as his owne worke. So long as man keepes his ſinne, he workes di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectlie againſt the Lord, hyding that which God will diſcouer, and harbouring within him the rebel, whom God is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſewing, but when man turnes
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:177902:55"/> againſt ſin, confeſſing it, bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to light, that it may be deſtroyed, then works he with <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> God, <hi>qui Confitetur peccata ſua et accuſat, iam cum deo facit, accuſat deus peccata tua &amp; ſi tu accuſas, iam coniungeris deo.</hi> Yea, he that in humble manner confeſſeth, giueth to the Lord the praiſe of iuſtice, that knowes if hee did continew in theſe ſinnes the Lord ought to puniſh him, he giues him alſo the praiſe of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, that no ſecret thing can be hid from the Lord, and the praiſe of power, hee knowes there is no way to flee from the Lord, and therefore in time he flies to him, and at laſt he giues him the praiſe of mercy, that hee is gracious and readie to forgiue.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:177902:55"/>
               <l>Bis deum laudamus,</l>
               <l>vbi pie nos accuſamus.</l>
            </q>
            <p>The ſecond fruit of it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion <note place="margin">2. <hi>It brings Confusion to Satan.</hi>
               </note> to Sathan, it is a chiefe point of his labour to accuſe vs night and day, for in one of theſe three he is alway exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, either to tempt, or to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe or to torment, when hee tempts let vs reſiſt him, that we ſinne not, if we haue ſinned, let vs preuent the accuſer, and bee the firſt accuſers of our ſelues, ſo ſhall we ſtop the mouth of our aduerſarie, that hee ſhall haue nothing to ſay. <hi>Non cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumueniet te ante iudicem, cum e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim tui ipſe fueris accuſator, &amp; dominus liberator, quid erit ille niſi calumniator?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:177902:56"/>
            <p> The third is that true con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion which brings comfort, <note place="margin">It brings peace and quietneſſe to a mans owne heart.</note> peace, and quietneſſe to a mans owne heart. As a ſicke ſtomack is eaſed by vomiting, ſo a guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty conſcience by confeſſion. They who will not ſow, how can they reape? we muſt ſow in teares, the humble confeſſion of ſinne, if we looke to reap the ſweet conſolation of the ſpirit, let vs not do the one ſparingly, if wee hope to enioy the other abundantly, <hi>Modica Sementis</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ber.</note> 
               <hi>de tractio, non modicum meſsis est detrimentum.</hi> So long as wee keepe in the heart the pleaſures of ſinne, we can not taſte of the ioyes of God. <hi>Vis vt intret mel,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Aug.</note> 
               <hi>vnde acetum nondum fudiſti? funde quod habes, vt capias, quod non habes,</hi> no more then it is
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:177902:56"/> poſſible to powre ſweet hony into that veſſel, which is filled with ſowre Vineger already, but as after great ſhowres of raine, the aire becomes more calme and cleare, ſo after that ſinne is powred out with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion and teares, the heart is pacified, and freed from her former perturbations.</p>
            <p>Furthermore wee perceiue <note place="margin">Publike ſins would haue publike re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</note> here, how <hi>Dauid</hi> contents not himſelfe with a ſecret confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his ſinne to the Lord, and to <hi>Nathan</hi> the Prophet, but wil haue his repentance declared in publike, and a memoriall of it extant for benefite of the Church of God. No doubt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny impediments had <hi>Dauid</hi> to hinder him from ſo cleare a confeſſion, but ſuch is the force
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:177902:57"/> of true repentance, that it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercomes all impediments and maketh the penitent man har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily well content to giue glory to God, although it were with neuer ſo great ſhame to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Such as had fallen in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like offenſes were not receiued <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The forme and order of publike repentance in the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue church. Ambros de paenitent. li.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 16.</note> but vpon their publike repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, yea and their ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made to all the aſſembly of Gods people, <hi>Petat veniam reus cum lachrym is, petat gemiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, petat populi totius fletibus, vt ignoſcatur obſecret &amp; cum ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, aut tertio fuerit dilata eius communio, credat ſeremiſsius ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicaſſe, fletus augeat.</hi> Let him that is guilty ſeeke pardon with teares, ſeeke it with grones, let him ſeeke that all the people
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:177902:57"/> may mourne for him, and if twice or thrice his receiuing to the communion be delaied, let him thinke he hath praied but ſlackly, and hath neede to aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment his teares, and becauſe many then thought ſhame to doe this, he giues them a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table admonition, <hi>Si homini ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfacien dum</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 10.</note> 
               <hi>eſſet, multos obſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res vt dignentur interuenire, hoc in eccleſia facere faſtidis, vt deo ſupplices, vt patrocinium tibi ad deum obſecrandum ſanctae plebis requiras,</hi> if thou hadeſt to doe with men, thou wouldeſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt many to ſue for thee, thinkeſt thou euill to doe that in the Church, to make there ſupplication to God, and to ſeeke the helpe of the Saints of God. <hi>Vbi nihil est quod pudari</hi>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:177902:58"/> 
               <hi>eſſe debeat, niſi non fateri, cum om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſimus peccatores, vbi ille lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dabilior, qui humilior; &amp; iustior qui abiectior, fleat ita<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> pro te Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter eccleſia,</hi> where there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing wherof we ſhould thinke ſhame except not to confeſſe our ſins, ſeeing wee are all ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and he is moſt worthy of praiſe who is moſt abiect. Let therefore thy mother the Church mourne vnto God for thee.</p>
            <p>It is a common policie of <note place="margin">Sathan takes away ſhamewhere it ſhould be, and brings it in where it ſhould not be.</note> Sathan, to take away ſhame where it ſhould bee, namely in the committing of it; and to bring it in where it ſhould not be, to wit, in the confeſſing of ſinne: But if men bee mooued with ſhame, I would wiſh they were mooued with the greateſt
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:177902:58"/> ſhame, for it is a greater ſhame to confeſſe ſin before the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and the whole world, God ſitting in his iudgement ſeate to condemne it, then to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe it before his Church, God ſitting in his mercie ſeate, readie to forgiue it. Concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led can it not be, for the word of God hath confirmed it with a ſolemne oath. <hi>As I liue</hi> (ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Lord) <hi>euery tongue ſhall confeſſe vnto me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Two wayes in this verſe, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>By two argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid <hi>ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth his ſin.</hi>
               </note> doth <hi>Dauid</hi> amplifie his ſinne: firſt that it was done againſt God, Next in the ſight of God. To ſin againſt a King his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement lawfull, is a great ſinne, but to ſinne againſt him in his owne face, is a double re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion. Sin is counted a light
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:177902:59"/> thing among men, becauſe they commonly weigh it in <hi>Statera ſuarum conſuetudinum</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug. cont. Parmen. lib</hi> 3. <hi>Cap.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>doloſa,</hi> The deceitfull balance of cuſtome: but if we come and weigh it in the balance of Gods word, wee ſhall finde it heauie, which otherwayes wee thinke light.</p>
            <p>This firſt circumſtance that <note place="margin">That it was done againſt God.</note> it was againſt God, doth great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aggrauate his ſinne. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ye looke to the goodneſſe, or to the greatneſſe of God. The Lord was good many waies to <hi>Dauid,</hi> of a Sheepheard he made him a King; and did in euery ſtate of life ſo bleſſe him, that as hee himſefe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth, hee was loaded with the benefits of God. Now it cannot bee but a great ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:177902:59"/> to offend ſo louing and gracious a God, who daily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights to doe good vnto vs.</p>
            <p>Or otherwiſe if we conſider his greatneſſe wee muſt ſay it <note place="margin">What a fearfull thing it is to fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God.</note> is a fearefull thing to fall into the hands of the Lord. <hi>Are we ſtronger then hee? why then doe wee prouoke him to anger?</hi> This is a great argument of his power, that hee turnes againſt vs thoſe things which wee doe againſt him, and puniſheth vs with our owne deedes. <hi>Thine own wickedneſſe ſhall correct thee,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ierem.</hi> 2. 19</note> 
               <hi>and thy turnings backe ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue thee, and thou ſhall know that it is an euill thing, and a bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that thou haſt forſaken the Lord thy God, and procured this</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 17.</note> 
               <hi>vnto thy ſelfe.</hi> The <hi>Sidonians</hi> ſought peace from <hi>Herode</hi>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:177902:60"/> when hee entended warre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, and all becauſe they were nouriſhed by <hi>Herods</hi> lands, and might not want his fauour: and fooliſh man thinkes it nothing to fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, who is offring him peace, which is ſo great a good, that he is able to driue backe mans weapons vpon his owne face, and confound him with his owne thoughts.</p>
            <p>But heere it is to be deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>How ſaies</hi> Dauid <hi>hee ſinned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God onlie, ſeeing hee ſlew</hi> V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riah, <hi>and defiled</hi> Bathſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath.</note> how ſaies he that hee ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt God onely, ſeeing he ſinned againſt <hi>Bathſheba,</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſing her to the ſnare of Satan: he ſinned againſt <hi>Vriah,</hi> whom he ſlew with the ſword of the <hi>Ammonite;</hi> and he ſinned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the whole Army, caſting them into danger for <hi>Vriah</hi> his
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:177902:60"/> ſake: and laſtly, againſt the whole Church in his kingdome by his euill example. The an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer <note place="margin">1 <hi>In all ſinne God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly is the party offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</hi>
               </note> is, that to ſpeake proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, In all ſinne, properly God is the party offended; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be done imediatly, as in ſinnes againſt the firſt Table, or mediatly, as in ſinnes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſecond table: and ſo the wrong done to the creature is not for the hurt of ſuch a creture, but for the interceding command of God, which is broken, for ſinne is the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion of the Law; and were it not for that, no wrong were <note place="margin">2. Dauid <hi>ſpeaks this acording to his ſenſe, for at this time he had no party, but God.</hi>
               </note> done to the creature.</p>
            <p>Next <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeakes this, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his owne ſenſe and feeling, at this time he had no partie that troubled him, but
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:177902:61"/> the Lord, for as to him that got the wrong, <hi>Non timebam</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note> 
               <hi>eum, miles meus erat, non poterat me iudicare.</hi> He was my ſeruant he could not iudge mee. As for others, <hi>Rex ſum, caeterorum omnium Dominus, te ſolum com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſorum</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uthym.</note> 
               <hi>a me ſcelerum iudicem habeo.</hi> I am their King and Lord, and finde nothing in them to trouble me, but thou O Lord, art hee to whom all creatures muſt render an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, thou art higher then the higheſt, and iudgeſt the King and the ſubiect alike. What peace then can<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> bee to mee, ſo long as thou art a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt mee, purſuing mee for my ſinnes.</p>
            <p>Heereof firſt ariſes, a leſſon to men of power in the world,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:177902:61"/> let them not thinke the leſſe of <note place="margin">Let not men thinke the leſſe of their ſinnes, becauſe they are done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt weak men.</note> their ſinnes, becauſe they haue to doe with a weake partie, that hath neither power nor meanes to redreſſe their wrongs; let them remember, that God is their party, who will iudge the cauſe of the poore, the widowe, and the fatherleſſe: this ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain them from doing wrong to any, albeit they might doe it vncontrouled of men; this was a meanes of awe to <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> he might haue reuenged the wrong in <hi>Egypt</hi> which his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren had done him in <hi>Canaan,</hi> but hee would not becauſe hee feared God, and conſidered that hee himſelfe was alſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God.</p>
            <p>Secondly, wee learne of this
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:177902:62"/> that ſeeing in all ſinne, God is <note place="margin">No diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of ſinne is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient but the Lords.</note> the party offended; the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion and diſcharge of the ſinne ſhould bee ſought from him. This is for theſe carnall Atheiſts, who if they can ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine pardon from the earthly Iudge; or a diſcharge of the partie, care nothing for the Lords part, but hee will ſtand to his own part and make thee finde by experience, that albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it all the world would forgiue thy ſinne, yet if the Lord for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue thee not, it ſhal nothing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile thee. <note place="margin">Men of meane e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate ſhould haue patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce when they are wronged becauſe the offence is done vnto God.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Laſt of all, let this learne them of meane eſtate patience, for no wrong can be done vnto them, which firſt of all is not done to the Lord, he is the principal party offended. If men could,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:177902:62"/> as I haue ſaid before, ponder this, it might learne them with patience to commit their cauſe to the Lord, and not raſhly to ſtep in into his roome, either by imprecations, or raylings, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other ſuch carnall meane, but to reſerue vnto the Lord his owne honour. <hi>Vengeance is mine and I will repay it, ſaith the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And done euell in thy ſight.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>The other argument whereby he amplifies his ſinne, is that it was done in Gods ſight.</hi>
               </note> The other circumſtance wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by hee amplifies his ſinne, is, that it was done in the ſight of God: when hee did the ſinne, God ſaw him, but hee forgot then that God was looking vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him: but now when his conſcience is wakened, and hee lookes backe againe to his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer iniquity, he ſees now that
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:177902:63"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:177902:63"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:177902:64"/> he did it in the ſight of God.</p>
            <p>This is alſo one of Satan his <note place="margin">Satans de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit is to make man conceiue that God ſeeth him not.</note> cuſtomable policies whereby he drawes men vnto ſinne to couer their minds with a vaile to darken their vnderſtanding, to ſteale out of their hearts the remembrance, at leaſt the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence of the diuine Maieſty, ſo that he is brought to thinke for a time, that either God ſees it not, or then doth not regard it. But this is a pittifull blinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, like the folly of children, who when their owne eies are cloſed that they cannot ſee, do therefore conceit that none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeeth them: ſo is it, I ſay with them whoſe affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are captiued by a ſin, they are blinded and haue not an eye to looke vp to God, and
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:177902:64"/> therefore thinke that hee is not looking down vpon them.</p>
            <p>The beſt remedy for this is to ſanctifie the Lord alwaies in <note place="margin">The reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of God is a new band to ſinne.</note> our hearts, let vs ſet the Lord alwaies in our ſight, eſteeming of euery place as <hi>Iacob</hi> did of <hi>Bethel,</hi> The Lord is in this place, and I was not aware, that ſo his countenance may bee an newe band to keepe vs from ſinne, otherwiſe it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee but a deepe contempt of God, when in our eſtimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on wee ſet him inferiour to his creature, not aſhamed to doe that vnder the eye of GOD, which wee would be aſhamed to doe vnder the eie of man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That thou maieſt be iuſt.</hi> His <note place="margin">The Lord ſtrikes not without a cauſe.</note> meaning is not, that he ſinned for this ende: that God might
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:177902:65"/> be iuſtified, <hi>quod dicit vt iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceris, non habet cauſae ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem, non eam ob cauſam peccauit</hi> Dauid, <hi>vt Deus iuſtificaretur.</hi> No, but that for this end hee confeſſed his ſinne, that the iuſtice of God, iudging, repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, and threatning him by <hi>Nathan,</hi> might bee manifeſted to others. It is not Lord with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe that thou haſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced ſo ſharpe puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments againſt mee, by thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant <hi>Nathan, Ego haec mihi ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la conciliaui,</hi> I haue deſerued them all, and giuen thee iuſt cauſe to ſpeake and iudge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt mee as thou haſt done, and now I humbly confeſſe it before the world, that thou maieſt haue the praiſe of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes in all thy ſpeaking, &amp; iudging.</p>
            <pb n="113" facs="tcp:177902:65"/>
            <p> The children of God hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled <note place="margin">Men viſited with his rods ſhould giue him the prayſe of righteouſnes</note> with a ſenſe of their ſins, ſpare not to ſhame themſelues that they may glorifie God. So <hi>Daniel</hi> aſcribeth ſhame and confuſion to himſelfe and his people, but giues tho praiſe of righteouſneſſe to the Lord. Where the Lord ſtrikes with his rods which men may ſee, and hee that is ſtriken will not acknowledge his ſinnes, in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect hee blames the Lord, as if hee did ſtrike without a cauſe; therefore <hi>Ioſua,</hi> when <hi>Achan</hi> was taken by <hi>Lot</hi> for his ſinne, and the wrath of God on Iſrael was manifeſt, but the cauſe procuring the wrath, was hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den from them, exhorted him to giue glory to God, thou ſeeſt doth he, ſay that God is angrie
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:177902:66"/> with Iſrael, he hath ſuffered his people to fall before their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, this cannot be without a cauſe: ſeeing the lot is fallen vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee, and the finger of God points at thee, that thou haſt procured this euill. I pray thee giue glorie to God, by confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the ſinne thou haſt done, that all the people may knowe that the Lord is not angrie without cauſe. It is a danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous thing to hide our ſinnes, where the hiding of them, may hide and obſcure the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of God; as the maner of hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites is, who grudge and murmure when God ſtrikes them with his rods, as if either they were puniſhed without a cauſe, or then worſe handled, then they had deſerued.</p>
            <pb n="115" facs="tcp:177902:66"/>
            <p> Againe, let vs marke here <note place="margin">Happie are they whom God iudges now in ſuch ſort that he corrects them.</note> the manner of God his dealing with his own, he iudgeth them in this life, that they ſhould not be condemned hereafter. This he doth partly by his word, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proouing them of ſinne; partly by his rods, correcting them. Happie are they who now are ſo iudged, for they who profit not, neither by his rebukes nor his rods; what elſe doe they, but reſerue them ſelues to a ſharper iudgment.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="116" facs="tcp:177902:67"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>VERSE. 5.</bibl>
               <q>Behold I was borne in iniquitie, and in ſinne hath my mother conceiued me.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>E ſtill proceedes <note place="margin">Dauid <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches out the firſt origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall of his ſinne.</hi>
               </note> in the amplifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of his ſin, and now he rip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth it vp from the verie foutaine and firſt ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal thereof, entring in a deep conſideration of the vniuerſall corruption of his Nature. It is not in this fact onely will hee ſay that I am culpable, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe my whole Nature to bee ſo corrupt from the verie wombe through ſinne, as moſt
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:177902:67"/> iuſtly making me odious &amp; ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable in the eyes of God, yea now when by occaſion of this one ſinne, which hath bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out in externall action, I looke to my inward diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and conſider the originall corruption of my nature con-containing all ſorts of ſin with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it, proceeding from the want and priuation of originall righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, I am aſhamed of my ſelfe in the ſight of God.</p>
            <p>To expreſſe this he vſes two wordes; the firſt <hi>Cholel</hi> ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">
                  <hi>How origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſinne is expreſſed by</hi> Dauid.</note> to creat or forme, whereby he will declare that euen in his forming in the wombe, he was infected with ſinne, the other is <hi>Iacham</hi> ſignifying to warme: thereby declaring that while hee was warmed, foſtered and
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:177902:68"/> nouriſhedde in his mothers wombe, hee was defiled with ſin originall. At the beginning hee was but an vncleane Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>Where we are not to thinke <note place="margin">Mariage is not blamed, when it is ſaid that man was conceiued and borne in ſinne.</note> that hee accuſes the formation or foſtering of a birth in the mothers wombe, theſe are the great and maruailous workes of God. Neither yet that hee reiects the blame on his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, or condemnes mariage, or vſe of the mariage-bed, theſe are the ordinances of God. <hi>Non</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug. cont. Pelag. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 21. <hi>De nupt. et concupiſcen.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>eſt malum quod natus es, ſed cum quo natuses.</hi> And againe, <hi>Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra humana quae de coniugio naſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, opus eſt Dei.</hi> And to this ſame purpoſe ſaid <hi>Baſil, non ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſat</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Baſil.</note> 
               <hi>hic nuptias, ſicut quidam ſtulte ſunt ſuſpicati. Sed praeuari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cationem</hi>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:177902:68"/> 
               <hi>quae ab initio mundi a progenitoribus noſtris eſt commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa, in medium producit, &amp; hanc fontem eſſe factam ipſorum fluen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum dicit.</hi> Hee doth not here accuſe mariage, as ſome haue fooliſhly ſuſpected, but the tranſgreſſion commited by our firſt Progenitors, he brings out as the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tain of al theſe flouds of iniquitie, that ſince ſinne haue broken out in our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>Here firſt we may perceiue, <note place="margin">The rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke by which godly men moue the Lord to mercie.</note> what is the Rhetoricke, which godly men vſe whereby they would mooue the Lord to bee mercifull vnto them, namely to preſent to the eies of his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion their heauy diſeaſes and the deep, wide, and inueterate wounds which they haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:177902:69"/> from their deadly ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, let vs learne by their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample not to couer nor hide our ſinnes, if wee would haue mercie. A wiſe man deſires his wound to be ripped vp, and not to bee ouerplaiſtred, albeit the Phyſitian would forget it, hee wil remember and requeſt him to doe it. How much more ſhould we lay open our wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds to Chriſt, that hee may cure them, he is that ſweet <hi>Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan</hi> who at the firſt ſight of the wounds of that poore Trauel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler betwene <hi>Iericho</hi> and <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> was moued to compaſſion and powred wine and oyle in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his wounds, when Prieſt nor Leuit had pitie vpon him, what mercie here he preached in that parable, he hath it ready to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:177902:69"/> vpon all that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a penitent and beleeuing heart, preſent their miſeries vnto him.</p>
            <p>Secondly, wee ſee heere how <note place="margin">Particular ſinnes moue the godly to a deteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the whole cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of Nature.</note> theſe particular ſinnes of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> leades him to a narrower inquiſition and greater deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the whole corruption of his nature, thus the children of God are moued by ſome particular ſinnes, wherein they are fallen to grow in the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of all ſinnes whatſoeuer. Whereas by the contrary car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall men excuſe their particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar ſinnes by the common cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of mans nature, as if their ſinnes, were the leſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all men by nature are ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, but they deceiue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, for the leſſe they thinke of their ſinnes, the more ſhall
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:177902:70"/> God thinke of them when he ſhall viſit them, let vs not ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringly iudge our ſelues, if wee would haue the Lord merciful vnto vs.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, ſince this is true in <note place="margin">What great neede man hath to be changed out of Natures eſtate.</note> vs all, that we were conceiued, and borne in ſinne, what great need haue we of regeneration: <hi>for vnleſſe a man be borne again, hee can not ſee the kingdome of God?</hi> Let natural parents who haue been inſtruments to their children of a naturall generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whereby they are borne heires of the wrath of God, do what lies in them by prayer and good education to make them pertakers of regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, otherwaies they will curſe the loines that got them, and the wombe that bare them,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:177902:70"/> and children againe who glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in the external priuiledges of blood and heritage, which they haue gotten from their parents, let them remember vnleſſe they be borne againe, it had beene better for them ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to haue beene borne.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>VERSE. 6.</bibl>
               <q>Behold thou louest truth in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward affections, and haste taught me wiſedome in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret of mine heart.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>E proceedes ſtill <note place="margin">The vile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſin appeares in this, that it is contrary to Gods ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> to amplifie his ſinne by conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of that contrary holie diſpoſition, which is in God:
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:177902:71"/> the Lord is holy, his eye is ſo pure that it cannot behold ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, he loueth truth and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights in the holineſſe, and cleanneſſe of the heart, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las I am vncleane, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſo much the more miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that my diſpoſition is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to his.</p>
            <p>Of this wee learne that the <note place="margin">The true knowledge of God workes true humility.</note> beſt way to humble vs in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of that ſinfull corruption which is in vs, is the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, when <hi>Eſay</hi> in a viſion ſaw the maieſty of God as it pleaſed him to ſhew it, then he cried out woe is me. I am a man of polluted lippes, he knew before that he was a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full man, but a new ſight of God his holineſſe, diſcouers to him a deeper ſight of his owne
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:177902:71"/> corruption, the ſpots of the face not perceiued in darkneſſe, are manifeſted in the day, and then doe men thinke ſhame of them, when they are diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the light. So long as the eye lookes to the earth, and creatures which are in it, it ſeemes to be quicke enough but turne it vpward toward the ſunne, the weakneſſe of it is ſoone perceiued: when wee looke to our ſelues, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare our ſelues with our ſelues, and with men like our ſelues, we ſeeme to be ſome thing, but if our eyes were open to ſee the Lord, and that moſt excellent purity and holineſſe which is in him, then would we cry out with Iob. <hi>Now mine eies hath ſeene the Lord, therefore I abhor</hi>
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:177902:72"/> 
               <hi>my ſelfe.</hi> The holy Angels co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer their faces at the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his glory, what ſhall man doe who is duſt and dwelles in lodgings of clay?</p>
            <p>Againe, ſeeing God loues <note place="margin">Sin is but a lying vanity.</note> truth in the inward affections, let vs alſo ſtudy to loue it, for in a conformity with God ſtandeth mans felicity. By truth heere wee vnderſtand two things: holineſſe, and ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, oppoſite to ſinne, and hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie: ſinne is in very deede but a lie, a falſhood, and a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, and therefore ſo named by the ſpirit of God. It ſeemes to be an other thing then it is indeed, al that to this day haue beene inamoured with it, haue found it in the end to be but a lying vanitie, and yet vaine
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:177902:72"/> man cannot learne to deſpiſe the deceit thereof.</p>
            <p>And this euill becomes ſo <note place="margin">Then is it worſt when it is couered with hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie.</note> much the worſe, when it lurk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vnder a ſhew of holineſſe, hypocriſie is a generall lie of the whole man. In a common lie the tongue lies againſt the heart onely, but in hypocriſie not the tongue onely, but the eye, the hand, the feet lie alſo, when the hand is lifted vp to heauen, and eye lookes vp, but the heart followes them not, when the knee is bowed, but the heart is not bowed before the Lord.</p>
            <p>Nothing diſtinguiſhes a true <note place="margin">The proper difference of a true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian from a counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit.</note> chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from a counterfeit, but this truth, and ſincerity in the inward affections, the baſtard Chriſtian can counterfeit the
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:177902:73"/> true Chriſtians behauiour in al things, but he cannot follow him in this one, the ſincerity of his heart. As a Painter can paint the cullour of the fire, and the forme of the flame thereof, but cannot paint the heate of it, ſo a hypocrite can reſemble a Chriſtian in any thing, but not in his heart. <hi>Eſau</hi> can mourne and weep bitterly like <hi>Ezechia: Ahab</hi> can put on ſack cloth, like <hi>Mordecai, Saul</hi> can confeſſe in word, I haue ſinned, like <hi>Dauid,</hi> but none of their hearts were vpright in the ſight of God.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, when wee heare <note place="margin">If the Lord require truth in vs, how much more is he true him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe-</note> that God loues truth we may conſider that hee is true or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther truth it ſelfe, what hee loues in his creature is but a
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:177902:73"/> ſparkle of that goodnes, which is in himſelf, we haue here then ſtrong conſolation againſt our naturall doubtings, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſts, if we conſider how God is verity. Of his nature he can not breake his promiſe, if he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire ſuch conſtant truth in his <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.</note> creature, that when he ſweares, he wil not haue him to change, but to performe the good which he promiſes, how much more may wee looke to finde this truth in himſelfe?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore thou hast taught me wiſedome.</hi> This is the laſt argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <note place="margin">An other amplifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uids ſinne, it was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</note> wherby <hi>Dauid</hi> amplifies his ſinne, that hee had done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that knowledge, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with God had indewed him, for the Lord had delt fauoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie with him, and had taught
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:177902:74"/> him the knowledge of his will, but he like a beaſt ſuffered that light to be ſuffocated by the fury of his owne affections.</p>
            <p>Of this we ſee that the light <note place="margin">A fearefull thing to ſin againſt knowledge.</note> which God giues men, if they do againſt it, is a great augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of their ſin, <hi>The ſeruant that knoweth his maſters will and doth it not, is worthy of double ſtripes:</hi> If I had not come, and ſpoken to you, ye ſhould haue had no ſinne, the Gentiles who had no more but the light of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uinced, becauſe that when they knew God, they <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.</note> glorified him not as God: what then ſhall become of vs, who beſide the light of nature haue alſo the light of the goſpell, if ſtill we walke in darkneſſe, it ſhall certainly aggrauate our
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:177902:74"/> ſinne, and make our condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation more fearefull, then that of <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorrha.</hi> From which, the Lord of his great mercy preſerue vs.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>VERSE. 7.</bibl>
               <q>Purge me with Hyſſop and I ſhall be cleane, waſh mee and I ſhall be whiter then ſnow.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter that DAVID <note place="margin">After con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion the godly ioine petition for mercy, not ſo the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked.</note> had made a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of his ſin, and that not cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, or for faſhion, as they doe, whoſe conſciences are not wakened with the ſight of their ſinnes, but had by all circumſtances aggrauated his
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:177902:75"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:177902:75"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:177902:76"/> ſinne, now hee returnes to his petition of mercy.</p>
            <p>This hyſſop, wherewith <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The hyſſop by which</hi> Dauid <hi>craues to be purged.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Dauid</hi> craueth to be purged, it is as <hi>Baſil</hi> cals it, <hi>Alterius reioe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigma.</hi> Naturall hyſſop is an hearb <hi>humilis, calida, &amp; odorife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra,</hi> of excellent vertue in medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, <hi>Eſt enim in hyſſopo vis pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatoria</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug. de doct. chriſt. lib.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>maxime pulmonum.</hi> The typicall vſe of it in the ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall Law was threefold; firſt, the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſprinkled the poſts of their dores, with a bunch of hyſſop dipped in the bloud of the Paſchall Lambe: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.</note> ſecondly, a bunch of hyſſoppe dipped in bloud, was vſed in the beſprinkling and cleanſing of the Leper: and thirdly, in the Sacrifice for ſinne. <hi>Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leuit.</hi> 14.</note> 19.</p>
            <pb n="133" facs="tcp:177902:76"/>
            <p> All theſe were typicall, and did ſignifie no other, but that <note place="margin">All typicall purgations figure the blood of Chriſt.</note> all his people ſhould looke for purgation from all their lepro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie and vncleanneſſe in the blood of the Lambe Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus: who takes away the ſinnes of the world, and his blood clenſeth from all ſinne. <hi>Dauid</hi> knew that theſe were types and figures inſtituted for ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of better things, and therefore did hee not neglect them, yet on the other part, he would not leane vnto them, as if remiſſion of ſinnes were to be gotten by theſe Legall pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, but by them he aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the ſpirituall thing ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified by them, hee had enough of the typicall hyſſop at his commandement, and
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:177902:77"/> the Prieſt ready to ſpinkle him with it, when it pleaſed him, but he knew this would not ſerue his turne, he lookes to the Spirituall hyſſop, and hee praies that God would purge him, without which no Leuiticall waſhing could make him cleane.</p>
            <p>The Spirituall hyſſop then <note place="margin">The pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging vertue of Chriſts bloud.</note> full of bloud, is Chriſt Ieſus. <hi>Qui humiliauit ſe ad mortem, qui calore ſuae immenſae charitatis nos dilexit, qui odore manfuctudinis, &amp; ſuauitatis totum mundum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleuit.</hi> His blood ſprinkles not the bodies ſo much as the ſoules and conſciences of men, for ſo the purging vertue which is in the naturall hyſſop is internall, and by it is ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Coram Deo opus eſſe non ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terna,</hi>
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:177902:77"/> 
               <hi>ſed interna purgatione.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seeing ſo it is, that the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie <note place="margin">How car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Papiſts are, who place ſo great ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification in externall things.</note> Iſraelites in vſing theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall types, which were not ordained for themſelues, but for other things, had a ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all diſpoſition looking euer to the thing ſignified by them. Is it not a ſhame for Papiſts to be ſo groſſe and carnall, as to place any ſanctificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the like ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall ſprinkling of their body with their holy water, as they call it: with as great reaſon might they bring in againe all that ceremoniall Law, which was but for a time, and now is abrogated, But now ſeeing the truth is come, which is Chriſt Ieſus, it is good reaſon the type and figure ſhould ceaſe. The fountaine is opened to
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:177902:78"/> 
               <hi>Dauids</hi> houſe, for ſinne and for vncleanneſſe. Hee hath made a perfect purgation of our ſins by his owne blood. Now to retaine the ceremonies of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daiſme, or to bring in from Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganiſme their ſuperſtitious waſhings of ſinne, as Papiſts borrow from <hi>Pompilius</hi> theſe heatheniſh purgations, by ſprinkling of water which they vſe, is to offer wrong to Chriſt Ieſus: for the firſt, in effect, imports that Chriſt the veritic is not yet come, and therefore they will ſtil retaine the figure: the ſecond imports, that albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it hee bee come, hee hath not made a perfect purgation of our ſinnes by himſelfe, but his wants muſt bee ſupplied by a purging with water on earth,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:177902:78"/> and a purging by fire in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond houſe of hell.</p>
            <p>But heere it is to be deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <note place="margin">Sinne not imputed is as if it had not beene committed.</note> how it is that <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaies, if the Lord waſh him, hee ſhall bee cleaner and whiter then the ſnow, doth he meane, that after ſinne is forgiuen, there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bideth no more any remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of ſinne vnto him. No, this is not his meaning, but that if the Lord forgiue him his ſin, hee ſhall hee in as good eſtate with the Lord, as if he had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer done it, <hi>Peccatum enim non imputatum eſt quaſi non commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum,</hi> a ſinne not imputed, is, as if it had neuer beene com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted.</p>
            <p>That wee may vnderſtand <note place="margin">A twofold purging of ſinne.</note> this the better, wee are to
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:177902:79"/> conſider, how there is a two-fold <note place="margin">1 <hi>One by Chriſts bloud, this is our iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</hi>
               </note> waſhing or taking away of ſinne: one, that is made by the blood of Chriſt: another, by the ſpirit of Chriſt. The ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away of ſin by the bloud of Chriſt is perfect euen now. For they to whom the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the blood of Chriſt is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted, haue preſently all the giltineſſe of their ſinne remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued fully and perfectly; this in effect is the benefit of our-iuſtification. The other taking away of ſinne by the ſpirit of <note place="margin">2 <hi>The other by his ſpirit this is our ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </note> Chriſt, is imperfect: his vertue hath begun in vs a mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our earthly members; his ſpirit daily weakeneth and ſubdueth in vs the life and power of ſinne, that it reig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not to command vs as it
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:177902:79"/> was wont to doe, and this in effect is the benefit of ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; but this taking away of ſinne in this life is not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, for ſome remainders of ſin euen in them to whom ſinne is forgiuen, will the Lord haue remaining, for the exerciſe of our faith, and daily humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as more at large wee haue ſhewed in our Treatiſe vpon the 8. to the <hi>Romans.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="140" facs="tcp:177902:80"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>VERSE 8.</bibl>
               <q>Make mee to heare ioy and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that the bones which thou haſt broken may reioice.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Itherto DAVID with his confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The ſecond ranke of</hi> Dauids <hi>petitions is for peace of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi>
               </note> of ſin hath ioined petitions for mercy. Now he proceeds and craues that theſe euils which his ſinne had brought vpon him, may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued. Sinne hath many e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill effects, at the firſt it offends God, and grieues his ſpirit, but at the laſt, it ſhall grieue the ſoule of him that did it. Let vs learne to beware of it.</p>
            <pb n="141" facs="tcp:177902:80"/>
            <p> This petition of <hi>Dauid</hi> is to <note place="margin">Sin ſpoiles man of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward peace and ioy.</note> bee oppoſed to his preſent diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, ſo ſhall wee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it. O Lord, I heare with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in mean accuſing voice of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, which terrifies and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiets me, I beſeech thee, Lord let me heare the contrary voice of ioy and gladneſſe. Heere then he confeſſeth that which all the children of God may finde in their own experience, that ſinne impaires the peace of conſcience. If wee could re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member how ſweet is the ioy and peace which wee loſe, for the vaine and periſhing plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of ſinne, wee would bee loath any more to make any ſuch exchange.</p>
            <p>Secondly, wee ſee here that there is not any teſtimony
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:177902:81"/> ſaue onely the teſtimony of <note place="margin">Mans teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of the remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſinnes is nothing, without the teſtimony of Gods ſpirit.</note> Gods ſpirit that can bring peace to the troubled conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. <hi>Nathan</hi> had before this witneſſed to <hi>Dauid,</hi> that his ſinnes were forgiuen him, but <hi>Nathans</hi> word pacified not his conſcience, the miniſtration of the word of God hath credit with men, the miniſtration of the Spirit, that bringeth conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation hee hath reſerued to himſelfe. When <hi>Martha</hi> and <hi>Marie</hi> mourned for dead <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarous,</hi> many godly Iewes came out of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort them, but they got neuer comfort till Chriſt Ieſus came, and ſo the godly may mourne for their ſinnes, and for the deadneſſe of their heart, but there ſhall bee no comfort till
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:177902:81"/> the comforter come, and re freſh their ſoules,</p>
            <p>But here it will be obiected, <note place="margin">The mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterial com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants greatly to be regarded and why.</note> what then auailes the miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the word, and the conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations of the ſeruants of God giuen out of it. Yea very much indeed, for where the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the word pronounced by Gods ſeruants goes before to witneſſe mercie, there the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of Gods ſpirit confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming it followes after, for the bleſſing of peace pronounced <note place="margin">Luke.</note> by the ſeruants of God vpon the children of peace abides vpon them, this we ſee cleere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly here in <hi>Dauid:</hi> Nathan pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced to him vpon the knowledge of his repentance the remiſſion of his ſinnes, hee could not feele it for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:177902:82"/> but the Lord followes and iuſtifies <hi>Nathans</hi> Miniſtrie, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſing that to <hi>Dauids</hi> heart, which <hi>Nathan</hi> had witneſſed vnto his eare.</p>
            <p>And this we haue to marke <note place="margin">Remiſsion of of ſins may be thine, ſuppoſe thou feele it not.</note> for a comfort againſt theſe ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall deſertions, whereunto the Children of God are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect. Remiſſion of ſinnes may bee thine, the ſeruants of God with a warrand may witneſſe vnto thee, that thy ſinnes are forgiuen thee, as heere <hi>Nathan</hi> doth vnto <hi>Dauid,</hi> and yet thou not feele that it is ſo, wee muſt not therefore bee ſo diſcoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged; as to thinke wee want that grace alwaie, which we cannot <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Therefore</hi> Dauid <hi>craues not onely mercy, but ſenſe of mercy.</hi>
               </note> feele.</p>
            <p>It is now cleare what is the benefit which DAVID here
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:177902:82"/> craues. To wit not mercie only that he hath ſought before, but the ſenſe of mercie alſo, make me to heare ioy, ſo that I may feele it. For all the inward ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the ſoule are in feeling; to heare the Lord, to ſee him, to taſt how good he is, is no other but to enioy him and to feele his conſolations. It is thy praiſe ô Lord that thou ſpeak'ſt peace to thy Saints; among the reſt, ſpeake peace vnto mine heart alſo. O what a ioy was it to that man ſicke of the palſie when he heard that voice, thy ſinnes are forgiuen thee. And ſuch like to that ſinfull woman when ſhee heard, goe in peace, thy faith hath ſaued thee. And how was the ſoule of that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted ſinner comforted in the
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:177902:83"/> middes of the dolors of death when he hard that voice, This night thou ſhalt be with me in paradiſe.</p>
            <p>This is the exceeding great <note place="margin">Great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, that God not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forgiues our ſinnes, but telles vs they are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuen.</note> loue of the Lord toward his children, that he hath not only prouided a ſure ſaluation for them through the remiſſion of their ſinnes in Chriſt Ieſus, but alſo ſeales vp in their heart the teſtimony thereof by his Holy Spirit of adoption, and that for their preſent conſolation leaſt they ſhould bee ſwallowed vp of heauineſſe through conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall temptations. Though he ſpeake not to all his children as hee did to <hi>Daniel</hi> by an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell; O man greatly beloued of God, nor as he did to the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Virgin <hi>Marie;</hi> haile <hi>Marie</hi>
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:177902:83"/> freely beloued, yet doth hee witneſſe the ſame to the hearts of his children by an inward teſtimonie, when they heare it, they are aliue; when they want it, they are but dead, their ſoule refuſes all other comfort whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the hones, which thou hath</hi> 
               <note place="margin">A troubled mind ſore weakneth the bodie.</note> 
               <hi>broken may reioyce.</hi> By theſe <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil</hi> vnderſtands <hi>Oſsa animae ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualia,</hi> that is as ſaith <hi>Sauanarola</hi> and others, <hi>Vires animae rationa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis</hi> but as this agrees not with this ſenſe, ſo there is no reaſon why it ſhould be enforced. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> his words, Pſalme 32. ſerues for a commentarie to this, there hee complaines, that through extremitie of the anguiſh of his Spirit; the moiſture of his body was turned into the drought of
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:177902:84"/> Sommer, now the marrow we know is the ſtrength of the bones, theſe being ſo extenuate no maruell, his fleſh conſumed, his skinne was parched, his face withered, his ſight dimmed, his knees enfeebled, and the whole externall man greatly weakned, the Spirit of a man ſayes <hi>Salomon</hi> will ſuſtaine his infirmitie, but a wounded ſpirit who can beare it?</p>
            <p>Of this let vs learne that if <note place="margin">The miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſtate of the wicked who muſt beare the burden of their owne ſinnes.</note> the ſight of ſinne preſented to the godly from a iuſt accuſing conſcience, doe ſo terrifie them, and breede them ſuch exceſſiue trouble as for a time, doth ſore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly torment them. In what ſtate ſhall the wicked be, when the Lord ſhall preſent their ſins to them &amp; wake their conſcience
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:177902:84"/> vpon them not in mercie, as he doth to his owne, but in wrath, not for a time, but for euer. O what anguiſh and remedileſſe tribulation ſhall be vnto them, the dayes of wicked mens ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning are compared to the time of a womans conceiuing, but the daies of their puniſhment are compared to the time of her trauelling: they conceiue their ſinnes with wantonneſſe and pleaſure, but ſhall beare them with dolor vnſpeakeable, their dolors ſhall exceede the dolor of a woman, for ſhee knowes once to bee deliuered of her paine either by life or death, but the wicked ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer bee lighter of their ſinnes, nor bee deliuered from the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh of their accuſing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:177902:85"/> from which moſt miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable condition the Lord deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs for Chriſt Ieſus ſake.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>VERSE 9.</bibl>
               <q>Hide thy face from my ſinnes, and put away all mine iniquities.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>AVID yet from <note place="margin">Guiltineſſe of ſin ſoone contracted, not ſo ſoone put away.</note> God the fourth time ſeekes the remiſſion of his ſinnes, the gilt of ſinne is ſoone contracted, but not ſo ſoone gotten away, wee are happie if the examples of other men may learne vs to be wiſe, he was a man deerely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued of God, and yet how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:177902:85"/> requeſts makes hee, before he can get his heart aſſured of mercy: but the preſumption <note place="margin">Fooliſh are they, who thinke they may get mercy for a word.</note> of this age is ſo great, that men feare not to offend the Lord, becauſe they thinke, mercie may be gotten for a word. But let men remember that fearful ſentence, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> the L. pronounc't vpon the people of the Iewes, for the abuſe of his mercy; <hi>When they faſt, I will not heare their crie:</hi> And againe; <hi>Thougb Moſes and Samuel ſtood before me, yet mine affection could not be toward this people,</hi> that ſo our hearts may be humbled with holy feare, which may reſtraine <note place="margin">He that ſeekes not to hide his ſinnes, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uokes the Lord to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire it.</note> vs from offending our God, vpon preſumption of mercy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hide thy face.</hi> All <hi>Dauid</hi> his care, when hee had committed
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:177902:86"/> his ſin, was to hide it from the Lord, for this cauſe he commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted murther and ſlew <hi>Vriah,</hi> thinking if he were not aliue to perceiue it, his iniquity ſhould neuer come to light. Now he ſees it with a vaine labor, <hi>Vriah</hi> is dead, but the angry counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God looking vpon his ſinne troubles him, As the fiſh called Sepia caſting forth a black liquor out of hir mouth, of purpoſe to lurke vnder it, doth therby giue notice to the fiſher of the place wherin they ſhall finde hir: ſo fooliſh man, while he thinks to hide one ſin by another, doth but caſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the more ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the eye of God, who then looks moſt nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly to a ſin when man moſt craftily labours to conceale it:
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:177902:86"/> Euery ſinner in ſinning takes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God the praiſe of righteouſnes as if the Lord were like him, &amp; were not a God that loues righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and hates iniquity.</p>
            <p>But he that thinkes to hide <note place="margin">Hee that ſeekes to hide his ſin from the Lord makes an idole of him.</note> his ſinne from the Lord, when he hath done it, takes alſo from him the praiſe of wiſedome, and makes the Lord ſo far as he may, like an Idoll of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that hath eyes and ſees not. And therefore the Lord as he will be auenged of euery one that offends, ſo principally vpon them who ſcorne him, by hiding their ſinnes from him. <hi>Woe be to them that ſeeke in deepe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">We to ſuch.</note> 
               <hi>to hide their Councell from the Lord, their workes are in ſecret, and they ſay who ſees it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At this time <hi>Dauids</hi> ſin was
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:177902:87"/> vnknowen to the world, no ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing <note place="margin">
                  <hi>No man knew</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uids <hi>ſinne, yet is be ſore trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he knew that God knew it.</hi>
               </note> creature but himſelfe <hi>Bathſhabe</hi> and <hi>Nathan</hi> were pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie to it, yet this terrifies him, that he ſaw the Lord looking vpon it: It is no comfort to a man to haue his ſinne hidden from all the world, vnleſſe hee knew that the Lord alſo hath couered and forgiuen it, <hi>alioqui</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ambroſ. de paeniten. li.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 11.</note> 
               <hi>ita grauis est culpa conſcientiae, vt ſine iudice ipſa ſe puniat.</hi> So hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie is the ſinne of any euill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, that albeit no creature were to iudge it, it iudges and puniſhes it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>He ſaid in the third verſe that <note place="margin">God will looke to our ſinnes, if we looke not to them.</note> his ſin was alway in his ſight, and now hee praies that God would put it out of his ſight, this is a very good ordor, if we hold our ſinnes in our eies to
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:177902:87"/> perſue them, God will caſt them behinde his backe to pardon them, if we remember them and repent, hee will for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get them and forgiue, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <hi>peccatum vnde ſe homo non auertit, aduertit deus, &amp; ſi aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit, animaduertit,</hi> the ſinne from which man turnes not, God lookes to it, and if he looke to it, ſure he will puniſh it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thy face.</hi> The face of God is <note place="margin">The face of God put ſometime for his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time for iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice.</note> ſometime put for his fauor, and with this he lookes on the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of them, who are the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of his good will, this <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uid</hi> praies may be lifted vp vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him Pſa. 4. that God would not hide it from him Pſal. 27. the hyding of his face did trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble him ſore Pſal. 30. therefore it is his cuſtomable prayer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="156" facs="tcp:177902:88"/> 
               <hi>Lord cauſe thy face to ſhine vpon vs,</hi> Pſa. 4. ſometime againe it is put for his anger or angry face, whereby he lookes on the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the wicked, when he wil vex them in his diſpleaſure, or vpon the ſinnes of his owne children, when he wil humble them.</p>
            <p>How fearefull a ſight this <note place="margin">How feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full a ſight Gods angry face is.</note> angry face of God is, ſee it in <hi>Dauid,</hi> for his good, the Lord who loued <hi>Dauids</hi> ſelfe, looked with an angry countenance at <hi>Dauids</hi> ſinnes, but hee proteſts hee may not indure it, and praies God to hide it from him. See it againe in Chriſt Ieſus, who endured the looks of that angrie face, not for himſelfe but for vs, how did it make his ſoule heauy, and his fleſh ſo
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:177902:88"/> weary that he did ſweat blood. How miſerable then are the reprobates, who muſt endure for euer the ſight of Gods an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry face looking vpon them? for they and their ſins are one, no maruell they ſhall cry hils and mountaines fall vpon vs, and hide vs from the face of him that ſits vpon the throne. Let vs feare and looke with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger vpon our ſins in time, that God in mercy may looke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our ſelues, and wee may finde ioy in his face, wherein the wicked ſhall ſee nothing but terror.</p>
            <pb n="160" facs="tcp:177902:89"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="161" facs="tcp:177902:89"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="158" facs="tcp:177902:90"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>VERSE. 10.</bibl>
               <q>Greate in mee a cleane heart, O God, and renew a right ſpirit within mee.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow followes <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uids</hi> third petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The third ranke of</hi> Dauids <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions.</hi>
               </note> wherein he craueth the grace of ſanctification, hee ſought before the forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his ſin, now hee ſeekes to be deliuered from it in time to come: for it is for this end that hee praies for a cleand heart, and a renewed ſpirit, that hee ſhould not any more fall to the like vncleanneſſe: This is a good order in our
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:177902:90"/> prayer, when firſt we ſeeke the <note place="margin">Remiſſion of ſinne and renouation go together.</note> grace of remiſſion, and then the grace of renouation, for theſe two goe inſeparably together; to whom the Lord giues re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, them hee makes new creatures, ſo that renouation of the heart is alway an vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted token of the remiſſion of thy ſinnes; and by the contrary he whoſe heart is not renewed but abides ſtil in his former vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe, hee deceiues him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, if ſo be he thinkes that his ſinnes are forgiuen.</p>
            <p>This is to be marked for the common ſort of prophane men <note place="margin">They who ſeeke for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe and not ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſeeke but liberty to ſinne.</note> in this age, who ſeeke from God mercy to forgiue for feare of his plagues, but not grace to renew them to his image for loue of himſelfe, this in effect is
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:177902:91"/> no other but to ſeeke a liberty to ſinne, while as men ſeeke ſin to be forgiuen, but not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained, it is an argument they haue not a right hatred of ſin, but wee ſee in <hi>Dauid</hi> what the diſpoſition of the godly is, as they deſire mercy for be-gone ſinnes, ſo alſo grace to renew them and preſerue them from the power and deceit of ſinne in all time to come, otherwiſe to craue that the Lord would pardon theſe ſins, which thou art of purpoſe to commit, it is but to mocke the Lord, by turning his grace into wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. <note place="margin">The vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleaneſſe of ſinne origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all. Iob.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dauid</hi> his heart was two waies vncleane, firſt by reaſon of originall ſinne wherein hee was conceiued and borne, <hi>Who</hi>
               <pb n="161" facs="tcp:177902:91"/> 
               <hi>can bring a clean thing out of that which is vnclean:</hi> &amp; this vnclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart is common to al mankind, but beſide this he had defiled it with many actual ſins, ſpecially this foule adultery &amp; murther, for euery ſin pollutes the heart, &amp; leaues a new gilti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes vpon the conſcience, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with now <hi>Dauid</hi> finding his heart ouergrowne, that it is not like the heart he had before, he praieth the Lord to giue him a new heart. He had now not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſinned, but fallen as Baſile expounds it in <hi>Senium peccati</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <note place="margin">Baſil.</note> the very old age of ſin, and therefore hee deſires, that the Lord would begin with him againe, and make him to renew his youth like the Eagle.</p>
            <p>Many circumſtances are to
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:177902:92"/> bee marked heere, whereby <note place="margin">Sinne ſeeks the very life of the ſoule.</note> 
               <hi>Dauid</hi> aggrauateth the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his miſery: as firſt, that his diſeaſe was in his heart, which is the fountaine of life. As the naturall heart is the life of the body, which when it is not well, vitall hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor, health, beauty, ability, and all decaies in the body: ſo is the Lord the life of the ſoule. So <hi>Dauids</hi> meaning is, O Lord, by my ſinne I haue grieued thy holy ſpirit, and forced thee to forſake me. <hi>Tu proprie cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The heart of any Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian his heart.</note> 
               <hi>mei proprium es cor &amp; vita:</hi> thou properly art the proper heart, and life of mine heart. Come againe Lord, and reſtore life vnto mee, without thee I am dead and ſenſleſſe, and an abominable creature, like a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:177902:92"/> which wanting an heart is an vncleane carion, thou art the light of my minde, the peace of my ſoule, the life of my heart. I haue loſt life by my ſinne, I am like a man wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his quickning ſpirit: when thou wenteſt away, my life went away: Lord come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and create a new heart within me.</p>
            <p>Againe, in that hee craues a <note place="margin">Repentance is a new creation.</note> cleane heart may bee created in him, he acknowledgeth that his ſinne had not onely woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him, but ſlaine him, and that he ſtood in neede not of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reparation, but of an new creation, wherein hee vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie <note place="margin">And ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the power of nature.</note> diſtruſteth the power of his nature: yea the ability of his owne free will notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:177902:93"/> grace once reſumed, hee findes it ſo oppreſſed by the power of his corruption, that he is forced to craue from God the benefit of a new creation, <hi>Vt cor eius tale fieret per gratiam,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Sauan.</note> 
               <hi>quale non potuit eſſe per naturam.</hi> Of our ſelues wee fall, but of our ſelues wee riſe not againe. Not onely is our firſt conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion a worke of Gods grace al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together and alone; but the workes of our reſtitution by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, after we haue fallen: as it is in the Lords praiſe, <hi>Hee quickened vs, when we were dead.</hi> So is it his praiſe, <hi>that hee keepes</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 100. <hi>As we crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not our ſelues. So we cannot renew our ſelues.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>our ſoules in life. The Lord made vs, we made not our ſelues.</hi> Wee are content to giue him the glory of our firſt creation, let vs alſo giue him the glory of
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:177902:93"/> our ſecond creation. Yea, ſo oft as we fall into ſinne, let vs conſider that our riſing againe, is no leſſe a worke of the great power, and mercy of God: then was the rayſing of <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> out of the graue, for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe wee ſhould haue lien ſtill with others, rotting and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing in our ſinnes. And ſo haue wee to praiſe the Lord, not onely for our firſt and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond creation, but for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing of that benefit vnto vs, as oft as we by our tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on haue loſt that life, which the Lord did once communicate vnto vs.</p>
            <p>And this that our ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, <note place="margin">A proper compariſon of our firſt creation with the ſecond.</note> or reſtitution by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance after that wee haue ſinned, is called new creation,
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:177902:94"/> renders yet vnto vs a profitable inſtruction, if we compare our new creation with <hi>Adam</hi> his firſt creation. When ſhall wee ſay that <hi>Adam</hi> was made a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall man? neuer till the Lord breathed the breath of life in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him: the Lord firſt formed his body of clay, after the ſame ſhape and ſimilitude, that now yee ſee the body of man in all the porportion of the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers thereof. No image can be made by mans wit ſo liuely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting a man, as did that portraiture of clay, which the Lord at the firſt formed with his owne hand, but al this time it lay vpon the ground, hauing eyes that ſaw not, eares that heard not, a mouth that could not ſpeake, and feet that could
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:177902:94"/> not walke: hee was then very like vnto that which now man <note place="margin">Many pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians are but carka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</note> is; but (as I ſaid) was not a naturall man, til God breathed the breath of life vnto him. Let vs conſider the like in the new creation, how many ſhall ye find verie like vnto chriſtians baptized in the name of Ieſus. who haue a mouth to ſpeake, and an eye to looke vp vnto heauen, and an care, as a man would thinke, to heare very reuerently the word of the Lord: who when all is done, what euer they ſeem in the eies of men, are no other in Gods ſight, but as the carcaſes of chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians: So to ſpeake, deſtitute of that quickning ſpirit of grace, which onely giues life to the actions of men. Let vs take
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:177902:95"/> heede to our ſelues that we bee not of that number; for then onely haue wee this comfort that we are Chriſtians indeed, when we finde that quickning ſpirit of grace, which is in Chriſt Ieſus, communicating life vnto our ſpirits, that what we doe in the workes of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity ſtand not in externall ſhew, but may proceede from inward ſenſe and feeling.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="169" facs="tcp:177902:95"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>VERSE. 11.</bibl>
               <q>Caſt mee not away from thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and take not thine holy Spirit from me.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Till <hi>Dauid</hi> conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues <note place="margin">Dauids <hi>feruency in Supplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </note> his ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, ſeeking a remedy of theſe manifold miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, which he found by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, his ſinne had brought vpon him. For wee muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, that all theſe petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons proceeded from a ſenſe of a contrary euill, which by his ſinne hee had incurred, and craues that God of his mercy would diuert it. He lamemted
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:177902:96"/> before that ſinne had ſlaine him, and made him like a dead man wanting a heart, or quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſpirit, and now hee feares leſt as the dead are abhorred by the liuing, ſo the Lord ſhould caſt him out, as a dead and abominable thing out of his preſence.</p>
            <p>Whereof wee learne, this is <note place="margin">The plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of ſin are deare bought.</note> one of the iuſt puniſhments of ſinne, it procures the caſting out of a man from the face of God, and it may let vs ſee how deare bought are the pleaſures of ſinne, when a man to enioy the face of the creature, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priues himſelfe of the comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table face of the Creator, as <hi>Dauid</hi> here for the carnall loue of the face of <hi>Bathſheba,</hi> puts himſelfe in danger to bee caſt
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:177902:96"/> out for euer from the preſence of the Lord his God. If man could remember this in all Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans tentations, what it is <note place="margin">For Satan ſeekes frous man better then he can giue him</note> that the deceiuer offers, and what it is againe that hee ſeekes, hee would be loth to buy the periſhing pleaſures of ſinne, vpon ſuch a price as Satan ſelleth them, but would anſwer him, as the Apoſtle did <hi>Simon Magus, Thy money with thy ſelfe goe into perdition, thy gaine, thy glory, thy pleaſure, and what euer thou wouldeſt giue me to offend the Lord my God, goe with thy ſelfe into perdition, for what canſt thou offer vnto mee comparable to that, which thou wouldeſt ſteale from me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But how is it that he praies, <note place="margin">A twofold preſence of God.</note> 
               <hi>Caſt me not out from thy preſence.</hi>
               <pb n="172" facs="tcp:177902:97"/> May a man bee caſt any way from it: ſaies hee not himſelfe <hi>What way can I flee from thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence?</hi> This is ſoone anſwered by diſtinguiſhing his twofold preſence: one in mercy where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with hee refreſheth and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forteth his owne; and this without intermiſſion they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy, who are in heauen: ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in wrath, whereby hee terrifies and torments without intermiſſion the da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned in hell. As to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who are vpon earth, certaine it is, hee is diſpleaſed with many, who becauſe <note place="margin">No caſting out from the one.</note> they ſee not his angry face, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard it not, borne out with temporall recreations of the cteature, which wil faile them, and there are many againe to whom hee lookes as a louing
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:177902:97"/> father in Chriſt, and yet they ſee not his mercifull face, by reaſon of many interiected vailes: but to them who once haue felt the ſweetneſſe of his fauourable face, it is death to want it. <hi>Abſolom</hi> proteſted hee could not want the ſight <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 14. 32.</note> of <hi>Dauid</hi> his Father, hee ſpake it out of his hypocriſie; but to ſuch as are truely godly, there can be no puniſhment ſo heauy as to debarre them, and it were but for a ſhort time, from the comfortable face of their heauenly father.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, let vs learne how <note place="margin">What an alſufficient good the Lord is.</note> the all-ſufficiencie of the Lord our God, and his great power appeares in this. It is puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment enough to a man, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe he were Monarch of the
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:177902:98"/> world, and had all comforts earthly to vphold him; to want the countenance of God. O <note place="margin">It is life to ſee his fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable face, and death to want it.</note> what an infinite good, what an all-ſufficient Maieſtie is hee in himſelfe! a looke of whoſe countenance refreſhes his cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ature: &amp; no comfort can com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort him that wants it; as yee may ſee in <hi>Beltaſar,</hi> how did he tremble in the midſt of all his pleaſures, at the ſight of Gods anger? and here in <hi>Dauid,</hi> who once debarred from the ſight of Gods ioyful face for his ſins, could neuer reſt till he got it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. All the ſports and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights of his Kingdome could not refreſh him. Doubtleſſe he is an all-ſufficient God, who liues by himſelfe, whoſe onely countenance comforts his cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atures,
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:177902:98"/> and without whoſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, life, yea, the moſt honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable life that can be deuiſed on earth, is worſe then death.</p>
            <p>But what moued him to <note place="margin">The godly feare when they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments on others.</note> fear caſting out from Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, who had ſo many both externall and internall teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of Gods fauour toward him? Out of queſtion the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of <hi>Caine,</hi> caſt out for murthering his brother, &amp; the example of his predeceſſor <hi>Saul,</hi> iuſtly reiected of God, did terrifie him, left hee for mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileſſe murthering his owne ſeruant, and fearfull back-ſly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from the Lord, ſhould al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo be reiected. He remembred well the example of Gods iudgements on others for their ſinnes, and his conſcience told
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:177902:99"/> him within, hee was guilty of the like or greater: &amp; this made him afraid.</p>
            <p>Yet was not his feare with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hope ſuſteyned by conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration <note place="margin">Yet their feare is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer without hope, if they feare God as a Iudge, they hope in him as a Sauiour.</note> of God his vnchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able loue, but by the inward conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his own vnfeyned repentance, and by the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold examples of Gods mercie ſhewed to penitent ſinners. If <hi>Caine</hi> was caſt out from thy face, it was becauſe he ſought not thy fauour: and <hi>Saul</hi> was reiected becauſe hee repented not. But Lord, I haue opened my heart to thee; thou ſeeſt what griefe is in my ſoule, for grieuing thee by my ſinnes; thou neuer reiectedſt any, that from a penitent heart ſought thy mercie: <hi>Quis vnquam venit</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Sauan.</note>
               <pb n="177" facs="tcp:177902:99"/> 
               <hi>ad te &amp; confuſus abijt?</hi> Who e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer came to thee, and went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way aſhamed? Shall I be the firſt that ſought thy face, and was reiected? Nay Lord, <hi>Caſt me not, I beſeech thee, out of thy preſence.</hi> Thus we ſee, how <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> at one time, <hi>Et timet à iudice,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Bernard.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; ſperat à ſaluatore,</hi> is both af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of God as his Iudge, and hath hope in God as his Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our; ſomtime feare oppreſſeth his hope, but at the length hope ouercometh feare: <hi>Felix conſcientia in qua eiuſmodi lucta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And take not thy holy Spirit</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleaneneſſe of ſinne, grieues Gods Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</note> 
               <hi>from me.</hi> The Spirit of GOD will not dwell in a polluted ſoule. Euery vncleaneneſſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſheth his preſence. The Apoſtle warneth vs heereof,
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:177902:100"/> when hee ſaith, <hi>Grieue not the Spirit.</hi> And againe, <hi>Quench not the Spirit. Dauid</hi> felt it by his own experience, and therefore makes he this prayer to God, that the grace of his Spirit, which was weakened by his ſinne, ſhould not vtterly be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from him.</p>
            <p>This is a petition neceſſary alway to bee vſed vnto God: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Without the Spirit, no fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with God. Rom.</hi> 8.</note> for without this Spirit we can haue no fellowſhip with God. <hi>If any man haue not the Spirit of Chriſt, the ſame is not his:</hi> &amp; this Spirit, hee is knowne by his fruits, which are, <hi>Loue, Peace, Ioy, long Suffering, Gentleneſſe,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 22.</note> 
               <hi>Goodneſſe, Faith, Meekeneſſe, Temperance.</hi> Where wee finde the preſence of this Spirit by his fruits, wee are to cheriſh
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:177902:100"/> him; where we find a want, or decay of them, wee are to pray for them: but many prophane men in this age are like theſe, who know not whether there bee ſuch a thing as the Holy <note place="margin">Yet pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane men cannot di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcerne his preſence from his abſence.</note> Ghoſt, or not: they neuer felt his preſence, neyther had they euer experience of his renuing, and comforting grace; &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore feele no loſſe by his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. Let them enioy ſuch things as they loue, they care not for him, becauſe they know him not: moſt like vnto brute beaſts, to whom pearles and moſt excellent jewels are <note place="margin">What an excellent gueſt and worthy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the Spirit of God is.</note> of no price; onely ſuch things as affect their ſenſuall appetite, are pleaſant vnto them.</p>
            <p>But how excellent a gueſt this Spirit is, and how worthy
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:177902:101"/> to be harboured in our hearts, may be gather'd from this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Epithet, which alway is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to him, <hi>A holy Spirit;</hi> both becauſe in himſelfe he is ſo, and dooth alſo make them holy in whom he dwels. What notable effects hee workes in his own children, is ſummarily compriſed by <hi>Bernard</hi> in three <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bern. in feſt. Pente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſt. Ser.</hi> 5.</note> wordes: he is <hi>Pignus Salutis,</hi> the pledge of ſaluation: all ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſaluation without him, is but babling: hee is <hi>Robur vitae,</hi> the ſtrength of our life<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him we haue no ability to any ſpirituall action; and he is <hi>Scientiae lume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> the light of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: for without his ſanctify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing grace, all knowledge what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, is but darkneſſe.</p>
            <p>But heere it is demaunded;
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:177902:101"/> May the ſpirit of God, once gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen <note place="margin">Whether Gods Spirit once giuen, may be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from his children or not.</note> to Gods children, be taken from them? I anſwer, there are ſome of his gifts which may be giuen and taken away againe: theſe are ſecondary and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, ſuch as God giues indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently to good men and euil. So <hi>Achitophels</hi> wiſedome, and <hi>Saul</hi> his gift of Kingly gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, were at length taken from them: but there are other gifts, which once giuen, are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer taken away againe. Theſe are principall and proper, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated only to Gods elect; as the grace of regeneration, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption, ſanctification: theſe graces are crowned with that great grace of Perſeuerance. The reaſon whereof is not in vs, nor in our ſtabilitie; but in
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:177902:102"/> the vnchangable counſell and will of him who loued vs, for <hi>whom he loues he loues, to the end: his gifts and calling are without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance:</hi> Wee may fall after grace receiued, but the Lord puts vnder his hand and raiſes vs vp againe: <hi>Becauſe I am not changed, therefore ye are not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed,</hi> ſaith the Lord: And truely euen at this ſame time when <hi>Dauid</hi> makes this praier, it is euident, hee wanted not this ſpirit of grace, reſtoring him by repentance after hee had fallen, and making him thirſt for mercy: <hi>Nullum enim certius praeſentiae ſpiritus testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium, quam deſiderium amplioris gratiae.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="183" facs="tcp:177902:102"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>VERSE. 12.</bibl>
               <q>Restore to me the ioy of thy ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſtabliſh mee with thy free ſpirit.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hree great euils <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Three great euils</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uids <hi>ſinne brought vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him.</hi>
               </note> did <hi>Dauid</hi> bring vpon himſelf by his ſinne; a gilti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe which em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired the ſenſe of Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, an vncleanneſſe which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted and corrupted all the powers of his ſoule, vpon which two, followed horrour of a iuſt accuſing conſcience. Againſt theſe three he frames his ſupplications. Againſt the <note place="margin">His reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die againſt them all three.</note> firſt he ſeekes mercie to pardon
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:177902:103"/> and forgiue his ſinne: Againſt the ſecond hee ſeekes grace to renew him, and that God would create a cleane heart within him. Againſt the third he ſeekes to be reſtored to the ioy of Gods ſaluation.</p>
            <p>But as this is the laſt and <note place="margin">The way of a penitent ſinner is:</note> greateſt petition that a ſinner can ſeke to be comforted with the ioyes of God, ſo are wee to remember, that in this petition wee cannot preuaile, except ſome other goe before it, there then is the order to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by a penitent ſinner, let vs firſt fall downe at his feet, and mourne: <hi>ploremus coram domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no qui fecit nos, ea quae fecimus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bez. in Cant. ſer.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>nos,</hi> let vs therefore continew a long time lamenting our mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold ſinnes, and taking a view
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:177902:103"/> if poſſibly we may, of euery one of them, that as by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting them wee contracted giltineſſe, ſo by mourning parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly for them, wee may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feeble their teſtimony againſt vs. Then let vs looke vp out <note place="margin">From mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning at Gods feete to goe vp to the kiſſes of his mouth.</note> of the aſſurance of faith, and require the helping hand of the Lord to raiſe vs vp, theſe two being rightly done we ſhal finde him like that merciful fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, embracing the forlorne ſonne in his armes and kiſſing him, from his feete we goe to his hands, from his hands to the kiſſes of his mouth, ſuch as fall not downe to mourne at his feete, how can his helping hand raiſe them vp, or the kiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of his mouth comfort them?</p>
            <pb n="186" facs="tcp:177902:104"/>
            <p> See here what a deceiuer, and <note place="margin">Sathan in tempting makes faire offers but indeed is a robber.</note> ſupplanter Satan is, in tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he ſeemes to be a giuer, for he makes great offers to men, if they will obey him, but in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry deed he is but a robber, and ſo ſhall euery man finde him, when they are deliured from the deceite of ſinne, and get their eares opened, they ſhall ſee, that Satan by alluring them to ſinne, hath taken ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent things from them, for which they haue need to pray earneſtly vnto God, as <hi>Dauid</hi> here doth, that hee would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore them. Let vs not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore harken to him when he flattereth vs the faireſt. Where God gets loue and obedience from man, there man gets com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in his God, but Satan like
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:177902:104"/> a ſubtill diuider doth what hee can to depriue God of that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience which his creature ſhould giue him, that ſo he may depriue the creature of that ioy and comfort, which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe he might haue in his God.</p>
            <p>And again we ſee how there <note place="margin">No ioy can comfort mans ſoule but the ioy of Gods ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</note> is no ioy can content <hi>Dauid,</hi> but the ioy of Gods ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he was a King, &amp; wanted none of theſe earthly comforts wherein worldly men reioyce, but none of them can comfort the heart of <hi>Dauid,</hi> it is the ioy which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes to the conſcience from the feeling of God his ſaluation that he craues, &amp; indeed what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ioy can there be, albeit the Lord would giue vs all things that he hath made, vnleſſe we
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:177902:105"/> feele himſelfe our father, and Sauiour in Chriſt, what can they helpe vs, it is true of them all, which Iob in his trouble ſpake of his friends, <hi>Miſerable comforters are ye,</hi> and yet many ſuch miſerable men are there in the world, who know no ioy, but that which ariſes of meat, and drinke, ſiluer and gold, and ſuch like things, this is but a brutiſh ioy, for euen the beaſts haue their owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, when ſuch obiects are preſented to them, as are agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to their nature, and thou if thou knoweſt no other, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect thou waſt made for grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter things, art more beaſtly then they. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Three great graces ſeeks</hi> Dauid <hi>in this peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And ſtabliſh me with thy free ſpirit:</hi> In this ſhort petition
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:177902:105"/> many notable benefits, <hi>Dauid</hi> ſeeketh from the Lord, for by this free ſpirit <hi>Vatablus</hi> vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands <hi>Spiritum libertatis, qua proni &amp; faciles reddimur ad faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endum quae Deus praecipit,</hi> that ſpirit of liberty, which enclines our hearts willingly to doe, what the Lord commands ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that of our Sauiour, Iohn 8. <hi>Then ſhall ye be free if the ſonne make you free:</hi> So then the benefit <hi>Dauid</hi> here craued, is <note place="margin">1 <hi>That rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon may command affection.</hi>
               </note> that he may finde reaſon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding affection, as <hi>Baſil</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds it, and that his carnall affections haue no power to draw his heart toward exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and vnlawful obiects, away from his God as they had done: for affections once let looſe, are not eaſily bridled and
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:177902:106"/> reſtrained againe, but after a furious and inordinat manner caries away the heart of man, ſuffocates light, captiues rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, whereby they themſelues ſhould be ruled, and this <hi>Dauid</hi> feeling in himſelfe, praies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, that the Lord would eſtabliſh him with his free ſpirit.</p>
            <p>Secondly, he is called <hi>Ruah</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>That the ſenſe of Gods loue may ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the terror of his accuſing conſcience.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Nedibah</hi> the ſpirit of liberty for an other effect which hee workes in our hearts, whereof the Apoſtle ſpeakes Rom. 8. <hi>Ye haue not receiued the ſpirit of bondage to feare again but the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of adoption, whereby ye cry ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba father:</hi> This effect is to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort our heart with the ſenſe of Gods fatherly loue, <hi>Dauid</hi> was trouble with terrors of minde
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:177902:106"/> which his gilty conſcience had wakened, and now he craues the confirming ſpirit of God or as <hi>Tremell.</hi> tranſlates it, <hi>Spiritum ingenuitatis,</hi> thy kindly ſpirit, which in regeneration thou giueſt to thy owne children, wherby I may know that I am one of them: Euery ſinne em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paires in our heart the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the ſpirit of adoption witneſſing Gods loue, and therefore <hi>Dauid</hi> craues it might againe be renewed vnto him.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the word <hi>Nadab</hi> ſignifies to be willingly moued <note place="margin">3 <hi>That a Princely minde may be giuen him accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to bis calling.</hi>
               </note> to giue, therefore among the Hebrewes their Princes were called <hi>Nedibim</hi> for their free munificence and liberality and out of this ſenſe he ſeekes a new benefite <hi>Dauid</hi> was not a
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:177902:107"/> priuate man, but a publike and therefore craue ſo to be gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the ſpirit of God, that he might be made anſwerable to his calling: For the pride of Nebuchadnezer the heart of a <note place="margin">A admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for men in au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</note> man was take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from him, &amp; the heart of a beaſt giuen, &amp; <hi>Dauid</hi> hauing miſruled himſelf, found his gift decaied, by which hee ſhould haue ruled his people: And therefore now praies that as the Lord had called him to be a Prince of his people, hee would not caſt him away for his ſinnes, but reſtore to him that meaſure of Gods ſpirit, whereby hee might doe that worke according to the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of his calling. Oh that al Kings and Rulers of people could euer remember this,
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:177902:107"/> what ſhall purchaſe them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence of their ſubiects? is it not the image of God? what ſhall make them able to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne others? is it not the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God gouerning them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues? This was <hi>Pharao</hi> his reaſon why he made choiſe of <hi>Ioſeph, Where can we finde ſo meet a man as this to rule, in whom the Spirit of God is.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore aboue al other men ſhould they bee moſt inſtant to pray, that God would eſtabliſh their hearts by his ſpirit: ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king their affections ſeruants to their reaſon, that ſo them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues being ruled by God, they may the better rule his people.</p>
            <p>Alway wee ſee, it is not a ſmall thing, which <hi>Dauid</hi> heere
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:177902:108"/> ſeeketh from God, but hee ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth <note place="margin">It is an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouring of God, when we ſeeke great things from him. Sauan.</note> the greateſt gifts that God giueth on earth to his children, <hi>Rem magnam a te peto domine, quia tu es Deus magnus Dominus, iniuriam tibi facit qui a te parua petit.</hi> O Lord, I ſeeke great things from thee, becauſe thou art a great God, they diſhonor the Lord, who ſeeke ſmall things from him, and they are moſt welcome to him who ſeeke greateſt things from him; as is euident by <hi>Salomons</hi> petition: hee of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers himſelfe to be our Father, his Sonne to bee our Sauiour, his Spirit to be our comforter, to confirme and eſtabliſh our hearts. Theſe are his moſt excellent giftes let vs couet theſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="195" facs="tcp:177902:108"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>VERSE. 13.</bibl>
               <q>Then ſhall I teach thy way vnto the wicked, and Sinners ſhall be conuerted to thee.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Itherto we haue <note place="margin">
                  <hi>With petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> Dauid <hi>ioynes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes</hi>
               </note> heard DAVIDS petitions; now followes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, which are of two ſorts, in the firſt, hee promiſes to bee a good inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to conuert others vnto the Lord: in the next that hee ſhall publiſh the praiſes of his God.</p>
            <p>There is a dutie that goeth <note place="margin">Before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinne goes repentance.</note> before remiſſion of ſinne, and that is a godly ſorrow for ſin,
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:177902:109"/> which cauſes repentance to ſaluation: for how ſhall the Lord remit the ſinne whereof man wil not repent. And there is an other dutie that followes it, and that is thankefulneſſe to God, and a louing care of the ſaluation of others. Our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our collected well, that many ſinnes were forgiuen to that <note place="margin">And after followes thankeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> penitent woman that did waſh his feete with her teares, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhee loued him much. But alas, if it bee conſidered how ſmall is our loue towards God, how little is our regard of the ſaluation of our brethren. It may be ſaid of many in this age, they haue but ſmall, or no warrant, that there ſinnes are forgiuen them, who haue ſo little, or no loue toward God,
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:177902:109"/> and their brethren, for the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument holds ſure, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but loue the Lord great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to whom great and many ſinnes are pardoned and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then:</hi> Marke his words, <note place="margin">He is not meete to ſpeake of peace and pardon to to others, who is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the power of his owne ſinne.</note> when will <hi>Dauid</hi> teach others, when God hath deliuered him from his ſinnes? A man vnder the power and gultineſſe of his owne ſinne, is not meet to ſpeake of peace and pardon vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to others. <hi>Obmuteſcit facundia, ſi aegra ſit conſcientia.</hi> Eloquence is ſilent where, the conſcience is ſicke and diſeaſed. A pitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nicephor. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 32.</note> proofe whereof wee haue in <hi>Origen,</hi> who being compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led either to ſuffer the abuſing of his body by an <hi>Ethiopian,</hi> or to ſacrifice vnto Idols, made
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:177902:110"/> choiſe of the laſt, and offered incenſe vnto Idols, wherewith his conſcience was ſo troubled, that afterward comming to <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> and there being firſt requeſted, and then vpon his refuſall forced to teach, hee went to the Pulpit, and read there theſe words of the 50. <hi>Pſalme, What haſt thou to doe to take my ordinances in thy mouth, ſeeing thou hateſt to be reformed, when thou ſeest a thiefe, thou run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt with him, and art pertaker with the adulterers.</hi> When hee had ſo done, hee cloſed the booke, and becauſe hee found his mouth cloſed by the guilt of his conſcience, he fel to wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and mourning, whereby he prouokt all the congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to mourne with him, but
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:177902:110"/> was not able to teach any. whereof all preachers haue <note place="margin">A warning to Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers.</note> their warning, that with great care they ſhould keepe their conſcience cleane, if they would ſpeake to the conſcience of others: and if at any time they haue hurt their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, without delay ſhould they heale it by repentance <hi>Cum eradicantur ex corde peccata</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bern. in aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſ. dom. Ser.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>exinde qui in Chriſtum credunt, linguis loquuntur nouis.</hi> Then do they, who beleeue in Chriſt, ſpeak with new tongues, when old ſinnes are rooted out of <note place="margin">The talent of mercie we haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is greateſt ſhould bee moſt vſed to the edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of others</note> their hearts.</p>
            <p>Againe wee ſee our duty craues, that when wee haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued mercy from God for our ſelues, wee ſhould make vantage of it for the edification
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:177902:111"/> of others. Euery talent recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from God ſhould bee put to profit, but ſpecially the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent of mercy, as it is greateſt: ſo the Lord requires greater fruit of it, both for his owne glory, and for the edification of our brethren. Seeing wee are the veſſels of mercy, ſhould not the ſent and ſweet odour of mercy go from vs to others. This duty Chriſt craued from <hi>Peter,</hi> and <hi>thou when thou art conuerted, confirme thy brethen.</hi> And this duty, as <hi>Dauid</hi> heere promiſes, ſo we may reade how he did performe it, <hi>Come vnto mee all yee that feare God, and I will tell you what God hath done to my ſoule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The propetie of a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an <note place="margin">Baſil.</note> is, <hi>fides per dilectionem effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cax,</hi>
               <pb n="201" facs="tcp:177902:111"/> faith working by loue. <note place="margin">How we are bound to haue a care of the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren</note> What auiles it to pretend faith toward God, where there is no loue toward thy neighbour, and wherein can thy loue bee declared more then in this, to draw thy neighbour to the participation of that ſame me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, whereunto God hath cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led thee. By the Law a man was bound to bring home his neighbours wandring beaſt, if he had mette with it before, how much more then to turne againe his neighbour himſelfe, when hee wanders from the Lord his God? If two men walking on the way, ſhould both fall into one pit, and the one beeing releeued out of it, ſhould goe his way and forget his neighbour, might it not
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:177902:112"/> iuſtly be called a barbarous &amp; inhumane cruelty. Wee haue all fallen into one and the ſame myre of iniquity: ſith the Lord hath put out his merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full hand to draw vs out of this priſon of ſinne, ſhall we refuſe to put out our hand, to ſee if poſsibly we may draw vp our brethren with vs?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thy wayes.</hi> He ſaith not, that <note place="margin">Prophane men not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly commit ſinne, but teach the way of ſin to others.</note> he wil teach ſinners his wayes; the wayes of ſinne can bee lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned without a teacher: but he will teach them Gods wayes. There are many profane men in the world, who think it not enough to commit ſinne with greedineſſe, but will boaſt of their ſinnes, when they haue done them, teaching and allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring others to commit the like
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:177902:112"/> iniquitie: theſe are but like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <note place="margin">Theſe are like beaſts.</note> dogges, and other ſuch bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh beaſts, who when they haue auoyded their dongue, turne about their face vnto it, delighting in the ſcent therof; and yet blinded man will glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in ſuch a beaſtlie quality.</p>
            <p>But what are theſe wayes <note place="margin">Some wayes of God are vnſearchea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, theſe a man ſhould not learne. Leuit.</note> of God, which <hi>Dauid</hi> ſayth hee wil teach? Som of Gods waies are vnſearchable: of theſe wee ſhould beware; neyther to teach, nor learne that which God firſt hath not taught vs. But there are other of his wayes, which hee hath manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, as, the way of iudgement, whereby he walkes ſtubbornly againſt them that walke ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bornly againſt him going farre from them that depart from
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:177902:113"/> him: and the way of mercie, wherin he ſhewes himſelfe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18. <hi>But the way of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and mercy we ſhould both teach it to others, and learn it our ſelues.</hi>
               </note> with the vpright man, &amp; comes neere vnto them, who with a humble &amp; contrite ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit draw neer vnto him. Theſe are thy wayes, O Lord, which I ſhall teach, ſaith <hi>Dauid,</hi> when I ſhall learne them: I haue lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the way of thy iudgment: I haue felt thou art terrible to ſinners, and that it is a fearefull thing to fall into thine hands; let me alſo feel thy ſweet mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, forgiuing my ſin; then ſhall I teach the way of thy mercy to ſinners alſo, &amp; ſhall let them know how gratious thou art, how ready to forgiue, &amp; what they muſt doe, if they would be receiued into thy fauour.</p>
            <p>All the wayes of GOD are
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:177902:113"/> vnknowne to men by nature, <note place="margin">The way of Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy naturally is vnknown.</note> but eſpecially the way of his mercie. Nature could neuer haue dreamed of that way of mercy, which God hath diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered: it ſurpaſſeth all light that is in nature; if God had not reuealed it, man ſhould neuer haue knowne it. Experience may confirme this: for we ſee it is an eaſie thing to inſtruct a man in the knowledge of Gods power, prouidence, iuſtice, and all, but to bring a ſinner to the knowledge and aſſurance of Gods mercy, is a difficult thing. It is eaſie to preach iudgement by the Lawe, not ſo to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade mercy by the Goſpell: this is the higheſt, and moſt dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult point of a Paſtors calling.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And ſinners ſhall be conuerted</hi>
               <pb n="206" facs="tcp:177902:114"/> 
               <hi>vnto thee.</hi> Marke the wordes <note place="margin">Conuerſion of a ſinner is Gods worke.</note> of <hi>Dauid;</hi> I, ſaith he, ſhal teach, and they ſhall bee conuerted. When the conuerſion of a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner is aſcribed to man, we muſt vnderſtand, hee is not the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, but the inſtrument of it. He ſhall not want his owne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence: <hi>For they who conuert many to righteouſneſſe, ſhall ſhine like the ſtarres in the Firmament.</hi> But the glory of the conuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is proper to the Lord: men may plant and water, but God giues the increaſe. <hi>Paul</hi> preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at Philippi, but God opened the heart of <hi>Lydia: Peter</hi> prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched to <hi>Cornelius</hi> and his kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, but the Holy Ghoſt brought downe the vnction, which made them Chriſtians. Repentance is a worke full of
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:177902:114"/> miracles. it makes the dead to riſe, the blinde to ſee, the dumb to ſpeake; and who can worke theſe but the Lord? <hi>Vera Sani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Macar. hom,</hi> 44. <hi>Repentance a worke full of miracles.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>à Domino ſolo proficiſcitur,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. As one ſheep cannot heale another, but their health com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth from their ſhepheard; ſo the true health of our ſoules cometh from the great Paſtor and Shepheard of Iſrael, <hi>Qui Leones manſuefecit &amp; igni vim adurendi ademit, &amp;c.</hi> Hee that tamed the Lions, &amp; reſtrained the fire from burning, hee it is that muſt tame our wilde affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and moderate the fire of our deſires. Let Preachers when they goe to any ſuch worke, require the helping hand of the Lord to work with
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:177902:115"/> them: and let people anſwer, and pray with <hi>Ieremie, Conuert vs Lord, and we ſhal be conuerted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As ſinne averts man from God, ſo it peruerts him: repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance <note place="margin">An vnpeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ſinner is a peruerſ and mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and how.</note> by the contrary turnes a man to God againe, and recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth all that is in him. An vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent ſinner is a peruerted or monſtrous creature: for in him, that part is vndermoſt which ſhould be aboue. The ſoule that came from heauen, cleaueth to the duſt by his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy which was made of the earth: he can looke vp to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen but in regard of his ſoule: he is but earthly minded. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, hee hath his face where his back ſhould be, and by the contrary, the world which ſhould be behinde him, is euer
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:177902:115"/> before him, &amp; the price of the high calling of God: euen the riches of that glorious inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, which ſhould bee before him, he caſteth it behinde his backe, and hath no thought of it. And where a wiſe man hath alway his heart at his right hand, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10. That is ſet vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on beſt and moſt neceſſary things: this foole by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, hath his heart at his left hand, buſie about vaine &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable things, neglecting that one thing, which onely is needfull. And laſtly, hee hath that without which ſhould be within: for he ſhould be more beautifull within then with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out. But the beſt ſight ye will ſee in him, is that which is out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt: there<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> hee lookes like a
<pb facs="tcp:177902:116"/> painted ſepulchre, but within is full of rottenneſſe: So confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a creature, is miſerable man in his ſinnes; all is diſordered in him, he is <hi>Tartarus,</hi> a little hell on earth, a terror to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, a trouble vnto others, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vexed with reſtleſſe and fruitleſſe perturbations.</p>
            <p>But from this time, by the <note place="margin">But by grace he is recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed.</note> grace of repentance hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerteth &amp; turneth to the Lord his God, then a comfortable change and comely order is wrought in him, then the body becomes ſubiect vnto the ſoule, then the affections begin to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low reaſon, and order reſtored makes him a quiet and peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble heart, by the which he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins his heauen vpon earth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="211" facs="tcp:177902:116"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>VERSE. 14.</bibl>
               <q>Deliuer mee from blood, O God of my ſaluation, and my tongue ſhall ſing ioyfully of thy righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the middeſt of <note place="margin">Dauid <hi>can not ſatisfie himſelfe in ſeeking mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie for his ſinnes.</hi>
               </note> his promiſes wee ſee how he inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laces a new peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for mercie, for ſtill he found his conſcience preſſed with the greatneſſe of his ſinne, and therefore ſo oft as hee feeles it, ſo oft cals hee for mercy, ſin is ſoone committed as I ſaid, but the gilt, the terror and the ſecret accuſing voice therof not ſo eaſily diſcharged.</p>
            <pb n="212" facs="tcp:177902:117"/>
            <p> And that now hee diſcends <note place="margin">A generall confeſſion of ſinne is not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent.</note> in particular, it is to teach vs, that a generall confeſſion of ſin is not ſufficient, we muſt come to a particular, for it may truly be ſaid, that he hates no ſinne, who hates not one aboue the reſt, the ſin which hath woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded our conſcience deepeſt wil grieue vs ſoreſt, this is manifeſt in <hi>Dauid,</hi> who hauing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted two abhominable ſins, Adultery and Murther, in his particular confeſſion makes mention of the bloud, not of the adultery, for as in griefes of the body the greater paine makes the leſſe not to be felt, ſo is it in the griefe of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, though there be a griefe for all ſinne in the penitent, yet the griefe for the greateſt ſinne
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:177902:117"/> exceedes all the reſt.</p>
            <p>How heauy a ſinne the ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <note place="margin">Shedding of innocent blood a fearefull ſinne.</note> of innocent blood is, may appeare, if wee conſider theſe particulars. Firſt it is a deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the image of God, which cannot be without a great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the diuine maieſty. When <hi>Theodoſius</hi> had reſolued to ſlay many Citizens of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ochia for caſting downe the image of his wife, the Empreſſe <note place="margin">1 <hi>Becauſe it is a demoliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Gods image.</hi>
               </note> Placilla: It was a notable war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning which a certaine Macedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian ſent to him: If thou be ſo mooued for demoliſhing of the braſen image of Placilla, how ſhall God be offended at the deſtruction of man who is the liuely image of God, the loſſe of the one may ſoone be repared, but the loſſe of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:177902:118"/> can neuer be recouered, a Braſen-image caſt downe may be ſet vp againe in the ſame or a better eſtate; let a man once be ſlaine, and who can reuiue him?</p>
            <p>Secondly, if a man be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered <note place="margin">2 <hi>It puts out the life of man for whom Chriſt died, and ſo is iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to Chriſts death.</hi>
               </note> as he is a Chriſtian, he is a part of the price of Chriſts blood, I am commanded not to offend my brother for whom Chriſt died in a matter of meate and drinke, which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe is lawful, how then dare I ſlay him? Oh what a horrible crime is this to put out the life of that man, for whom Chriſt died, that he might pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe life vnto him! <note place="margin">3 <hi>It makes a man more vnnaturall then beaſts.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, the ſimilitude of nature makes it a greeuous ſin for a man to deſtroy his owne
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:177902:118"/> kind Euery hearb that growes out of the earth hath a ſeede or ſome other equiualent vertue, wherby it ſeekes the conſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his owne kinde: and brute beaſtes forbeare on ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: only vnnaturall man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroies his kinde, yea wee read that Lyons and Beares haue <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cent.</hi> 4. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 5.</note> ſpared chriſtians preſented na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked before them, but whom the beaſts did ſpare, them man more beaſtly then vnreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble beaſts did cruelly deuour.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, the fearefull pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of it declares, how <note place="margin">4 <hi>It is puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with fearefull plagues.</hi>
               </note> feareful a ſin it is. As in the firſt plague of Egypt all the waters therof were turned into blood, ſo is it with a murtherer, all is turned in blood to him, at his table his meate is ſeaſoned
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:177902:119"/> with the thought of it, in his reſting bed he is troubled with the dreames of euery one; whom he ſees he deemes to be a reuenger of blood, and euery noiſe which he heares, he feares as a meſſenger or fore-runner of blood.</p>
            <p>This ſinne then being ſo <note place="margin">In what ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity are they who thinke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent blood no burden.</note> grieuous as it is, we may eaſily conſider how it comes to paſſe, that prophane men thinke no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of it, the reaſon is here that their conſcience is ſleep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and cuſtome of ſin hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away ſenſe: ſo long as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uids</hi> conſcience was a ſleepe, he thought nothing of it, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares by his letter of <hi>Vriah,</hi> let not this trouble thee, hereof it is that men ſleeping in ſinne count ſhedding of innocent
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:177902:119"/> blood, ſome of them, but a paſtime, and others to be a pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and religion. Of the firſt <note place="margin">Ethnikes eſteeme it a paſtime.</note> ſort were Ethniques, who vſed combats betweene men vpon publike theaters, that by the ſlaughter of ſome men, they might make ſport vnto others: Of theſe ſaid Cyprian, <hi>Scelus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cyprian. epiſt.</hi> 2. <hi>Papiſts thinke it good reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>non tantum geritur, ſed docetur.</hi> Of the other ſorts are bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Papiſts, who thinke it good ſeruice to God to murther and ſlay ſuch, as are contrary min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to them in religion, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at this time I am content to ſpeake with Eraſmus, <hi>Non con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenit vt hoc argumento nos Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianos</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eras epiſt. ad volſium.</note> 
               <hi>declaremus, ſi quam pluri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos occiderimus, ſed ſi multos ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauerimus, alioqui citius futurum est, vt nos in Turcas degenere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi>
               <pb n="218" facs="tcp:177902:120"/> 
               <hi>quam Turcis in partes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtras pertrahamus, Et vt faeliciter cadat Martis ſemper ancipitis a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lea, fiet vt latius fortaſſe regnet pontifex aut huius cardanales, non vt latius regnet Chriſtus.</hi> It is not a good argument to proue our ſelues good Chriſtians, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we haue ſlaine many, but rather that we haue ſaued ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: otherwiſe it ſhall ſooner come to paſſe, that we ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate into <hi>Turkes,</hi> then turne Turkes into Chriſtians: And albeit the euent of battel which is alway doubtfull ſhould ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed as we would wiſh, it may well be that by blood ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the kingdom of the Pope and his Cardinals be encreaſed but the kingdome of Chriſt ſhall not by ſuch meanes be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged.</p>
            <pb n="219" facs="tcp:177902:120"/>
            <p> But howſoeuer to ſuch <note place="margin">A great mercie to be kept from ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent blood.</note> blind infidels the ſhedding of blood, bee either pleaſure or piety, yet to the godly whoſe conſcience is wakened it is an abominable ſinne: how ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full was <hi>Dauid</hi> when <hi>Abigail</hi> kept him from ſhedding of the bloud of <hi>Nabal.</hi> How hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily did he thanke God for kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping him from it. And when he had ſhed the bloud of <hi>Vriah,</hi> how earneſtly praies hee that God would deliuer him from it. When it was told <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Proof here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid <hi>and Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine.</hi>
               </note> there was no way to cure his leproſie, but by bathing him in the blood of an infant, (vpon what reſpect I know not not) it was a notable anſwere he gaue, <hi>Malo ſemper aegrotare quam tali remedio conualeſcere.</hi>
               <pb n="220" facs="tcp:177902:121"/> Let vs flee the burden of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent bloud, and this praier for pardoning mercy that <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> makes, let vs turne it in a prayer for preuenting mercy, <hi>Deliuer vs from blood, wee are the ſheepe of Chriſt Ieſus, let vs leaue the ſhedding of blood to rauening wolues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Deliuer me:</hi> No doubt <hi>Dauid</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Sinne hath firſt a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding power after an accuſing or controu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling power.</note> powred out theſe words from his ſenſe and feeling: his ſpeech imports a captiuity, hee was not a free man, but bound with the cords of his ſinnes; the commaunding power of it at this time he was freed from, though before it bound him: but he ſeekes to be deliuered from the controu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and accuſing power there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; this vexed him ſo that hee
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:177902:121"/> thinkes no ſhame publikely to aske God mercy for theſe ſins, by which hee had offended God, and giuen euill example to the Church: and men who haue fallen with him in publik ſinnes, and yet cannot be indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to giue glory to God, and remoue offence from his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple by as publike repentance, doe plainely declare that they were neuer touched with the conſcience of their ſinne.</p>
            <p>In the primitiue Church <note place="margin">The maner of publike repentance in the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue Church.</note> ſuch as had giuen publike of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, were not receiued with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out publike repentance, and humiliation, yea they made ſupplication to all the aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, <hi>Volo, veniam reus ſperet pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ambr. de paeniten. li.</hi> 1. <hi>ca.</hi> 16.</note> 
               <hi>cum lachymis, petat populi to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius fletibus vt ignoſcatur obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret,</hi>
               <pb n="222" facs="tcp:177902:122"/> 
               <hi>&amp; cum ſecundo vel tertio fuerit dilata eius communo, cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dat remiſsius ſe ſupplicaſſe.</hi> I will that he that is guilty hope for mercy, that he ſeeketh it with teares and mourning of the whole people: and if twice or thrice his receiuing to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munoin be refuſed to him, let him thinke that hee hath prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed more ſlackly then he ſhould and ſo humble himſelfe more intirely then hee hath done. And againe to the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, he ſaies, If thou hadſt a doe to ſatiſfie a man whom <note place="margin">How fooliſh are they who hauing committed publicke ſinnes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to make pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</note> thou hadſt offended, how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wouldeſt thou requeſt to ſue for thee at his hands? Now ſeeing thou haſt to ſeeke recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation with God, why im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploieſt thou not the praiers of
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:177902:122"/> all his his people, <hi>Vbi nihil eſt quod pudori eſſe debeat, niſi non fateri cum omnes ſimus pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores.</hi> For among vs nothing ſhould be a matter of ſhame, ſeeing wee are all ſinners, but not to confeſſe our ſinnes, <hi>Vbi ille laudabilior qui humilior, &amp; iuſtior qui abiectior.</hi> Heere hee is moſt worthy praiſe, who is moſt humble, and hee is moſt iuſt, who is moſt contrite, and deiected for ſinne. <hi>Fleat itaque pro te mater Eccleſia,</hi> let there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thy mother the Church mourne for thee.</p>
            <p>But if men who haue offended <note place="margin">This is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are not tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with the ſenſe of ſinne.</note> were touched with the ſenſe of ſinne, as <hi>Dauid</hi> was, they would not be aſhamed as publikly to confeſſe it and ſeeke mercy as he did. For as I ſaid, hee found
<pb n="294" facs="tcp:177902:123"/> himſelfe ſtraited with his own ſinnes. <hi>Infernus quidam animae rea eſt Conſcientia,</hi> a guilty conſcience is a hell to the ſoule and a ſore priſon, not like other priſons: for whereſoeuer the guilty man goes, he carries his priſon with him, and this is the equity of Gods iudgements, who inwraps ſinners in their ſinnes, and bindes them with the coardes of their own tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, whereof they cannot complaine.</p>
            <p>And this appeareth out of <note place="margin">How ſinne binds and captiues a man.</note> his owne words, when he ſaies, <hi>Deliuer me,</hi> His ſpeech tels, he found himſelfe captiued. Two manner of waies doth ſinne ſtrait, and bind any man; firſt, by the commanding power, of it, for then it oppreſſeth a
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:177902:123"/> man in ſuch a ſort, that hee can neither eate, nor ſleepe, till he obey it. An example of which tyranny we haue in <hi>Ammon,</hi> &amp; many mo. Next by the control<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling or accuſing power thereof, whereby in ſuch ſort ſinne committed, ſo ſtraites a man, that it ſuffers him not to heare nor thinke of any other thing, but of her accuſations onely, whereby the ſoule of man is filled with reſtleſſe feares, and horrible perturbations. Now at this time <hi>Dauid</hi> was not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with the commanding po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of ſin, but onely with the tormenting, &amp; accuſing power thereof; and from it heere hee praies the Lord to deliuer him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>From blouds:</hi> The word is plural, <hi>from blouds.</hi> Noting vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:177902:124"/> vs, how <hi>Dauid</hi> found euery <note place="margin">Innocent blood when it is ſhed fals not to the ground, but biaes on the head of him that ſhed it.</note> drop of <hi>Vriah</hi> his bloud a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den vnto him. By the phraſe of holy Scripture, the bloud of him that is ſhedde is ſaid to lie vpon his head that ſhed it. It ſeemeth vnto men, that the bloud of the man ſlaine is ſpilt on the ground: but the ſpirit of God ſaith, that it lieth on the man ſlayer. A fearefull thing: the bloud which before was in the body of thy neighbour, to conſerue his life, thou haſt now taken it vpon thy head, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure thy death, and to crie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God for a vengance againſt thee. If this were conſidered, it might ſerue for an awe-band to keepe murtherers from haſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as they do, to ſhedde inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent bloud.</p>
            <pb n="227" facs="tcp:177902:124"/>
            <p> And albeit <hi>Dauid</hi> was farre <note place="margin">Many waies may men be guilty of ſinne, albeit by their own hands they doe it not.</note> from <hi>Vriah,</hi> when he was ſlain; for the one was in Ieruſalem, the other in Rabbah of the Ammonites, yet the burden of that bloud lieth heauy on him, becauſe hee was the man who counſelled <hi>Ioab,</hi> how to ſlay him with the ſworne of the Ammonites. Many waies haue men, whereby to excuſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in their ſinne; ſpecially, if they did not euill with their owne hands, if they were farre off, when the turne was done: but you ſee how little all theſe auaile, where the conſcience cannot excuſe a man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O God of my ſaluation.</hi> So the godly ſtile the Lord; not onely <note place="margin">Praiſe of our ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on properly belongs to God.</note> becauſe he is the author of the beginning, but of the progreſſe
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:177902:125"/> alſo, and perfiting of our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: he not onely gaue life to our ſoules, when we were dead in ſin, but he keepes our ſoules in life: we fall, and he raiſeth vs vp: we wander, and he recalls vs: we ſinne daily, and he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueth vs. And it is for theſe renewing mercies, wherby the Lord euery day ſaues vs from a thouſand deaths, in which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe we ſhould periſh; that we praiſe the Lord as the God of our ſaluation: giuing him this glorie with the Apoſtle, <hi>The Lord hath deliuered vs from ſo great a death, he doth deliuer</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>vs: in whom alſo we truſt, that yet hereafter he will deliuer vs.</hi> For the time paſt he hath deliuer'd, for the time preſent hee doth deliuer, and for the time to
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:177902:125"/> come he will deliuer vs: In all theſe reſpects wee reioyce in him as in the God of our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Againe, hee acknowledges <note place="margin">Many great deliueran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces receiue the godly but the greateſt is deliuerance from ſinne.</note> that the deliuerance of a man from his ſinnes, is not a worke of mans Power. No, it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires the powerful hand, and ſauing health of the mighty God of our ſaluation. Many great deliuerances hath the Lord giuen to his annointed; hee ſaued <hi>Noah</hi> from the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge of waters, <hi>Lot</hi> from bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in Sodome, he ſaued Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el in the Red ſea, and <hi>Ionas</hi> in the Whales belly, he ſaued <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> from the Lyons, and <hi>Peter</hi> that he did not ſinke, when he walked in the water: but the deliuerance of a man from the
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:177902:126"/> hands of Satan, and ſinne is a greater work then any of theſe, let vs be thankefull to our God for it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>So ſhall I ſing:</hi> a ſoule oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <note place="margin">God hath fitted the exerciſes of his worſhip for our ſtate.</note> and borne downe with the terrors of ſinne, cannot ſing to the praiſe of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> a Chriſtian in that eſtate, anſwers al that find fault with him, as the Iſraelites of old did the Caldees, <hi>How can</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 97.</note> 
               <hi>wee ſing a ſong of the Lord in a ſtrange land?</hi> (and how can I ſaies the Chriſtian) ſing ioyful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, ſo long as the Comforter that ſhould refreſh my ſoule is away? But bleſſed be the Lord who in euery ſtate hath proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a remedy for vs, that when we are not diſpoſed for one ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of Gods worſhip, the Lord ſhould licence vs to go vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:177902:126"/> an other. Are we ſo afflicted <note place="margin">Iam.</note> that we cannot ſing, at leaſt let vs pray that wee may be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted?</p>
            <p>And in that he ſaies hee will <note place="margin">In ſinging pſalmes our affection ſhould be conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the word wee ſing.</note> ſing ioyfully, it learnes vs how we ſhould alway conforme our affections to the words which God puts either in our eares or in our mouthes. If the word of the L. when we heare it or ſing it, haue a promiſe of mercy or a ſong of thankſgiuing, ſhould wee not receiue it and vtter it with ioy? and if on the other hand it containe a threatning, or a confeſſion of ſinne, ſhould we not heare it with griefe and contrition: this is it which is taught vs in that parable, if the Lord Pipe we ſhould dance, if he mourne we ſhould ſorrow,
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:177902:127"/> And as his word is, ſo ſhould we conform our affections. But this diſcouers the Atheiſme of this age, whether they heare the word or reade it: no change of the Scripture changes their heart: one Chapter or Pſalme makes them not to reioice, and another to bee ſorrowfull, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they heare all, they ſing all after one manner, that is, for faſhion ſake, without any ſenſe or feeling.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Of thy righteouſneſſe.</hi> But <note place="margin">A two-fold righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in God worthy prayſes.</note> how is this that Gods righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe is the matter of our thankſe-giuing? Are not his righteous iudgements fearefull and terrible to ſinners? But we muſt knowe the ſortes of Gods righteouſneſſe: there is one wherby he puniſheth the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:177902:127"/> and impenitent, another whereby he pardoneth the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing penitent. And of this ſpake <hi>Abraham: God forbid that the Iudge of all the world ſhold do vnrighteouſly;</hi> He meant in condemning godly <hi>Lot</hi> with the vngodly Sodomites. And this is greatly for our comfort, that the Lord when hee par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doneth our ſinnes, he is a righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous God, both becauſe hee hath ſo promiſed, as alſo that our ſinnes are already puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Chriſt Ieſus: ſo that the mercie which we get doth no way violate his righteouſneſſe. And we whom he hath recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued into mercie, are in ſuch ſort to praiſe him for his mercy, that we may alſo ſing ioyfully of his righteouſneſſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="234" facs="tcp:177902:128"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>VERSE. 15.</bibl>
               <q>Open thou my lippes, O Lord, and my mouth ſhall ſhew forth thy praiſe.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Verſe contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth a new peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <note place="margin">The tongue to ſpeake, a great bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of God.</note> wherein he craues that God would open his tongue, which his ſinnes had cloſed, that hee might praiſe God, as hee was wont to doe. The naturall vſe of the tongue is Gods great benefit, yea, and a miraculous worke, that a member of fleſh ſhould bee an interpreter of a heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly mind, and as it were, a Trenchman,
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:177902:128"/> whereby the ſpirit of one man knowes what is the meaning of another.</p>
            <p>But as Conſuetude drawes Gods moſt excellent workes in <note place="margin">Diſ-eſteemd now, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is common.</note> contempt: ſo among the reſt this is thought nothing, to ſpeake with a tongue only, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is common; yet Gods children acknowledge it to be Gods benefite, and the Lord glories in it as in his own work. When <hi>Moſes</hi> complayned that hee was not meete to bee the Lords Embaſſadour, becauſe he was not cloquent, but ſlow of ſpeech, he receiued this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, <hi>Who hath giuen the mouth to man, or who hath made the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Exod.</note> 
               <hi>dumbe or the deafe, or him that ſeeth, or the blinde? Is it not I, the Lord?</hi> When he will he makes
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:177902:129"/> the dumbe to ſpeake, and the cloquent to be ſilent: <hi>Out of the mouths of babes hath hee ordained</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal.</note> 
               <hi>ſtrength:</hi> hee openeth the mouths of children to confeſſe his name, &amp; cloſes the mouthes of ancient men, as we ſee in <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chary,</hi> and all to teach that the benefit of the tongue is from the Lord.</p>
            <p>This benefit ſin tooke away from man that now naturally, <note place="margin">Sin takes away the vſe of the tongue, that man cannot ſpeake as be he ſhould.</note> when he opens his mouth and moues his tongue, he ſpeaks to the offence and diſhonour of God who made him: the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit to ſpeake he hath it giuen of God, but abuſeth it ſo through the corruption of his nature, that he ſpeak's not as he ſhould like vnto a man ſicke of the palſie, who by natural ſtrength
<pb n="237" facs="tcp:177902:129"/> moues his hand; but through his corrupt humours moues it inordinatly, and as this way the <note place="margin">It had been good for many men that they could neuer haue ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> mouing of the hand is a pain to the one, ſo is the mouing of the tongue without order both a ſinne and puniſhment to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Of theſe it may be ſaid that Satan opens their mouths, and not God, and good had it beene for them to haue beene ſtricken with naturall dumb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe all their daies, for ſo ſhould their ſinnes haue beene the fewer, and their puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the leſſe.</p>
            <p>And this is the loſſe, of the <note place="margin">The mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold euill effects of ſinne.</note> tongue, whereof now <hi>Dauid</hi> complaines, and which he cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth to be redreſſed. Where we haue to marke, how manie fearful euils his ſin had brought
<pb n="238" facs="tcp:177902:130"/> vpon him: it had ſtolne away his heart, peruerted his ſpirit, ſtopped his eares, and cloſed his mouth, that hee could not thinke, nor will, nor heare, nor ſpeake as he was wont to doe; therefore prayes he againſt all theſe in ſeuerall petitions, that God would create a clean hart in him, renue a right ſpirit in him: that God would make him heare ioy &amp; gladneſſe, and open his mouth to ſpeak again the prayſes of God.</p>
            <p>Such are the miſerable ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sinne takes away ſenſe of miſery, duety and all. Eph.</hi> 4.</note> of ſin: it takes from man all ſenſes both inward and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and leaues him without feeling; ſo that he is no more moued when hee doth euill, then if it were good, yea, not touched with fear of the iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="239" facs="tcp:177902:130"/> due to ſinne: but as <hi>Lots</hi> kinſmen made a mock of Gods iudgements, when they heard it, ſo doe they make a mocke of ſinne, &amp; of all that may follow it; but one day they ſhall feele the bitter fruits thereof. Men in their ſins are like vnto fooles or young children: when their parents or friends periſh they mourne not, for they know not the loſſe, and they care not to exchange the charters of their inheritance with trifles, but when they come to the yeares of diſcretion, and feele the loſſe, then they mourne, and lament for that which in their ignorance they little regarded. It is euen ſo with men, who as long as their ſinne blinds them, cannot mourne, but when God
<pb n="240" facs="tcp:177902:131"/> ſhall waken them, and they ſee the euil of it, then they take vp a bitter lamentation for it, and can get no reſt night nor day, til God of his mercy pardon and forgiue it.</p>
            <p>Againe ye ſee, that if we be <note place="margin">They who can not ſpeakc to the priſe of God are ſtricken with a ſore plague.</note> gouerned by the ſpirit of God, we will account that wee are ſtricken with dumneſſe, when we cannot ſpeake to the praiſe of God. Many are ſuch in this age, who haue a tongue for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery purpoſe, but none for the praiſes of God, they are ſtrick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en with a ſore plague, and yet they feele it not, their heart is bound by Satan with the cords of their ſinnes, and ſo their tongues cannot be looſed to glorifie God: from this moſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable eſtate the Lord deliuer vs.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="241" facs="tcp:177902:131"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>VERSE. 16.</bibl>
               <q>For thou deſirest no ſacrifice though I would giue it, thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightest not in burnt offerings.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this verſe <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ioy for Gods mercy and ſorrow for our own ſinnes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree well in the godly.</note> giues a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, why hee promiſed no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther duety of thankefullneſſe to the Lord, but to praiſe him, as hee prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted hee would doe in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer verſe: the reaſon is, becauſe the ſacrifice in man or from man which God likes beſt, is the ſacrifice of a contrite ſpirit. Then ye ſee, that <hi>Dauid</hi> when he ſacrificed praiſe, ſacrificed
<pb n="242" facs="tcp:177902:132"/> alſo a contrite ſpirit, what is it to giue thankes for Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, if all the ſame time we be not ſorrowfull, that we ſhould haue offended ſo mercifull a God? The thankes giuen by many is taſtles to God, becauſe when they are touched with ſome ſenſe of that God hath done to them, they feele no remorſe of that euill, they haue done againſt him: happy is the ſoule wherein theſe two meete together; a ioy for Gods mercies toward vs, and a ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for our ſinnes againſt God.</p>
            <p>And againe, ye ſee that if a <note place="margin">What praiſe is accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to God.</note> man praiſe God truely, he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers with praiſes himſelfe, and all that he may doe: <hi>My ſoule praiſe thou the Lord, and all that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.</note> 
               <hi>is within mee praiſe thou his holy</hi>
               <pb n="243" facs="tcp:177902:132"/> 
               <hi>name:</hi> As he ſhewes in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent verſe; <hi>The ſacrifices of God are a contrite ſpirit.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he declares, that in thankeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing to God, hee offered a thankefull heart for bee-gone mercies, a ſorrowfull heart for bee-gone ſins, a reſolute heart in time to come to amend: And this is the praiſe wherein God delightes.</p>
            <p>But heere ariſes a threefold <note place="margin">A threefold doubt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</note> doubt: firſt ſeeing the legall ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices commanded by God; how can it be ſaid the Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires not that which he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded? ſecondly, is not the Apoſtles praecept <hi>To doe good</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.</note> 
               <hi>and diſtribute forget not, for with ſuch ſacrifices God is pleaſed?</hi> And thirdly, are not wee comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to <hi>offer vp our bodies a liuing</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.</note>
               <pb n="244" facs="tcp:177902:133"/> 
               <hi>ſacrifice holy and acceptable to God,</hi> how is it then that heere <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeakes that God deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth no ſacrifice.</p>
            <p>To theſe it is anſwered, that <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The firſt is anſwered,</hi> Dauid <hi>doth not ſimply re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect legal ſacrifices.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeakes not ſimply, but by way of compariſo, theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal ſacrifices, if they be alone wanting the internall ſacrifices of a contrite ſpirit, are not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to God, and of this for the firſt doubt, we learne that if vnder the law externall wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip without the inward plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed not the Lord, far leſſe will it now pleaſe him vnder the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell: <hi>Curſed</hi> (ſaid Malachie) <hi>is the man who hath a male in his flocke, and vowes an ſacrifices a corrupt thing to the Lord:</hi> And this curſe is now double vpon them, who giue not the beſt
<pb n="245" facs="tcp:177902:133"/> they haue to the Lord, drawing neere him with their lips, but far from him in their hearts.</p>
            <p>As to the ſecond, externall <note place="margin">The ſecond anſwered, almes and ſuch ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of God if they flow from faith.</note> ſacrifices of almes and ſuch like now commanded, pleaſe the Lord out of all doubt, if they proceed from faith in Chriſt, offered out of a contrite ſpirit, not puft vp with conceit of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, the humble heart makes a ſmall gift to be great, an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple whereof we haue in the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes mite, it was a ſmal thing but becauſe it proceeded from a great affection, Chriſt accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it the greateſt gift was offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that day: And the want of a good heart on the contraty makes a great gift to be ſmall, an example whereof we haue in <hi>Cain</hi> his ſacrifice, in it ſelfe
<pb n="246" facs="tcp:177902:134"/> rich enough, but becauſe it proceeded from a poore affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it was not acceptable to God: Ten thouſand riuers of oile, and all the beaſts on thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand mountaines, yea in all the Foreſt of Lebanon are nothing to the Lord, if the heart be not rightly ſet that offers them.</p>
            <p>And as to the third, we are <note place="margin">The third anſwered wee are bound to offer our bodies but euery offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the body is not acceptable to God.</note> bound to offer vp our bodies vnto him, but remember euery offering of the bodie pleaſes him not, ſome of a blinde zeale becomes the buriers of their owne bodies, like <hi>Baal</hi> his Prieſts, Turkiſh Derbies and Popiſh Penitentiaries, cutting, lancing and renting their fleſh; or elſe defrauding their bodies of that due, which they owe vnto him, prodigall of them in
<pb n="247" facs="tcp:177902:134"/> their blind zeale, not moderat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſubdueing them by diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plin. If euery ſuch ſacrifice had pleaſed God, the Apoſtle would not haue ſaid, <hi>though I feede the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.</note> 
               <hi>poore with all my goods, and though I giue my body to be bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, if I haue no loue, it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing:</hi> we muſt firſt ſee, that the heart be ſacrificed to the Lord, and then the body in the reſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nable ſeruice thereof, for no vnreaſonable ſuduing of the body pleaſes God.</p>
            <p>But what ſhall be ſaid of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <note place="margin">Atheiſts conuinced who do not ſo much as offer exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to the Lord.</note> profane Atheiſts, who now doe not offer ſo much as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall ſactifices? they will not reſort to the aſſemblies of Gods ſaints, to giue God in his houſe external praier and prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: neither offer they to the
<pb n="248" facs="tcp:177902:135"/> poore externall almes, nor to God the externall ſeruice of their bodies, they bow not the knee, they lift not their hand, they vſe not the members of their body as weapons of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and how then ſhal we thinke they make conſcience of Gods in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal worſhip. But now to the words in particular.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="249" facs="tcp:177902:135"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>VERSE. 17.</bibl>
               <q>The ſacrifices of God are a contrite ſpirit: a contrite and a broken heart, o God, thou wilt not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E firſt learne that <note place="margin">Some offer to the Lord that which is theirs, but not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. Sauan.</note> if any man would offer a ſacrifice conuenient for the Lord, let him prepare the ſpirit and the minde, God himſelfe is a ſpirit, and will be worſhipped in ſpirit, hee lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth truth in the inward affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, <hi>Corpora fecit propter ſpiritus, ideoque etiam ſpiritualia non corporea quaerit:</hi> hee made alſo the bodies for the ſpirits,
<pb n="250" facs="tcp:177902:136"/> and therefore ſeekes he not bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily without ſpirituall ſeruice. Some there are <hi>qui ſua dant, non ſeipſos,</hi> who offer to him not themſelues, but that which is theirs, but it is a blinde folly to thinke thou canſt pleaſe him with gifts, when thou wilt not giue the ſeruice of thine heart, and ſpirit vnto him.</p>
            <p>But leaſt wee ſhould thinke <note place="margin">Contrition of spirit many waies<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> expreſſed in ſcripture.</note> that euery ſpirit is acceptable to God: he addes this epithet, That a Contrite ſpirit is Gods ſacrifice, or as after he cals it a broken heart<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it is called by <hi>Ioel</hi> a rent heart, by <hi>Eſay</hi> it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to a bruiſed reed, and it is alſo called a pricking of the heart and a melting heart: ſuch as was in <hi>Ioſiah.</hi> All which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports none other but that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="251" facs="tcp:177902:136"/> vnfained ſorrow which is in a penitent ſoule, for of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences done againſt God.</p>
            <p>Then were beaſts vnder the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>As beaſts in the Law were</hi> 1. <hi>bound,</hi> 2. <hi>ſlaine,</hi> 3. <hi>ſacrificed, ſo muſt our ſpirits be.</hi>
               </note> law ſaid to be ſacrificed to the Lord, when they were taken from commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; prophan vſes, bound with cords to the horns of the Altar, afterward ſlaine &amp; offered by fire vnto God. And ſo is it to be done with our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, if wee minde to ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice them to the Lord, we muſt firſt ſeparate them from their wonted wanderings, wee muſt binde them with the cords of Gods word, and lay them downe at the feete of Chriſt as his captiues, by godly ſorrow: we muſt ſlay that ſinfull plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure which was the former life of our affection, and then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="252" facs="tcp:177902:137"/> they ſacrifices vnto God.</p>
            <p>But heere the difference is <note place="margin">But in theſe ſacrifices beaſts offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red loſt their liues, here men ſacrificed recouer their liues.</note> great: for beaſts ſacrificed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the law loſt their liues, and became dead creatures, that they might be ſacrificed. But we, when wee are ſacrificed, of dead creatures are made liuing: wee being dead in ſinnes and treſpaſſes, then begin to liue when ſinne is ſlaine, and ſinfull luſts mortified in vs. Oh that wee could remember this, that the ſtrife betweene vs and ſin, is here, Who ſhall ſlay other: if ſinne liue, we muſt die: if we ſlay it, we ſhall liue: except we binde our affections, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them captiues to Chriſt, they ſhall binde vs, and deliuer vs captiues to Satan.</p>
            <p>And that yet better we may
<pb n="253" facs="tcp:177902:137"/> know the quality and valour <note place="margin">Three things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre to a contrite ſpirit.</note> of a contrite ſpirit, let vs conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der theſe things in it: firſt, an inward ſorrow for ſinne, which cauſeth repentance to ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <note place="margin">1 <hi>An inward ſorrow.</hi>
               </note> not to be repented of. Sinne is contracted with carnall plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, but is diſſolued with ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall diſpleaſure: euen as the cauſe of ſickeneſſe is remoued by medicine, which is contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to it. And this godly dolor is not onely profitable to cure ſinnes paſt, but alſo to preuent them in time to come. <hi>Cum do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemus admiſſa, admittenda exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimus,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amb. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de paeniten. cap.</hi> 10.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; fit quaedam de condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natione culpae, diſciplina innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae:</hi> for when wee mourne for ſinnes done, we cloſe the doore vpon ſinnes to be don, and the damning of our former faults,
<pb n="254" facs="tcp:177902:138"/> becomes a diſcipline, whereby we are inſtructed to amend in time to come.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in a contrite ſpirit there is a great ſincerity: it is <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sincerity without diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimulation.</hi>
               </note> that <hi>bleſſed ſpirit, wherein there is no guile;</hi> no couering nor diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling of ſinne: for as in a thing which is brayed &amp; ſtam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, the very inward parts of it are made manifeſt, and that which before was with a skin or ſhel, is now preſented to the eye of man: ſo is it in a ſoule truely humbled: theſe ſinnes which were ſecret &amp; couered, the contrite ſpirit caſts them out, and makes them open to God &amp; man, fearing no ſhame in the eyes of man, if ſo be it may finde mercie in the eyes of God. And therefore ſaid
<pb n="255" facs="tcp:177902:138"/> 
               <hi>Augustine</hi> of contrition, that it was <hi>Sanitas animarum, holo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caustum medullarum,</hi> a health of the ſoule, and an offering to God, not of any outward mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but of the inward marrow.</p>
            <p>And thirdly, this true con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition is neuer without faith, <note place="margin">3 <hi>True faith with an earneſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of mercie.</hi>
               </note> which cauſeth ſuch a veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t deſire of mercie, as maketh the ſoule of man to long, to wait, to faint, to crie, to hunger, to thirſt for Gods conſolation: the delay whereof makes the ſoule of the creature pine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with inward griefe, and he becoms like that book, wherin <hi>Ezechiel</hi> ſaw written, lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug. Ezech.</hi> 11.</note> and wo: for ſtill he cries, Wo is me, alwayes til the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter com, and aſſure him that his ſinnes are forgiuen him.</p>
            <pb n="256" facs="tcp:177902:139"/>
            <p> Now this being ſpoken of <note place="margin">A contrite ſpirit called ſacrifices in the plurall and why.</note> the contrit ſpirit, we are to ſee, why hee cals it ſacrifices in the plurall number, the reaſons heereof are two, firſt becauſe this is more worth in Gods eies then all the legall ſacrifices, though they were ioyned in one, this one excelleth them al, &amp; next becauſe in the contrite ſpirit are many ſacrifices, for it ſtrikes the life of euery ſinfull affection, and ſo ſacrifices ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny beaſts to the Lord: <hi>Nam ſi</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gregor. Moral.</note> 
               <hi>vis compunctionis in intimis affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit, omnis ſtrepitus prauae ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis obinuteſcit,</hi> for if once the ſting of godly compunction touch the heart, incontinent the whiſpering of wicked ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion is ſilenced.</p>
            <p>Vnder the law ſuch as wee
<pb n="257" facs="tcp:177902:139"/> Nobles and Princes offered <note place="margin">
                  <hi>As Princes vnder the law multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices: ſo now pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull Chriſtians are diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations.</hi> 2. <hi>Chro.</hi> 7.</note> great oblations, which far ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded the offerings of the poore. Wee read at one time <hi>Salomon</hi> offered many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſacrifices, the common people contenting themſelues with the offering of Pigeons and ſuch like more ſimple ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices: But now Princes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Gods people in Gods e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimation are they, who ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice moſt of their ſinfull affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons vnto him. If the Lord ſhould ſend vs to the boſome of the earth, to the deepe bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of the ſea, to the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ends of the world, to ſeeke a ſacrifice for him, wee might moſt iuſtly be aſtoniſhed, and ſpecially the poorer ſorte, whoſe meanes may not extend
<pb n="258" facs="tcp:177902:140"/> to the furniture of ſo great a ſacrifice, but now O man, ſince <note place="margin">They are inexcuſable who ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice not to God, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that which be craues is within them.</note> the Lord requires no thing, but that which is within thee, or at leaſt may be and ſhould be, if thou haue not to offer him a contrite ſpirit, a ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full heart for ſinne; is not all excuſe taken away from thee? God hath proclaimed to men, what is the ſacrifice that plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth him, and if any man offer it not vnto him, it is not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he may not, but becauſe he will not: for in this ſacrifice the poore may excell the moſt rich and honourable men in the world. <note place="margin">A contrite ſpirit is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Gods ſacrifice, becauſe he is the giuer of it.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And yet further, that hee cals the contrite ſpirit the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of God, imports that he is the giuer of this grace: he pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<pb n="259" facs="tcp:177902:140"/> vpon his people the ſpirit of grace and compaſſion, which cauſes them to mourne: hee takes away the ſtony heart and giues them a heart of fleſh. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as he prouided a ſacrifice for <hi>Abraham,</hi> when hee called him to worſhip on Mount <hi>Moriah,</hi> ſo doth hee not onely honour his children to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers of his maieſty, but alſo giues vs grace, whereby we doe it: that ſuch wormes as we are haue place to ſtand before ſo great a maieſty as he is, it is of his fauour: that we haue hearts diſpoſed to pray to him or praiſe him, is of his grace: and that hee anſwers vs, is of his own vnſpeakable mercie. And in theſe reſpects is the ſacrifice we offer called Gods ſacrifice.</p>
            <pb n="260" facs="tcp:177902:141"/>
            <p> Hee is not like vnto other <note place="margin">Earthly kings loue mirthbetter then mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, the Lord doth not ſo.</note> Kings, for commonly they loue mirth better then mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, <hi>Ioſeph</hi> mourning for <hi>Iacob</hi> his father, might not come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Pharao: Nehemiah</hi> with his ſad countenance was afraid to ſtand before <hi>Artarxerxes: Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decai</hi> with his mourning weed, entred not the courts of <hi>Aha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuerus,</hi> but we are moſt welcom to the Lord, when wee come with our mourning weedes: <hi>Achabs</hi> ſackcloth profited him ſomething, but <hi>Iezabel,</hi> hir atti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and painting of hir face a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed nothing, ſhe was caſt to the dunghill, as a portion for dogges: Our face is neuer ſo pleaſant, as when it is watered with the teares of a penitent heart. <hi>My Doue that mourneth</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Cant.</note>
               <pb n="261" facs="tcp:177902:141"/> 
               <hi>in the clefts of the rocke, let me ſee thy face.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now in this that wee haue ſpoken concerning the ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces <note place="margin">The great ſacrifice of Chriſtians which maks al other ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable, is Chriſt.</note> of God, let vs remember, that there is one great &amp; prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall ſacrifice, which for the valour of it ſelfe is acceptable to God, that is the ſacrifice of Chriſt once for all offered vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the croſſe, all other only in this and for this are acceptable to him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou wilt neuer diſpiſe.</hi> What <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The end of godly mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is ioy. Macar. hom.</hi> 15.</note> fruite ariſeth of a mourning heart for ſin he now ſubioynes, the Lord neuer diſpiſeth it, at no time, in no perſon. It ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders comfort not onely for the time to come, but alſo for the time preſent, <hi>ipſaelachrymae ſunt vice delitiarum,</hi> for euen teares
<pb n="262" facs="tcp:177902:142"/> are in ſteed of delights, and Gods children finde more ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid ioy in their preſent mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, then worldlings can in their mirth and greateſt reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cings. And as for the time to come, we know that our mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning will be turned into ioy, and all teares ſhall be wiped a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from our eies, <hi>ſicut poſt ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hementes</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chryſ. in Math. hom.</hi> 6.</note> 
               <hi>imbres aer purus effici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ita lachrymarum pluuias ſere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitas mentis ſequitur.</hi> For as af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſhowers of raine the aire is clearer, ſo after the teares of repentance, the mind becomes calme, perturbations ceaſe, and the ſoule is pacified. <note place="margin">Contrition of ſpirit an excellent grace and we ſhould delight in it.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Since a contrite ſpirit is ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent a grace, as brings com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort preſently, and much more for the time to come, for <hi>they</hi>
               <pb n="263" facs="tcp:177902:142"/> 
               <hi>that ſow in teares ſhall reape in ioy: Bleſſed are they that mourne, for they ſhal be comforted.</hi> What a folly is it that we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not mourn, how ſhall the Lord gather our teares, which we ſcatter not? or how ſhall he wipe thoſe teares from our eies, which we neuer ſhed? or ſhal he comfort vs that mourne not? No ſacrifice is more acceptable to him, none more pleaſing to him, none more profitable for our ſelues: and why then are we not care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to be more abundant in it? <hi>Nemo potest, &amp; in hac vita &amp; in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Aug.</note> 
               <hi>futura gaudere: Neceſſe est vnam amittat, qui alteram vult poſside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re:</hi> No man can haue pleaſure here, &amp; hereafter alſo. He that receiues his conſolation heere, let him looke for deſolation
<pb n="264" facs="tcp:177902:143"/> hereafter, that anſwer giuen to on, ſerues for all the wicked, <hi>In thy life time thou receiuedſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 65. 13.</note> 
               <hi>and</hi> Lazarus <hi>paines: now therefore is hee comforted, and thou tormented:</hi> And again, <hi>My ſeruants ſhall eate and yee ſhall be hungry, my ſeruants ſhall drinke and ye ſhall be thirsty, my ſeruants ſhall reioyce, and ye ſhal be aſhamed, my ſeruants ſhall ſing for ioy of heart, and ye ſhall cry for ſorrow of heart, and ſhall houle for vexation of minde,</hi> God make vs wiſe, that wee may make choiſe of the beſt, to mourne now with Gods ſeruants, and hereafter alſo be comforted with them.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="265" facs="tcp:177902:143"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>VERSE. 18.</bibl>
               <q>Be fauourable vnto Sion for thy good pleaſure, build vp the wals of Ieruſalem.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow followes the <note place="margin">The ſecond part of the Pſalme, contayning a praier for the Church.</note> ſecond part of the Pſal. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he praies for the Church of God, after that he hath praied for himſelfe. His order is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good; to haue done the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, and neglected the firſt had beene vnprofitable: for with what ſucceſſe canſt thou pray for others, who art not reconciled with God, thy ſelfe? And again if he had contented
<pb n="266" facs="tcp:177902:144"/> him with the firſt, and negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted the ſecond, he had beene vndutifull.</p>
            <p>For all they who are liuely <note place="margin">The gody prefer the welfare of the Church to their own priuate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> members of the Church, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the good of the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, vnto their own particular welfare; as we ſee in good <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemiah:</hi> all his honor and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment in the Court of <hi>Artah<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhast,</hi> was not ſo pleaſant vnto him, as the deſolation of Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem was grieuous. The wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked by the contrary, like <hi>Tobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi> and <hi>Sanhallat,</hi> with the reſt of theſe Samaritans, are grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, when they heare that Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalems wals are a building: and miſerable <hi>Haman</hi> made a plain confeſſion, that all his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, wherunto he was aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, did him not ſo much good
<pb n="267" facs="tcp:177902:144"/> as the welfare of <hi>Mordecai,</hi> and of the people of the Iewes, did him euill. Wo be vnto all them that are of ſuch a diſpoſition; not onely ſtrangers, but ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to Iſraels Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-wealth, they ſhall neuer reioyce with the ioy of Gods children: but wee will pray for Ieruſalem, <hi>That proſperity may be within her wals, &amp; peace within her Palaces.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dauid</hi> had hurt his people, <note place="margin">Repentance teacheth vs to repaire wrongs we haue done.</note> not onely by giuing them an euill example, &amp; by wakening Gods wrath againſt them; but by deliuering a number of them to the ſword of the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monites for <hi>Vriah</hi> his ſake: and now he benefites them by his prayer. This true repentance will teach vs, firſt, to reſtore the Lord to his glory, and then to
<pb n="268" facs="tcp:177902:145"/> repaire the wrong wee haue done to any man, ſo far as we may.</p>
            <p>Againe, we haue to marke <note place="margin">An example of happie loue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene a good King and his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</note> 
               <hi>Dauid</hi> his father loue to his people: hee had hurt them twice, once now by his adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and murther, and after by numbring the people, for the which God diminiſhed their number by peſtilence. And both the times his heart was ſore grieued for them, as he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares by his prayer, that both heere and there he makes for them: <hi>It is I</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>that haue ſinned, and committed the euill, but theſe poore ſheepe, what haue they done? O Lord God, let thine hand be on me, and on my fathers houſe, and not on thy people for their destruction.</hi> What a loue
<pb n="269" facs="tcp:177902:145"/> is here! he wiſheth himſelfe to be ſtriken, that his people may be ſpared: and they againe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payed him with the like louing affection, for when he would haue gone out to battel againſt <hi>Abſalom,</hi> they would not let him hazard himſelfe: <hi>Thou art</hi> (ſaid they) <hi>more worth then ten thouſand of vs.</hi> A happy har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie, where a King with ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der affection embraceth his people as his owne children, and they again eſteeme and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence him as their father.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For thy good pleaſure.</hi> He ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">The Church is preſerued by Gods mercy, not their merit.</note> pretends his merits, nor his peoples innocency, but ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peales to Gods mercie: the good pleaſure of his owne will mou'd him to chuſe a Church, and it is the ſame that moues
<pb n="270" facs="tcp:177902:146"/> him to conſerue it. Euen when the ſins of his people procure that he ſhold deſtroy it, if there were no more to preſerue the Church, but hir owne deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings, or the fauour, fidelity, and conſtancie of Kings, prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors thereof, it could not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue long; but God is the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Ieruſalem, his fauour is the wall thereof, and therefore is it, that neither the ſinnes of them who are within, nor ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of them who are without it can ouercome it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Build vp the wales.</hi> He praies <note place="margin">Ieruſalems materiall walles were foure.</note> both for the materiall and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall wals of Ieruſalem. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of materiall wals, Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem was a ſtrong City, of foure quarters, euery one of them by walles deuided from another.
<pb n="271" facs="tcp:177902:146"/> The firſt &amp; higheſt was mount Sion, in it was the City of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> called by <hi>Ioſephus</hi> the ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour city, exceeding ſtrong in regard of the naturall ſituation thereof: the ſecond was called the daughter of <hi>Sion,</hi> becauſe it ſeemed to come out, as it were, of the boſome of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in this was the mount <hi>Moriah,</hi> whereupon the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſtood: this City was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed with a ſtrong wal wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſtood threeſcore of ſtrong Towres. The third was beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified with many ample ſtreets pleaſant ports, and compaſſed with a wall, whereupon were fourteene Towers. The fourth was inhabited by all ſorts of Artificers, compaſſed with the third wall which was twenty
<pb n="272" facs="tcp:177902:147"/> and fiue cubits high, and had in it foureſcore and ten Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſtrong, high and foure cornered.</p>
            <p>And albeit in <hi>Dauids</hi> daies <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Externall ſtate of a citie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends on Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Pſal.</hi> 127.</note> the city was not as yet brought to this perfection, but was ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the building, yet <hi>Dauid</hi> knew, <hi>except the Lord build the houſe, they labour in vaine that build it, and except the Lord keepe the Citie, the keeper watches in vaine,</hi> and that many flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Cities and ſtrong Caſtles haue beene made deſolat for the ſinnes of them that dwell in them: and therefore fearing leaſt his ſinne had procured a curſe in Ieruſalem, like the curſe of Iericho, hee praies euen for the externall ſtate thereof.</p>
            <p>But much more may wee
<pb n="273" facs="tcp:177902:147"/> think he had regard to the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual <note place="margin">Ieruſalems ſpirituall walles.</note> wals therof, which his ſin had demoliſhed, and he praies God to repaire againe. The firſt, innermoſt, and ſtrongeſt <note place="margin">1 <hi>Gods prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi>
               </note> wall of Ieruſalem, is the Lords fauourable protection: this is called by <hi>Zacharie</hi> a wall of fire compaſſing Hieruſalem, which wil burne and conſume the enemies that inuade it: the <note place="margin">2 <hi>Holines and vnitie.</hi>
               </note> ſecondarie walles are holines and vnitie, for an vnholy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are naked, like the idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous Iſraelites, after their worſhipping of the golden Calfe, and this breach of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe euer procures breach in vnitie among people, &amp; makes a rupture in the wall, whereby the aduerſarie may eaſily get vantage. Now <hi>Dauid</hi> knew
<pb n="274" facs="tcp:177902:148"/> that by his ſinne hee had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured to be depriued of Gods fauour, and that his ſons and ſeruants ſhould rebell againſt him, as he had rebelled againſt the Lord his God: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he craues that theſe euils may bee remoued, his filthie ſinne pardoned, the fauoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble protection of God conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued, and vnity betweene him and his people preſerued<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And this for Ieruſalems wailes.</p>
            <p>Wherof let vs learne what <note place="margin">No enemies can deſtroy the walles of Ieruſalem, only the ſins of inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants.</note> it is that makes the Church a prey to her enemies: what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyes the wals of Ieruſalem: No force, no multitude, no po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie, nor engine of the enemy, only the ſinnes of them who dwell within it. God make vs wiſe to take this to heart, leſt
<pb n="275" facs="tcp:177902:148"/> our ſinnes make a breach in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalems walles.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>VERSE. 19.</bibl>
               <q>Then ſhalt thou accept the ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of righteouſneſſe, euen the burnt offering and oblation, then ſhall they offer Calues vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thine Altar.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Is petitions are <note place="margin">An heart to offer praiſe and prayer to the Lord, is an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of mercie.</note> concluded with a promiſe of thankeſ-giuing. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou ſhalt be fauourable to vs, then ſhall we offer, and thou ſhalt accept. Multiplicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> then of ſacrifices is an effect of Gods fauour, to haue a heart rightly ſet to pray
<pb n="276" facs="tcp:177902:149"/> to the Lord, or praiſe him, is an argument of mercie. When God was angrie with Iſrael, he ſent vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Caldeans, who tooke away the daily ſacrifice; but it is an effect of a farre more fearefull wrath, when God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuers vp men to the hardnes of their own hart, ſuffering them ſo to be captiued by Satan, that they can neither repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of their ſins, nor pray for graces which they want, nor yet giue thanks for benefits that they haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued: where the heauens be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come braſſe, and ſend downe no dew: what maruell the earth be like iron, and can ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der no fruit; but if the Lord looke on vs in mercie, as he did on <hi>Peter,</hi> then ſhall we mourne for our ſinnes, and if hee be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourable
<pb n="277" facs="tcp:177902:149"/> vnto vs, as heere <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> prayes, then ſhall we be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſacrificers of praiſe, and thankes vnto him.</p>
            <p>The order of his wordes <note place="margin">If our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons be not first in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour with God, our actions can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not pleaſe him.</note> makes this cleare vnto vs. When thou ſhalt bee fauoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to vs, then ſhalt thou accept our offerings. Except firſt our perſons be in fauour with God, our actions were they neuer ſo good in ſhew, will not bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to him. Examples hereof wee haue in <hi>Abel</hi> and <hi>Cain,</hi> God looked firſt to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel,</hi> and then had reſpect to his ſacrifice. Let vs therefore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all things haue a care that we may be in fauour with our God, reconciled with him in Chriſt, otherwiſe all our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and oblations whatſoeuer,
<pb n="278" facs="tcp:177902:150"/> are but an abomination to the Lord.</p>
            <p>And laſt of all, we ſee heere <note place="margin">Thankeſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie we muſt diſcharge to the Lord.</note> how the greateſt and moſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>during duetie wee owe vnto God for all his benefites, is thankeſgiuing, hee is content the profit of them all be ours, hee craues no more but praiſe. Wee want not matter for which wee ſhould praiſe him; onely we want affection: and therefore haue we to pray, that the Lord among all the reſt of his great goodneſſe, wherein he is daily abundant toward vs, would alſo bleſſe vs with a thankfull heart, that in this du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie alſo wee may abound to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Lord our God. To whom be praiſe, glorie, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour for euer.</p>
            <pb n="279" facs="tcp:177902:150"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Now vnto the King Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, Euerlasting, Inuiſible: Vnto God onely wiſe be honour and glorie for euer. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
